<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Theanthrōpos or The great mysterie of godlines opened by way of antidote against the great mysterie of iniquity, (now awork in the Romish Church.) In a sound and seasonable treatise; wherein 1. The incarnation of the Son of God (and evangelicall love, wisdome, humility, &amp;c. expressed in that contrivance) is fully explicated and displayed. 2. Ceremonies in poynt of divine worship are concluded to be by Christ (the true Messiah) abrogated; and examined whether they are not since Christ, Jewish-anti-Christian; where the Jew and Judaizing Christian are deservedly taxed. 3. Christian liberty with its VIII steps and V boundaries, is modestly and briefly asserted; and many other matters of consequence and moment are imparted; but now published for vindication of the truth and its assertor. By Thomas Douglas, M.A. minister of the Gospel at Olaves-Silverstreet, in London.</title>
            <author>Douglas, Thomas, fl. 1661.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 196 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36446</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2040</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R212841</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825492</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825492</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29874</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36446)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29874)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2004:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Theanthrōpos or The great mysterie of godlines opened by way of antidote against the great mysterie of iniquity, (now awork in the Romish Church.) In a sound and seasonable treatise; wherein 1. The incarnation of the Son of God (and evangelicall love, wisdome, humility, &amp;c. expressed in that contrivance) is fully explicated and displayed. 2. Ceremonies in poynt of divine worship are concluded to be by Christ (the true Messiah) abrogated; and examined whether they are not since Christ, Jewish-anti-Christian; where the Jew and Judaizing Christian are deservedly taxed. 3. Christian liberty with its VIII steps and V boundaries, is modestly and briefly asserted; and many other matters of consequence and moment are imparted; but now published for vindication of the truth and its assertor. By Thomas Douglas, M.A. minister of the Gospel at Olaves-Silverstreet, in London.</title>
                  <author>Douglas, Thomas, fl. 1661.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 74 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for H.C. in Popes-head Alley, and T.P. against the great Conduit at the lower end of Cheapside,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>ann. Dom. 1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First word of title in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Liberty --  Religious aspects --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29874:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ΘΕΑΝΘΡΩΠΟΣ OR THE Great Myſterie OF GODLINES, Opened By way of <hi>Antidote</hi> againſt The <hi>Great Myſterie</hi> of <hi>Iniquity,</hi> (now a work in the <hi>Romiſh Church.</hi>)</p>
            <p>In a Sound and Seaſonable Treatiſe; WHEREIN 1. The <hi>INCARNATION</hi> of the Son of God (and <hi>Evangelicall Love, Wiſdome, Humility,</hi> &amp;c. expreſſed in that Contrivance) is fully explicated and diſplayed. 2. <hi>CEREMONIES</hi> in Poynt of <hi>Divine Worſhip</hi> are concluded to be by <hi>Chriſt</hi> (the true <hi>Meſſiah</hi>) abrogated; and examined whether they are not ſince <hi>Chriſt, Jewiſh-Anti-Chriſtian;</hi> where the <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Judaizing Chriſtian</hi> are deſervedly taxed. 3. <hi>CHRISTIAN LIBERTY</hi> with its VIII <hi>Steps</hi> and V <hi>Boundaries,</hi> is modeſtly and briefly aſſerted; And Many other Matters of Conſequence and Moment are imparted: But now PUBLISHED For VINDICATION of the Truth and its Aſſertor. By <hi>Thomas Douglas,</hi> M. A. Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Olaves-Silverſtreet,</hi> in LONDON.</p>
            <q>The LAW was given by MOSES, but GRACE and TR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TH came by JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST, <bibl>John 1. 17.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Praeſente <hi>Veritate, Typus</hi> &amp; <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbra</hi> ceſſavit. <bibl>
                  <hi>Origen. in Jeſ. Nave. cap. 13. hom.</hi> 17.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON; Printed for <hi>H. C.</hi> in Popeſ-head Alley, and <hi>T. P.</hi> againſt the great Conduit at the lower end of <hi>Cheapſide. Ann. Dom.</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:29874:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29874:2"/>
            <head>An Epiſtle PREMONITORY <hi>To the</hi> JUDICIOUS And Impartial <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy <hi>Reader,</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>E pleaſed to know, that I once intended an Epiſtle <hi>Reprehenſory</hi> to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Church,</hi> the <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh</hi> Mother of THE MY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STERIE of INIQ<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ITY (for there it was <hi>Born</hi> though her Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaical Emiſſaries would <hi>compaſs Sea and Land,</hi> that it might be elſe-where <hi>Nurſed</hi>)
<pb facs="tcp:29874:3"/> but upon more mature thoughts, I conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be at the expence of no more then this Epiſtle <hi>Premonitory;</hi> whoſe Scope and Errand is to acquaint the World with the <hi>Occaſion</hi> of this (my firſt) appearance in <hi>Print.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am now by Perſonal Experience ſchooled in the Truth of that, <hi>Veritas odium parit.</hi> Never was there an Age, wherein TR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TH had more <hi>Daughters,</hi> and fewer <hi>Siſters;</hi> But the miſery is, the <hi>Brood</hi> is ILLEGITIMATE, and HETEROGENEAL.</p>
            <p>I was about two moneths ago <hi>brought to Pulpit</hi> of ſome honest <hi>Truths</hi> (ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Text, as that was to the Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) which were CONCEIVED (I hope) by a DIVINE (though now ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitated to a (Printed) <hi>Sheet</hi> by a MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIGNANT) <hi>Influence.</hi> And though (the Lord knows) my Diſcourſe was all along levelled and commenſurated (as neer as I could) by the Neceſſary <hi>Lawes</hi> of <hi>1. Piety,</hi> in reſpect of my <hi>God. 2. Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty</hi> in reſpect of my <hi>King;</hi> and <hi>3. Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:29874:3"/> in reſpect of my <hi>Neighbour;</hi> Yet have (innocent) I, been ſince, in ſuch a<note place="margin">O how ſad is it, when what is ſaid for Antidoting of <hi>Superſtition</hi> is preſently conſtrued to be (at leaſt) <hi>Sedition!</hi>
               </note> horrid manner, by ſome (whom God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give) cenſured, condemned, calumniated, and miſ-repreſented (what their ground was, let the Impartial judge) as that (fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lest <hi>Silence</hi> might be Interpreted <hi>Guilt,</hi> a pleaſing <hi>Gloſs,</hi> in ſuch a caſe, to <hi>Malice)</hi> I concluded, it was needful to Publiſh to the world, what I delivered, (with divers other things) <hi>Innocency</hi> and <hi>Ingenuity,</hi> thoſe Boſome-Solicitors, prompting me on; for VINDICATION.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Hic murus Aheneus eſto,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
            <p>Thus,</p>
            <p>What the Reaſon and End of the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication is, I have ſhewed; That the work is performed no better, let it be imputed to <hi>Mine,</hi> and not to the <hi>Weakneſs</hi> of my <hi>Cauſe,</hi> for that is not <hi>Guilty;</hi> neither let Men make uſe of <hi>Mine</hi> as <hi>Premiſſes</hi> to <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer</hi> other Mens <hi>Weakneſſes.</hi> Alas! I am <hi>leſs then the leaſt</hi> of ten thouſand. No mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel the <hi>Birth</hi> be condemned as <hi>Abortive,</hi> ſince the <hi>Parent</hi> is <hi>one born out of due
<pb facs="tcp:29874:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> time.</hi> I confeſs the Subject had better be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come both <hi>Age</hi> and <hi>Ability;</hi> but though the want of both, (eſpecially of the latter) did encline me to ſtand for a <hi>Mute,</hi> yet the Caſe was ſo urgent, that it preſſed hard for a <hi>Conſonant.</hi> What Cenſures ſoever I ſhall undergo, even while I endeavour to <hi>ſuppreſs</hi> or <hi>prevent</hi> Cenſures, <hi>I</hi> am reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved (through Grace) to be Paſſive under them; Only my Suit is to thee (Worthy Reader) that thou wouldest <hi>1. Forbear</hi> to <hi>Tax</hi> me (further) till thou hast read me through; (and then I hope, thou wilt not <hi>Tax</hi> thy <hi>Forbearance:)</hi> And 2. Pray for him, who is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy Servant <hi>in</hi> and <hi>for</hi> Chriſt, T. D.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:29874:4"/>
         </div>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:29874:5"/>
            <head>Praemonitiuncula.</head>
            <p>LIbenter velim Eruditioribus innote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcat, paſſim in hoc opuſculo Graecum Accentum, perperam collocari, quod partim <hi>Typographo,</hi> vitio vertendum eſt, partim mihi ipſi, utpote qui a teneris uſque, Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calis, Valorcm, magis quam Accentum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicere memet aſſuefecerim; quae Legenti maximopere praemonenda eſſe duxi; ut illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us facilior evadat cenſura; cui, ſi (nihil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ominus) ſteterit MOM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M agere; per me (quidem) licebit.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:29874:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Gal. 4. 4, 5.</bibl>
                  <p>But when the fulneſs of the time was come, God ſent forth his Son, made of a woman, made under the Law.</p>
                  <p>To redeem them that were under the Law, that we might receive the Adoption of ſons.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Apoſtle's deſigne in the Context, is to demonſtrate the Chriſtian Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es Exemption and Redemption from <hi>Legal Rites</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> and her emancipation from a <hi>ſervile</hi> ſtate by the Son of God <hi>Incarnate,</hi> the true <hi>Meſſias.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This he illuſtrates by a plain and familiar <hi>Simile,</hi> taken from the <hi>Civil Law;</hi> the ſum is this. As the <hi>Heir</hi> while he is under age, and in his minority, is ſubject to Tutors, Governours, and Guardians, from which he is freed, when he comes at age, being then <hi>ſui juris,</hi> at his own diſpoſal; even ſo the Church, under her <hi>Legal</hi> Conſtitution, and Minority, was ſubject to the <hi>Moſaical Pedagogie,</hi> and Ceremonial Shaddows, Pigures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as to a School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter, and Rudiments, ſuited to her Infant-State; but <hi>when the fulneſs of the time was come, God ſent forth his Son made of a woman, made under the Law, to redeem them that were under the Law.</hi> So that the Church in her ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and adult age, and under her <hi>Chriſtian</hi> and <hi>Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical</hi> Conſtitution, is by Chriſt, <hi>God-man,</hi> the prefigured Body and Subſtance of <hi>Levitical</hi> ſhaddows, exempted from the ſervile yoke of Jewiſh Rites and Ceremonies. The words then are <hi>Demonſtrative,</hi> and in them there be two general parts, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Chriſt's Perſon.</item>
               <item>2. Chriſt's Portion.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Perſon</hi> of Chriſt, conſidered as our <hi>Mediator,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:29874:6"/> lyeth in theſe words; <hi>But when the fulneſs of the time was come, God ſent forth his Son, made of a woman, made under the Law.</hi> Where there be two great things obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The <hi>Incarnation</hi> of the Son of God.</item>
               <item>2. The <hi>Legal Qualification</hi> of his Perſon.
<list>
                     <item>1. The former, in theſe words; <hi>But when the fulneſs of the time was come, God ſent forth his Son made of a woman.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. The latter, in theſe words; <hi>made under the Law:</hi> whereby is intimated Chriſt's humble (but <note n="*" place="margin">Notat, <hi>Non Obligationem, ſed uſum.</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelm</note> 
                        <hi>voluntary) ſubjection</hi> to the Law; which was threefold.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt was his ſubmiſſion to the <hi>Civil</hi> or <hi>Judicial Law,</hi> the <hi>Jewiſh Policy;</hi> in that he condeſcended to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive his humane Body and Being from the <hi>Jewes,</hi> for the <hi>Jewes</hi> were <hi>the Fathers of whom, as concerning the Fleſh, Chriſt came, Rom.</hi> 9. 5. Chriſt was a <hi>Native Jew,</hi> and therefore ſubject to the <hi>Jewiſh Policy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond was his ſubjection to the <hi>Ceremonial</hi> Law, and thus Chriſt was <hi>Circumciſed,</hi> Luke 2. 21. It was in purſuance of this Law, that Chriſt went up three times in the year to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to wit, at Feſtival Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities; according to that in <hi>Exod. 23. v. 14. Deut. 16. v.</hi> 16. &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third was Chriſt's <hi>Obediential</hi> Conformity to the <hi>Moral</hi> Law, which was two-fold, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Original.</item>
               <item>2. Actual.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. The former was the <hi>Native Righteouſneſs</hi> of Chriſt's <hi>Perſon: Chriſt</hi> is the only Perſon that was <hi>born</hi> holy; <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> was <hi>created</hi> holy, every Believer is in ſanctification made holy; but Chriſt (the immaculate Lamb of God) was <hi>born</hi> holy.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The latter, was Chriſt's <hi>Actual Obedience,</hi> which again was two-fold, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Active.</item>
               <item>2. Paſſive.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:29874:6"/>
            <p n="1">1. That was the <hi>Legal Righteouſneſs</hi> and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of his <hi>Life,</hi> anſwering to the <hi>Active</hi> condition of the Law, <hi>Do this and Live.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. This was Chriſt's <hi>Paſſive</hi> Undertakings in behalf of Mankinde; it implies, his voluntary ſubmiſſion to the <hi>Curſe</hi> and Malediction of the Law, to a <hi>miſerable life,</hi> and an <hi>accurſed death,</hi> to a <hi>Croſs</hi> and a <hi>Curſe</hi> at once, (not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>noſtro bono,</hi> but even <hi>noſtro loco,</hi> in our room; which the <hi>Socinians</hi> deny) in anſwer to the <hi>poenal</hi> demands of a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated Law, and the Threats and Comminations annexed. In a word, the Apoſtle in ſaying Chriſt was <hi>made under the Law,</hi> doth intimate, the Quality and Nature of his Eſtate of <hi>Humiliation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
               </label> This ſhould ſtir us all up to thankful admiration; O the wonderful condeſcention of God, Chriſtians! What? That He who <hi>made</hi> the Law, ſhould be <hi>made under</hi> the Law! That the <hi>Scepter Royal,</hi> and <hi>Legiſlative Power</hi> of Heaven ſhould ſtoop to <hi>Obedience!</hi> Here the <hi>Law-maker</hi> was <hi>made</hi> under the <hi>Law!</hi> Here <hi>God</hi> was <hi>ſubject</hi> to his Subjects Law. This is the only caſe wherein (be it ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with reverence) <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>In forma fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi ſcipſo minor eſt</hi> Aug. de Trin. <hi>lib. 1. cap. 7.</hi>
               </note> God was <hi>ſubject</hi> to <hi>Himſelf;</hi> O Beloved! This is at once matter both of Thankfulneſs and wonder.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Chriſt's <hi>Portion</hi> lyeth in theſe words, <hi>To redeem them that were under the Law, that we might receive the Adoption of ſons.</hi> This was the great deſigne and <hi>Love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plot</hi> of the Son of God in aſſuming to himſelf our Nature; here are ſpecified two great Captial Priviledges accrew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Believers from and by the Son of God <hi>Incarnate, viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Redemption.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Adoption.</hi> Of which hereafter.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Theam that I intend to pitch upon and proſecute, is the <hi>Incarnation</hi> of the Son of God, That <hi>great Myſterie</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3. 16.</note> 
               <hi>of Godlineſs,</hi> the very <hi>Sun-ſhine</hi> of the Goſpel, and all E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelical contrivances, in the Application whereof, I
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:29874:7"/> may very pertinently take into conſideration thoſe ſignal Benefits, <hi>viz. Redemption</hi> and <hi>Adoption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But when the fulneſs of the time was come, God ſent forth his Son, made of a woman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here is aſſerted the <hi>Incarnation</hi> of the Son of God; where we have four Obſervables; <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The <hi>Subject Matter</hi> out of which Chriſt's Body was made.</item>
               <item>2. The <hi>Manner</hi> of the production of it.</item>
               <item>3. The Father's <hi>Commiſſion.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. The Circumſtance of <hi>Time</hi> when, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Subject Matter</hi> out of which Chriſt's Body was made, was the very ſubſtance of the <hi>Virgin Mary,</hi> its <hi>Material</hi> and <hi>Paſſive Principle;</hi> ſhe was the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vox Hebr. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; Gr. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> notant Sexum aeque ac conditionem.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Proco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius.</note> woman mentioned in the Text. <hi>In Virginem introducendum erat Dei Verbum, exſtructorium vitae, ut quod per ejuſmodi Sexum abierat in perditionem, per eundem Sexum redigere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in ſalutem.</hi> Tertul. lib. de Carne Chriſti.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Manner</hi> of the production of Chriſt's Body, is intimated in the word <hi>Made,—Made of a woman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is obſervable that the Son of God is here ſaid to be * <hi>made,</hi> and not<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>non</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Begotten</hi> of a woman. Chriſt as <hi>God</hi> was not <hi>Made</hi> but <hi>Begotten;</hi> Chriſt as <hi>Man,</hi> was not <hi>Begotten,</hi> but <hi>Made.</hi> Nor</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Born</hi> of a woman. <hi>Valentinus, Schwenckfeldius, Marcion,</hi> the primitive <hi>Anabaptiſts, Familiſts,</hi> &amp;c. did grant that Chriſt was <hi>born</hi> of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> but denied that his Body was made of the <hi>Real</hi> ſubſtance of the Virgin; now ſaith our Apoſtle (by the impulſe of the holy Ghoſt) The Son was not (only) <hi>born,</hi> but <hi>made</hi> of a woman.</p>
            <p>In a Word;</p>
            <p>In that the Son of God is here ſaid (not to be <hi>begotten,</hi> nor to be <hi>born,</hi> but) to be <hi>made of a woman;</hi> we may ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, That</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:29874:7"/>
            <p n="1">1. Chriſt's Body was a <hi>Real</hi> Body, and a true <hi>Corporeal</hi> ſubſtance, and not a meer <hi>Phantaſme,</hi> or <hi>Imaginary</hi> Body, as <hi>Marcion,</hi> and after him the <hi>Manichees</hi> did affirm; the firſt Author of which Hereſie was <hi>Cerdo,</hi> ſaith <note n="*" place="margin">Tom. 6. lib. de haereſ.</note> S. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. This Real Body was made of the very <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Corporeal</hi> ſubſtance of the Virgin <hi>Mary;</hi> and not a <hi>Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtial, Sydereal,</hi> or <hi>Elementary</hi> ſubſtance, conveyed into the world, <hi>modo tranſmeatorio,</hi> through the Virgins <hi>womb</hi> or Belly, <hi>tanquam per canalem</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Si</hi> Maria <hi>non filium ſed ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitem in utero geſtabat</hi> Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum, <hi>quomodo dixit</hi> Elizabetha, Beatus fructus Uteri tui? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Tertul. <hi>lib. de</hi> Carne Chriſti.</note> 
               <hi>vel hoſpitium,</hi> as through a <hi>channel</hi> or <hi>heſpitage, per Virginem, non, ex Virgine;</hi> as the <hi>Valentinians</hi> and <hi>Schwenckfeldians</hi> vainly conceit.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Excluditur concurſus Maris;</hi> the concurrence of the <hi>Male</hi> Sex, and by conſequence, <hi>Natural Generation,</hi> and <hi>ſinful propagation</hi> is excluded. Chriſt was <hi>ab Adamo,</hi> but not <hi>per Adamum.</hi> As <hi>ſin</hi> and <hi>miſery</hi> came by a <hi>Woman,</hi> made of a <hi>Man,</hi> without a <hi>Mother;</hi> ſo <hi>happineſs</hi> and <hi>ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> came by a <hi>Man,</hi> made of a <hi>Woman</hi> without a <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Eve</hi> was from <hi>Adam</hi> without a <hi>Mother; Chriſt</hi> came of <note n="*" place="margin">Therefore <hi>Mary</hi> is truly defined to be <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and <hi>Dei para.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Mary</hi> without a (Natural) <hi>Father.</hi> So that damnable was the opinion of <hi>Ebion,</hi> viz. That the Body of Chriſt was procreated of <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s <hi>Seed;</hi> as alſo that of <hi>Helvidius,</hi> viz. That Chriſt was not born of a <hi>Virgin,</hi> he denyed the <hi>Virginity</hi> of the Mother of our Lord.</p>
            <p>The Son of God did aſſume to himſelf the <hi>Nature</hi> of<note place="margin">Aſſumpſit De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us naturam peccatorum, non naturam pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricem.</note> 
               <hi>Sinners,</hi> (but) not a <hi>ſinful</hi> Nature. The Corporeal ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance which he took to him, was <hi>free</hi> from all <hi>impurity,</hi> and <hi>corrupted Qualities,</hi> by the <hi>omnipotent</hi> vertue of the <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt,</hi> the <hi>Active</hi> Principle, (as <hi>Aquinas</hi>) and Efficient Cauſe thereof; by the <hi>Preparatory</hi> Acts of whoſe <hi>purifying</hi> and ſanctifying power, the <hi>Bodily</hi> ſubſtance was fitted for <hi>Perſonal <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> with the <hi>God-head:</hi> for the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Damaſcen.</hi> lib. 3. <hi>Orthodoxa Fidei,</hi> cap. 2.</note> 
               <hi>holy Ghoſt</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:29874:8"/> did come upon the bleſſed Virgin, and <hi>the Power of the Higheſt did over-ſhaddow her;</hi> Luke 1. 35. And thus we profeſſedly believe that Chriſt was <hi>conceived of the holy Ghoſt,</hi> viz. not as a <hi>Material</hi> cauſe, but as a <hi>ſupernatural Effective</hi> and <hi>ſanctifying Cauſe; non de ſubſtantia, ſed de po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia; non generatione, ſed fuſſione, &amp; benedictione.</hi> Aug. Serm. 6. <hi>de Tempore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that Chriſt's <hi>Conception</hi> in the womb of the Virgin, was without all exception <hi>pure</hi> and <hi>immaculate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Father's <hi>Commiſſion</hi> is ſpecified in theſe words, <hi>God ſent forth his Son;</hi> This is the <hi>Authority</hi> of the Son's undertaking, it is no leſs then that of Heaven, and the bleſſed <hi>Trinity;</hi> He did not aſſume our Nature without a ſpecial Commiſſion: Which may condemn thoſe that <hi>run</hi> when they are not <hi>ſent</hi> forth into the great work of the Miniſtery, and irregular engaging therein. The Son of God himſelf came not in the fleſh without a <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> his undertaking was <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Diſpenſatio authentica.</hi> Muſculus <hi>in locum.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Authentique. God ſent forth his Son, &amp;c.</hi> which argues not an <hi>inferiority</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> to the Father, but only a <hi>Voluntary</hi> ſubjection in ſtate and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition;</hi> now an <hi>in-equality</hi> of <hi>condition,</hi> and a <hi>co-equality</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> a <hi>Natural Parity,</hi> and a <hi>Voluntary Diſparity,</hi> are not inconſiſtent.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The circumſtance of <hi>Time,</hi> when the Son of God came in the fleſh, is intimated in theſe words; <hi>When the fulneſs of the time was come,</hi> &amp;c. Where it may be enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, What are we to underſtand by <hi>the fulneſs of the time,</hi> or the full time?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw. Aquinas</hi> notes here a threefold <hi>fulneſs,</hi> viz.<note place="margin">Annus Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nationis eſt Lambardo. Annus benigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatu, lib 3 Sent. Diſt. 1.</note> 1. Of <hi>Grace.</hi> 2. Of <hi>Promiſes.</hi> 3. Of <hi>Types,</hi> and <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal ſhaddows.</hi> In a word.</p>
            <p>By the <hi>fulneſs of the time,</hi> we are to underſtand <hi>tempus praeſinitum a Patre,</hi> (ſay the <note n="*" place="margin">Ambroſe. Carnel. a lap. Eſtius. Luther. Calvin.</note> Learned) <hi>the time appointed of the Father,</hi> (as it is in <hi>v.</hi> 2.) and <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Divina ordinatione non fatali neceſſitate.</hi> Aquin.</note> infallibly deſtined
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:29874:8"/> for the <hi>manifeſtation</hi> of his <hi>Son</hi> in the fleſh, and the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption</hi> of his <hi>Church</hi> from the <hi>Legal yoke</hi> and <hi>bondage</hi> of <hi>Jewiſh Rites</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> by <hi>Him,</hi> of whom <hi>theſe</hi> were <hi>Typical Shaddows</hi> and <hi>Adumbrations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>fulneſs of time,</hi> notes the accompliſhment of all <hi>Prophetical Predictions</hi> and <hi>Promiſes</hi> of the coming of the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> and the <hi>abrogation</hi> of all <hi>Legal ſhaddows</hi> and <hi>Figures</hi> whereby he was typified.</p>
            <p>But more particularly, for our more diſtinct knowledge, of what is meant by the <hi>fulneſs of the time.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>The Son of God did take upon him our Nature,</q>
            <p n="1">1. A little before the end of <hi>Daniel</hi>'s ſeventy weeks, mentioned <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. 24, 25. which contain from the end of the <hi>Babyloniſh Captivity</hi> till the death of Chriſt, (as is <hi>una voce</hi> granted by Chronologers) <hi>four hundred and nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years.</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">De Incarnat. lib, 2. Quaeſt. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Zanchy</hi> is of opinion, that about the ſpace of <hi>thirty</hi> and <hi>three years</hi> (the time of Chriſt's bodily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moration in the world) before the end of the ſeventy weeks, the Son of God came in the fleſh. I confeſs it were the more remarkable, if <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Daniel's</hi> ſeventy weeks did both expire together.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Under the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> which was the <hi>fourth Monarchy,</hi> mentioned <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. In the time of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus Caeſar,</hi> Chriſt was born in the 42<hi rend="sup">d</hi> yeer of his Reigne, ſay <hi>Epiphanius</hi> and <hi>Euſebius;</hi> in the 41ſt, ſay <hi>Tertullian</hi> and <hi>Irenaeus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Three thouſand</hi> and <hi>nine hundred yeers</hi> from the Creation of the World; this is undoubted: but what the particular yeer of the <hi>Incarnation</hi> of the Son of God was, is variouſly reſolved upon by <note n="*" place="margin">Bullinger. ann. 3970. Funccius, ann. 3965. Melanchthon ann. 3965. Luther, ann. 3960. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Chronologers;</hi> but <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chron.</hi> Genevae <hi>Edit. Anno Chriſti 1575. lib. 3. cap. 7. &amp; 8. Notus Chriſtus anno Mundi 2929. Aequinoct. Autumnali, ab <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbe condita, anno. 752. anno 4. Olympiad.</hi> 194. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Bero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aldus</hi> his computation is moſt received, as the exacteſt of all. According to his Calculation, Chriſt was born in the yeer of the World 3929. in the yeer of <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:29874:9"/> his Reign 42. in the yeer of <hi>Herod</hi>'s Reign 33. at or about the <hi>Autumnal Equinoctial,</hi> &amp;c. This was (according to him) the <hi>fulneſs of the time</hi> mentioned in the Text; even the ſet and predeſtinated time of the <hi>Manifeſtation</hi> of the Son of God in the fleſh, and the Churches <hi>Immunity</hi> and Exemption from a <hi>ſervile</hi>-ſtate by and through him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> But why did the Son of God come in the fleſh at that time of all others? Why not ſooner? Why not later?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is a curious Queſtion; (<hi>Hidden things belong unto God,</hi>) but were we to reſolve it, we could aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne no other reaſon for it, then To <hi>Velle Divinum,</hi> the abſolute <hi>good pleaſure</hi> of the All-wiſe God, who in his great wiſdom, pitched upon this ſeaſon as moſt proper and convenient for the manifeſtation of his Son to the World in our Nature. Men can but admire the Wiſdome of God in this <hi>Circumſtance,</hi> as well as in the <hi>thing.</hi> From <hi>Aquinas</hi> we may reverence the Wiſdome of God in this in two reſpects. 1. <hi>Chriſt</hi> was a great perſon, (though he came not in great State) the <hi>King</hi> of Saints, the <hi>Soveraigne Majeſty</hi> of Heaven, (though he came not into the World in <hi>Majeſty</hi>) therefore it was fit that ſome preparation (of ſome thouſands of yeers) ſhould be made for his coming into the world, eſpecially in the hearts of the <hi>little World.</hi> 2. Chriſt was a <hi>Phyſician,</hi> the Phyſician of ſouls, therefore it was fit that his coming ſhould be deferr'd for ſome thouſands of yeers after his <hi>Patients</hi> indiſpenſable need of him; that ſo, though his <hi>Merits</hi> were of perfect vertue and efficacy for the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of believing ſinners, from the beginning of the world, yet) they might inſatiably long after even his <hi>Bodily</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, and ineſtimably prize him when come. The <hi>Old-Teſtament</hi> Saints might have come to this, <hi>O that the Deliverer</hi> were come out of <hi>Zion!</hi> O that our <hi>Phyſitian</hi> were once come! When ſhall the promiſed <hi>Seed of the woman</hi> come? O how acceptably did the Son of God
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:29874:9"/> appear in a <hi>Body</hi> in the <note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 1. 2.</note> 
               <hi>laſt dayes,</hi> to the ſinful, undone, captive ſons of men.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>De Incarnat.</hi> lib. 2. <hi>Quaeſt. 6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Zanchy</hi> after many pious and ſolid reaſons given for the conveniency and ſeaſonableneſs of the fulneſs of the time for the Son's aſſumption of our Nature, doth well obſerve, That this was, of all others, the fitteſt ſeaſon for God's producing to the world at once two moſt ſignal inſtances, <hi>viz.</hi> of <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Mercy:</hi> Of <hi>Juſtice</hi> towards the rebellious and unbelieving <hi>Jewes,</hi> (once God's pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar people) in <hi>rejecting</hi> of them: Of <hi>Mercy</hi> towards the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> in <hi>electing</hi> and making choice of them for his <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church; and in <note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 9. 27. <hi>Hic (Ieſus) in noviſſimis tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poribus apparens, lapis ſummus angularis, in unum collegit, &amp; univit, eos qui longe &amp; eos qui prope, hoc eſt circumciſionem &amp; praeputium, dilatans Japhet, conſtituens eum in domo Sem.</hi> Iren. adver. Haereſ. lib. 1.</note> 
               <hi>perſwading Japhet to dwell in the Tents of Shem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O the profound depth of the Wiſdome of God! How unſearchable are his judgements? His wayes paſt finding out.</p>
            <p>Thus the words of the Text have been in a Theologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal manner divided and opened.—<hi>When the fulneſs of the time was come, God ſent forth his Son, made of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the words, this great Evangelical <hi>Truth</hi> lyeth clear, <hi>viz.</hi> That</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <hi>Doctr. Dominus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in noviſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus tempori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus venit ad nos, non quemadmodum ipſe poterat, ſed quomodo illum videre nos poteramus.</hi> Iren. adverſ. haereſes, <hi>lib. 4.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>The Son of God was in the fulneſs of the time,</hi> (viz. ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen hundred and ſixty yeers ago) <hi>according to the deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate and infallible counſel of God's Will, made of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the proſecution of my intended Diſcourſe, this ſhall<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> be my method. 1. I ſhall firſt diſcover what is compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended under that, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Son of God was <hi>made
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:29874:10"/> of a woman.</hi> 2. I ſhall next prove, <hi>That the Son of God was made of a woman,</hi> and that <hi>in the fulneſs of the time.</hi> 3. I ſhall in the third place alleadge the principal <hi>Reaſons</hi> why <hi>the Son of God was made of a woman.</hi> And 4. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I ſhall endeavour to bring this down to Uſe and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication.</p>
            <p>1. As touching the firſt.</p>
            <p>The import of that, <hi>viz. That the Son of God was made of a woman,</hi> is very comprehenſive; for this is the great <hi>Goſpel-Myſterie</hi> of the <hi>Incarnation,</hi> wherein the <hi>Son</hi> of God did <hi>aſſume</hi> to himſelf the <hi>Humane Nature,</hi> and ſo became <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>God-man</hi> in <hi>one Perſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Aſſumption</hi> of our Nature, conſidered in a full Extent and Latitude, may be underſtood to comprehend under it two memorable things. <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion.</item>
               <item>2. Communion.</item>
            </list>
            <p>1. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion.</p>
            <p>There is a <hi>Hypoſtatical</hi> and <hi>Perſonal <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> between the <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Humane</hi> Natures in <hi>Chriſt.</hi> The <hi>Son</hi> of God, though for <hi>Nature,</hi> Co-eſſential; for <hi>Dignity</hi> Co-equal; for <hi>Time,</hi> Co-eternal with the <hi>Father;</hi> did notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſſume the <hi>Human Nature</hi> into a <hi>Perſonal <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> with the <hi>God head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Perſonal <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> is the moſt intimate <hi>Conjunction</hi> of the <hi>Man-hood</hi> with the <hi>God-head</hi> in <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Dam. <hi>lib. 3. cap. 2.</hi>
               </note> Chriſt, wherein thoſe <hi>two whole perfect</hi> and <hi>diſtinct</hi> Natures are without 1. <hi>Converſion</hi> of the one into the other; Or 2. <hi>Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition</hi> of a <hi>Third</hi> by <hi>both;</hi> Or 3. <hi>Confuſion</hi> and mixture, <hi>inſeparably</hi> conjoyned in <hi>one Perſon;</hi> which <hi>Perſon</hi> is <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>id.</hi> Cum legitur, <hi>Verbum caro factum eſt,</hi> in <hi>verbo</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligo verum Dei filium; in <hi>carne</hi> agnoſco verum hominis filium, &amp; utrumque ſimul, unam perſonam, <hi>&amp;c. Aug. de Trin. lib. 13.</hi>
               </note> very <hi>God,</hi> and very <hi>Man,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,) yet (but) <hi>one Chriſt,</hi> the only <hi>Mediatour</hi> between God and Man.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:29874:10"/>
            <p>The two Natures of Chriſt are united,</p>
            <p n="1">1. * <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, without any <hi>change</hi> or mutation in the<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Dam. <hi>Aſſumpſit (fili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us) carnem, non ſe conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit in carnem,</hi> Aug. <hi>Verbum caro factum eſt, non in carnem mutatum, ut non deſiſteret eſſe quod erat, ſed caperit eſſe quod non erat.</hi> Id. Dial. ad. Oroſium.</note> 
               <hi>Divine</hi> Nature, or <hi>converſion</hi> of the one Nature into the other; and therefore damnable was the opinion of <hi>Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linaris,</hi> who ſtuck not to affirm a kinde of alteration in the <hi>Divine</hi> Nature.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, without <hi>Diviſion;</hi> contrary to <hi>Neſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acceſſit Deo hum ana ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantia non perſona.</hi> Fulg.</note> who alledged (not a <hi>diſtinction,</hi> but) a <hi>diviſion</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the two Natures of Chriſt, attributing to each Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture its proper <hi>hypoſtaſis;</hi> and ſo obtruded to the world an Union of <hi>Perſons,</hi> inſtead of a <hi>Perſonal</hi> Union; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, non <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; a <hi>Social,</hi> not a <hi>Perſonal</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Neſtorian</hi> hereſie was anathematized by the firſt<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Juſtin. <hi>Imper. conteſſ. Rectae Fidei.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Epheſin</hi> Council, under <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the younger, and <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtine</hi> the firſt, whereof <hi>Cyril</hi> was Preſident, <hi>anno Chriſti</hi> 430.</p>
            <p>There is in Chriſt <hi>Aliud &amp; Aliud,</hi> but not <hi>Alius &amp; Alius;</hi> two <hi>Natures,</hi> but <hi>one</hi> Individual <hi>Perſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, without <hi>confuſion</hi> and mixture, or a <hi>compoſition</hi> of a <hi>Third</hi> Nature by both; Chriſt's two Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures remain ſtill <hi>diſtinct</hi> by their ſeveral <hi>Eſſential Propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eties,</hi> contrary to <hi>Eutyches,</hi> and (after him) <hi>Dioſcorus,</hi> who alleadged a <hi>mixture</hi> in the two Natures; ſo that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to them, <hi>Chriſt</hi> is a <hi>compound</hi> made up of the <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Humane</hi> Natures <hi>intermixed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Eutychian</hi> hereſie was anathematized by the Council of <hi>Chalcedon</hi> (which was the fourth <hi>cecumenical</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Dam. <hi>lib. 3. cap.</hi> 3. vid. Dam, <hi>lib. 3. cap. 2.</hi>
               </note> Council) <hi>Act.</hi> 5. under <hi>Martian</hi> and <hi>Leo</hi> the firſt, <hi>anno Dom.</hi> 451.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:29874:11"/>
            <p n="4">4. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Inſeparably.</hi> Chriſt's two Natures are <hi>indiſſolubly</hi> conjoyned. The <hi>Perſonal <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> is a <hi>Perpetual <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion.</hi> That Nature (Chriſtians) which the Son of God did ſixteen hundred yeers ago, aſſume into <hi>Hypoſtatical</hi> Union with the God-head, is by an <hi>everlaſting</hi> conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on united to him. And certainly this will be matter of everlaſting joy and wonder, to the <hi>conſanguinal</hi> Saints in Heaven.</p>
            <p>This is the Nature of the <hi>Perſonal <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> of the <hi>Deity</hi> and <hi>Humanity</hi> in Chriſt. <hi>Super hac re,</hi> vid. <hi>Symb. Antioch. Nicen. Conſtantinop. Athan. Chaleed. Act. 5. &amp; Dam. lib. 3. cap.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>From this <hi>Perſonal <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> of the <hi>Humane</hi> with the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine</hi> Nature in Chriſt, follows 1. <hi>A Mutual Communion of Proprieties,</hi> wherein what is proper to either of the <hi>Natures,</hi> is attributed to the whole <hi>Perſon;</hi> as in theſe Scriptures, <hi>No man hath aſcended up to heaven, but he that came down from heaven, even the Son of man which is in heaven.</hi> John 3. 13. <hi>The Church hath God purchaſed with his own blood.</hi> Acts 20. 28. <hi>God will judge the world by that man whom he hath ordained.</hi> Acts 17. 31. and ſuch like. 2. The <hi>Excellency</hi> of the <hi>Humane</hi> Nature, both in reſpect of the <hi>gifts,</hi> (as <hi>Wiſdome, Knowledge, Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> &amp;c.) with which he was qualified for his <hi>Mediatorſhip;</hi> and the <hi>honour</hi> and adoration due unto it by vertue of its Union with the <hi>God-head.</hi> 3. The <hi>Concurrence</hi> of both Natures, <hi>in operibus Theandricis,</hi> in the works which Chriſt produceth as <hi>God-Man,</hi> wherein both Natures co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>operate; each Nature contributing its <hi>own.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. Communion.</p>
            <p>There is a threefold <hi>Communion</hi> between <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Mankinde,</hi> viz.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>A Communion</hi> of <hi>Natures.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>A Communion</hi> of <hi>Properties.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>A Communion</hi> of <hi>Infirmities.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. There is a <hi>Mutual Communion</hi> of <hi>Natures</hi> and <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:29874:11"/> Parts</hi> between Chriſt and Man. The <hi>Son</hi> of God did aſſume to himſelf, the true <hi>Eſſentials</hi> of <hi>Man,</hi> viz. <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Symb. Chalced. Act. 5.</hi>
               </note> The Entire ſubſtance of a <hi>Real Body,</hi> and a <hi>Reaſonable Soul,</hi> the <hi>very</hi> Humane Nature; ſo that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is <hi>Conſubſtantial</hi> with <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> as well as with the <hi>Father.</hi>
               <note place="margin">* <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Symb. Chalced. ibid.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>This is a Communion of Eſſential Parts.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is between Chriſt and Mankinde a <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> of <hi>Eſſential Properties;</hi> the Son of God did aſſume the <hi>Powers</hi> of <hi>Life, Senſe, Motion;</hi> the Faculties of <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Will,</hi> and <hi>Affection;</hi> a <hi>Body</hi> with its juſt <hi>Quantity</hi> and <hi>Trin-dimenſion;</hi> even all the <hi>Natural</hi> Properties of <hi>Man,</hi> conſidered as a <hi>Corporeal, Animal, Senſitive, Reaſonable</hi> Creature.</p>
            <p n="3">3. There is between Chriſt and Mankinde a <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Infirmities:</hi> The Son of God did aſſume not only our <hi>Natures</hi> and Eſſential <hi>Properties,</hi> but alſo our <hi>Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> viz.</p>
            <p>1. Natural.</p>
            <p>Not <hi>Perſonal</hi> Infirmities; <hi>Thoſe</hi> were ſuch as do ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally accompany the Humane Nature, as its <hi>common</hi> At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants ſince Man's fall and prevarication from his Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Integrity; and they were of two ſorts; <hi>viz. 1. Body-Infirmities;</hi> as <hi>heat, cold, hunger, thirſt, ſleep,</hi> &amp;c. 2. <hi>Soul-Infirmities;</hi> as <hi>grief, anguiſh</hi> and <hi>ſorrow, fear, ignorance,</hi> &amp;c. (I mean <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ignorantia pura Negatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis. Non ignoravit aliquid priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive quod tenebatur ſcire, ſed neſcivit negative, abſque peccato, quod aetati</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>conditioni non competebat.</hi> Dr. <hi>Prideaux Manuduct. ad Theol. Polem. loc.</hi> 3. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Dam. lib. 3. cap. 21.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Negative Ignorance;</hi> that was ignorance (not of that which he ought <hi>ex officio</hi> to have known; but of that which was not congruous for him <hi>quoad ſtatum,</hi> according to his condition to know; and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:29874:12"/> thus Chriſt is ſaid to be ignorant of the particular <hi>day</hi> and <hi>hour</hi> wherein he himſelf is to come to judge the world, (<hi>Mark</hi> 13. 32.)</p>
            <p>Theſe, and ſuch like infirmities did the Son of God take upon him, but not Mens <hi>Perſonal</hi> infirmities, as <hi>blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, lameneſs, dropſies, gouts, conſumptions,</hi> &amp;c. which are not <hi>univerſal,</hi> or neceſſary concomitants of the Humane Nature, but attend upon <hi>Perſons,</hi> rather then upon the <hi>Nature,</hi> and proceed from ſome particular cauſes, as the <hi>malignity</hi> of the <hi>Conſtitution,</hi> the <hi>inequality</hi> of the <hi>Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rament,</hi> the <hi>predominancy</hi> of ſome <hi>corrupted humour,</hi> or ſuch like, not incident to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>2. <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſtus ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milu ſuit carni noſtra pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trici n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n in culpa ſed in p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>na.</hi> Lombar. Sent. lib. 3. diſt. 3. lit. D.</p>
                  <p>Infirmitates miſerabiles, non damnabiles, poenales, non Peccatrices. <hi>Dr. Prid. Montidust. ad Theol. Polem. loc. 3. Infirmitates merae privationis, non pravae diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> Penal.</p>
            <p>Not <hi>ſinful</hi> infirmities; Chriſt's infirmities were <hi>miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable,</hi> but not <hi>damnable;</hi> the infirmities of <hi>ſinners,</hi> but not the infirmity of <hi>ſin;</hi> which is not only an <hi>imperfection,</hi> but an <hi>infection;</hi> now <hi>Chriſt</hi> was the <hi>holy</hi> and <hi>juſt One,</hi> free from all (both) <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Perſonal</hi> guilt.</p>
            <p>Chriſt was by way of <hi>Paſſion</hi> here on earth (as he is now by way of <hi>compaſſion</hi> in heaven) <hi>touched with the feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our infirmities (yet</hi>) <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Symb. Chalced. <hi>Inter Trinitatem &amp; hominum infirmitatem &amp; iniquitatem, Mediator factus eſt homo, non iniquus, ſed tamen infirmus, ut ex eo quod non iniquus jungeret te Deo, ex quod infirmus, propinquaret tibi.</hi> Aug. Praeſ. in enarrat. 2. Pſal. 29.</note> 
               <hi>without ſin,</hi> Heb. 4. 15. Chriſt did partake of our <hi>infirmities,</hi> but not of our <hi>iniquities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Son of God was <hi>in all things made like unto his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Dam. lib. 3. cap. 20.</hi>
               </note> but <hi>that</hi> wherein (we) his Brethren are <hi>like</hi> unto <hi>Satan.</hi> In a word, Chriſt's <hi>Infirmities</hi> were wholly <hi>incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:29874:12"/>
            <p>2. As to the ſecond thing propoſed;</p>
            <p>That the Son of God was <hi>made of a woman,</hi> and is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready come in the fleſh, is a truth which runs clear in the veins of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> as the great <hi>Theam</hi> thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Word was made fleſh,</hi> John 1. 14. <hi>He was made in the likeneſs of Men, and found in faſhion as a Man,</hi> Phil. 2. 7, 8. <hi>In him dwelleth the fulneſs of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head bodily,</hi> Col. 2. 9. <hi>For as much as the children are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of fleſh and blood, he alſo himſelf likewiſe took part of the ſame,</hi> Heb. 2. 14. <hi>Verily, he took upon him the ſeed of Abraham,</hi> Heb. 2. 16. <hi>He was made of a woman,</hi> Gal. 4. 4. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>From theſe and ſuch like Scripture proofs it is evident, that the Son of God was <hi>made of a woman,</hi> he being the only true <hi>Meſſias</hi> who was promiſed from the beginning, and propheſied to come in our Nature; which yet the incredulous <hi>Jew</hi> will by no means admit of, what is <hi>Goſpel</hi>-teſtimony to him? But</p>
            <p n="2">2. This Truth is alſo clear from the manifeſt accord and conſent of the <hi>Evangeliſt</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Luke</hi> his Hiſtory of the <hi>Nativity</hi> of Chriſt, with the <hi>Prophetical Predictions,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning 1. The <hi>particular Time</hi> of the <hi>Meſſias</hi> his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49. 10. 2. His <hi>Family</hi> and Pedegree, <hi>Jer.</hi> 23. 5. 3. His <hi>Virgin-Mother,</hi> Iſa. 7. 14. 4. His <hi>Country,</hi> Mic. 5. 2. 5. His <hi>Condition,</hi> Iſa. 53. 2. which is apparent to any that compare them together. Yea,</p>
            <p n="3">3. The 1. <hi>Propheſied places</hi> of the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> 1. His <hi>Birth. 2. Education, 3. Teaching. 4. Suffering,</hi> are deſtroyed; and 2. The <hi>propheſied time</hi> of his <hi>coming</hi> is elapſed; <hi>Ergo,</hi> &amp;c. It was propheſied</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Chriſt ſhould be <hi>born</hi> in <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> Mic. 5. 2.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That he ſhould be <hi>brought up</hi> in <hi>Nazareth,</hi> Iſa. 11. 1.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That he ſhould enter into <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> while the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Temple was yet ſtanding, <hi>Hag.</hi> 2. 7. 9. &amp; <hi>Zech.</hi> 9. 9. compared; and in this ſenſe it was ſaid, and verified that the glory of the <hi>ſecond</hi> Temple ſhould exceed the glory of the <hi>firſt</hi> Temple.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:29874:13"/>
            <p n="4">4. And that under the <hi>fourth Monarchy,</hi> Dan. 2. 44. That was the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> which together with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther three, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Syrian, Perſian,</hi> and <hi>Grecian,</hi> were ſubverted by him, the King of Kings, <hi>The Stone out out of the Mountain,</hi> Dan. 2. 45. whoſe Kingdome is firm and everlaſting, and deſtructive to all Kingdoms contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to it.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That <hi>the Scepter ſhould not depart from Judah, nor a Law-giver from between his feet, till Shiloh</hi> (that is, the <hi>Meſſias) came,</hi> Gen. 49. 10. But <hi>Bethlehem, Nazareth, Jeruſalem,</hi> and the <hi>Temple,</hi> are razed and deſtroyed; the <hi>fourth</hi> Monarchy is totally ſubverted; The <hi>Scepter</hi> is wholly taken away and departed from <hi>Judah.</hi> For the better underſtanding whereof we muſt know, that the <hi>Scepter</hi> (that is, the <hi>Jewiſh Form of Government</hi>) conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued until the time of <hi>Herod</hi> the <hi>Aſcalonite</hi> (an <hi>Idumean</hi>)<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> Joſeph. Antiqu. <hi>lib. 14.</hi>
               </note> a <hi>Proſelyte-Jew,</hi> who began to reigne in <hi>Judea</hi> about <hi>thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> and <hi>three</hi> yeers before the Nativity of our Saviour, being created <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Jury</hi> by the <hi>Roman</hi> Senate; He in the <hi>thirtieth</hi> yeer of his Reigne, ſlew the <hi>Jewiſh San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hedrin,</hi> (a Convocation in whom did reſide the Legiſlative pre-eminence) and ſo deprived the <hi>Jewes</hi> of the <hi>Scepter</hi> and Principality, and defaced their <hi>Government,</hi> (which was afterwards at the deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> with all their Fundamental Lawes, and Civil Cuſtomes, and Rites, <hi>utterly</hi> aboliſhed, inſomuch that there remained no form nor face of a <hi>Commonwealth</hi> at all among them, as before.) Now near upon this time, <hi>Shiloh</hi> (that is, the <hi>Meſſiah</hi>) came, being lineally deſcended of the Royal Tribe of <hi>Judah;</hi> Ergo, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Nay,</p>
            <p n="4">4. Not only <hi>Prophetical Predictions</hi> concerning the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> but even the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> his <hi>own</hi> Predictions are fulfilled. O that the poor <hi>Jew</hi> would hearken to this! Had I to do with a <hi>Jewiſh Synagogue,</hi> I ſhould hope (through ſtrength from the Almighty) to urge this Argument with good ſucceſs; not only <hi>Propheſies concerning Chriſt,</hi> but
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:29874:13"/> 
               <hi>Chriſt's own</hi> Propheſies and <hi>Perſonal</hi> Predictions are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed. What? Did he not in the dayes of his<note place="margin">Matth. 24. 2. Luk. 19. 43, 44.</note> fleſh propheſie concerning the <hi>Temple,</hi> That <hi>there ſhould not be left one ſtone upon another, which ſhould not be thrown down?</hi> And did he not foretel with tears in his eyes, the future <hi>deſolation</hi> and <hi>depopulation</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem? O Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, Jeruſalem!</hi> &amp;c.—<hi>Behold your houſe is left unto you deſolate.</hi> And was not this accordingly fulfilled not long after? It was accompliſhed ſome <hi>forty</hi> yeers after Chriſt's <hi>Aſcention</hi> by <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> the Emperour, and his Son <hi>Titus,</hi> ſay <hi>Euſebius</hi> and <hi>Joſephus.</hi> It is a ſtrange thing to me (but that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief</hi> is become <hi>Penal,</hi> a <hi>curſe</hi> as well as a <hi>ſin</hi>) that the <hi>Jewes</hi> are not convinced from the very (<hi>vocally-ſilent) Ruines</hi> of their <hi>Temple</hi> and <hi>Metropolis.</hi> Oh Lord convince them!</p>
            <p>3. As touching the third thing propoſed, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Reaſons</hi> why the Son of God did take upon him our Nature.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Prime Impulſive cauſe</hi> hereof was, a Principle<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> of <hi>free</hi> and infinite <hi>Love.</hi> That <hi>Intrinſecal</hi> Motive, and <hi>Primum Mobile</hi> of all Evangelical Contrivances. The <hi>Aſſumption</hi> of our <hi>Nature</hi> into <hi>Perſonal <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> with the <hi>God-head,</hi> was the prime piece of God's gracious deſigne and <hi>Love-plot</hi> concerning ſinners. The Son of God was induced thereunto <hi>ab intra,</hi> from an <hi>impulſe</hi> of <hi>Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Love;</hi> By this the whole <hi>Trinity</hi> was (as it were) <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-powered. God ſo loved the world, that he gave his only begotten Son,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>John 3. 16. Love</hi> was <hi>Mightier</hi> then the <hi>All-mighty:</hi> Here <hi>God</hi> was his <hi>own Captive;</hi> (be it ſpoken with reverence.) Sure, there was a ſtrange <hi>Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency</hi> in <hi>Love.</hi> O wonderful <hi>Love!</hi> The moſt powerful <hi>Motive</hi> with God in <hi>God!</hi> The Project of Man's ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was a <hi>Love-plot;</hi> It was laid in Love; It was carried on in Love, It was accompliſhed in Love: The Son of God did out of <hi>Love</hi> to our <hi>Perſons</hi> aſſume our <hi>Natures.</hi> The <hi>Incarnation</hi> was purely the Product of Infinite <hi>Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction;</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:29874:14"/> That then which moved the Son of God to cloath the <hi>Deity</hi> with <hi>fleſh</hi> and <hi>blood</hi> (as I may expreſs it) and to take upon him our Nature, was not 1. Any <hi>Meritorious Qualification</hi> in <hi>Man;</hi> O no! We could as ſoon have merited <hi>Salvation</hi> as a <hi>Saviour,</hi> and ſo there had been no need of <hi>God-Incarnate.</hi> Nor was it 2. Any <hi>Created Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency;</hi> O no! So <hi>Angels</hi> had been <hi>Gainers,</hi> and <hi>Men</hi> irrecoverably <hi>Loſers;</hi> whereas (admired be rich Grace) <hi>God took not upon him the Nature of Angels, but the Seed of Abraham,</hi> Heb. 2. 16. But it was purely an Internal Principle of <hi>free, boundleſs,</hi> and <hi>illimited Love.</hi> This (Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved) is a Reaſon far above <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. A ſecond Reaſon why the Son of God was <hi>made of a woman,</hi> may be drawn from</p>
            <p>The Nature of Chriſt's <hi>Mediatory Office.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was proper and requiſite that the Son of God <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking</hi> the Office of <hi>Surety</hi> and <hi>Mediatorſhip</hi> between <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man,</hi> ſhould <hi>partake</hi> of <hi>both</hi> Natures; the <hi>Humane</hi> as well as the <hi>Divine,</hi> and ſo become <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>God-Man,</hi> elſe he had not been duely qualified thereunto; Hence <hi>Chriſt</hi> is a <hi>Mediator,</hi> not only <hi>qua Medians,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of <hi>Office;</hi> but alſo <hi>qua Medius,</hi> in reſpect of the <hi>Concurrence</hi> of the <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Humane</hi> Natures in Him. Chriſt as he is <hi>God,</hi> bears a Proportion to his Fathers <hi>Majeſty;</hi> In Chriſt as he is <hi>Man,</hi> there is a propinquity to our <hi>Meanneſs.</hi> In a word,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nota,</hi> Ter Medius eſt Chriſtus, viz. 1. <hi>In S. Trinitate eſt Media Perſona. 2. Inter Deum &amp; Hominem Medians ex par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Officii. 3. Reſpectu Naturarum, eſt Medius.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Mediator</hi> between <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man,</hi> muſt be both for <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Condition</hi> a <hi>Middle</hi>-Perſon, <hi>Ergo,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A third Reaſon why the Son of God became <hi>Man,</hi> may be taken from</p>
            <p>The <hi>Order</hi> of <hi>Divine Juſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As the Nature of <hi>Divine Juſtice</hi> is ſuch, that God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>ſalva juſtitia</hi> gratifie <hi>ſin</hi> with <hi>impunity,</hi> or ſuffer the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:29874:14"/> leaſt guilt to go unpuniſhed, (for that were <hi>Partiality</hi>) contrary to <hi>Socinus</hi> his ſoul-deceiving-fancy) ſo it requires <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> to be made in the <hi>ſame</hi> Nature wherein the <hi>offence</hi> is committed, and accordingly God doth <hi>puniſh</hi> ſin in the <hi>ſinners Nature.</hi> True it is, God might have given a Commiſſion to an <hi>Angel</hi> to <hi>aſſume</hi> our Nature; yea, and that Angel might have <hi>ſuffered</hi> in our Nature; But an <hi>Incarnate Angel</hi> could never have <hi>ſatisfied</hi> wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Juſtice.</hi> Therefore the Son of God interpoſing as <hi>Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> and <hi>Mediator,</hi> between a <hi>juſt God</hi> and <hi>ſinful Mankinde,</hi> condeſcended to become <hi>Man,</hi> that he might anſwer and <hi>ſatisfie</hi> the ſtricteſt demands of <hi>Impartial Juſtice</hi> in the <hi>ſame</hi> Nature that he came to <hi>ſave.</hi> Had not <hi>Chriſt</hi> been <hi>God,</hi> his <hi>ſufferings</hi> could never have been by <hi>condignity meritoricus;</hi> had he not been <hi>Man,</hi> they could never have been <hi>ſatisfactory</hi> to <hi>Juſtice.</hi> Therefore he became <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>God-Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Laſtly,</p>
            <p>The <hi>Attributes</hi> of God, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Love</hi> of God; The <hi>Goodneſs</hi> and <hi>Mercy</hi> of God; His <hi>Power;</hi> His <hi>Wiſdome,</hi> &amp;c. ſhine clear in the <hi>Incarnation,</hi> as in a Glaſs. Here they concur by way of Eminency, as in the <hi>Trinity's Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece</hi> (ſo to ſpeak) and the very <hi>Flower</hi> of the Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal <hi>Oeconomy.</hi> O how gloriouſly conſpicuous are they here, not only for <hi>kinde,</hi> but even for <hi>Degrees!</hi> Now one thing that the Son of God deſigned in taking upon him our <hi>Natures,</hi> was the <hi>Illuſtration</hi> of the Glory of his <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes.</hi> For theſe Reaſons was the Son of God <hi>made of a woman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any ſhould enquire, What is the Reaſon, why the Son of God was made of a woman <hi>in the fulneſs of the time</hi> (viz. <hi>ſixteen hundred</hi> and <hi>ſixty yeers</hi> ago) rather then at any other time ſooner, or later; This is anſwered before.</p>
            <p>Thus I have fully opened and demonſtrated that Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Concluſion, <hi>viz.</hi> That</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:29874:15"/>
            <q>The Son of God was in the fulneſs of the time, according to the infallible and determinate counſel of God's will, made of a woman.</q>
            <p>Come we now to the laſt thing propoſed, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Application.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. Here is matter of <hi>Wonder</hi> and Admiration, and that fourfold, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. An <hi>Evangelical Myſtery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, The <hi>Incarnation</hi> of the <hi>Son</hi> of God; That<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Great Myſtery of Godlineſs;</hi> What? That <hi>God</hi> ſhould be <hi>made of a woman!</hi> Is not that a Myſterie? That <hi>God</hi> ſhould become <hi>Man!</hi> The <hi>Immortal</hi> God, <hi>Mortal!</hi> That the <hi>Maker</hi> of all things ſhould be <hi>made!</hi> That <hi>God</hi> ſhould be <hi>made</hi> what <hi>He</hi> made!</p>
            <q>God ſent forth his Son made of a woman.</q>
            <p>Here <hi>God</hi> was <hi>made</hi> of her whome <hi>He</hi> made! Here<note place="margin">Iſa. 9. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Maries</hi> Everlaſting <hi>Father</hi> became <hi>Maries Son!</hi> Theſe are <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ddles</hi> to fleſh and blood, Beloved!</p>
            <q>God ſent forth his Son made of a <hi>Virgin!</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Here is <hi>Miraculum in miraculo,</hi> a <hi>Myſterie</hi> in a Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; That the Son of <hi>God</hi> ſhould become the Son of <hi>Man! David's Lord, David's Son!</hi> This was a great Myſterie, a caſe ſo intricate, that it plunged and <hi>non-plusd</hi> the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>Rabbies</hi> among the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> Matth. 22. 42, 43, 44, 45, 46. But</p>
            <p>That the Son of <hi>God</hi> ſhould become the Son of a <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin!</hi> — Here is a <hi>Myſterie</hi> in a Myſterie. That a <hi>Virgin</hi> ſhould become a <hi>Mother!</hi> This was a Thing ſo <hi>Myſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> that <hi>Mary</hi> her ſelf, the <hi>Royal Mother</hi> of our Lord, was a ſtranger to the manner of the accompliſhment of it, <hi>How ſhall this be</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>? ſaid ſhe to the (<hi>Angelical</hi>) Angel, <hi>Luke</hi> 1. 34. So ſtrange, that (as worthy Biſhop <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> notes in his <hi>Emmanuel</hi>) it was propoſed as a ſigne and wonder to Unbelievers, <hi>ſeven hundred</hi> and <hi>forty</hi> yeers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was accompliſhed, <hi>Iſa. 7. 14. Behold, a Virgin ſhall conceive, and bear a Son!</hi> &amp;c. What? For a <hi>Virgin</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:29874:15"/> to <hi>conceive,</hi> and <hi>bear!</hi> &amp;c. O! What <hi>Paradoxes</hi> be theſe? <hi>Angels</hi> wonder, <hi>Devils</hi> tremble at theſe aſtoniſhing <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities.</hi> Finally,</p>
            <p>The <hi>Perſonal <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> of the <hi>Humane</hi> and <hi>Divine</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is a <hi>ſtupendious Myſterie,</hi> (that which S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> did ſo much admire) and a thing which is able to plunge the Celeſtial <hi>Intelligences</hi> themſelves.)</p>
            <p>There be two great <hi>Myſteries,</hi> viz.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>One Nature</hi> in <hi>Three Perſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. <hi>Two Natures</hi> in <hi>One Perſon.</hi> And I dare (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt) be bold to ſay, That</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Three</hi> in <hi>One</hi> in the <hi>B. Trinity,</hi> is not a greater Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, then <hi>Two</hi> in <hi>One</hi> in <hi>Chriſt.</hi> O! Wonder Chriſtians, won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at this <hi>great Myſterie of Godlineſs!</hi> Wonder, That <hi>the Word ſhould be made fleſh!</hi> That <hi>the Son of God ſhould be made of a woman!</hi> I, of a <hi>Virgin!</hi> &amp;c. I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that <hi>This</hi> is, and will be to all eternity, matter of admiration and wonder in <hi>Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. Evangelical Love.</p>
            <p>Here is the moſt <hi>ſignal</hi> Demonſtration of the <hi>Love</hi> of God to Mankinde that is poſſible. What? That the <hi>Son of the Living God</hi> ſhould be <hi>made of a woman!</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Love</hi> may be conſidered in a two-fold reſpect, <hi>viz.</hi> As a</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Superlative</hi> Love, and in its <hi>Dimenſions.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Soparative</hi> and <hi>Diſtinguiſhing</hi> Love.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. This <hi>Love</hi> is <hi>ſuperlative,</hi> and (for <hi>degrees</hi>) tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent.</p>
            <p>Such are the <hi>Dimenſions</hi> of the Love of God, that it is (like <hi>God</hi> Himſelf) <hi>Incomprehenſible;</hi> it <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Eph. 3. 19.</note> 
               <hi>paſſeth know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge:</hi> O the <hi>height, depth, length,</hi> and <hi>breadth</hi> of this <hi>Love!</hi> It is the work of <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Glorified</hi> Saints to admire it. That <hi>God</hi> ſhould <hi>ſend forth his Son made of a woman,</hi> was an <hi>unparallell'd inſtance</hi> of Love. <hi>God SO loved the world, that he gave his only begotten Son into the world,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>John</hi> 3. 16. Note that particle (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) SO,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:29874:16"/> Thereby is intimated, the very <hi>Maximum Quod Sic</hi> of <hi>Love</hi> (and that may be termed without any Derogati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the <hi>Deity</hi>) the very <hi>Maximum Quod Sic</hi> of <hi>Omnipotency:</hi> The <hi>higheſt</hi> pitch and <hi>Degree</hi> of <hi>Love,</hi> that <hi>God</hi> could poſſibly expreſs to <hi>Angels</hi> or <hi>Men.</hi> Such was God's <hi>Love</hi> to Man, that He <hi>gave</hi> the <hi>Son of his Love</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Him; O what a <hi>Mirandum</hi> of <hi>Love</hi> did God exhibite in that <hi>Deed</hi> of <hi>Gift!</hi> The Reſult of God's <hi>Love</hi> to <hi>Man</hi> was <hi>no leſs</hi> then the <hi>great Emmanuel</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 7. 14. Matth. 1. 23.</note>, <hi>God with us!</hi> If ever <hi>God</hi> did (as I may ſay) excel <hi>Himſelf,</hi> it was in this ſame <hi>Love.</hi> Herein the <hi>B. Trinity</hi> is moſt Eminent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Two</hi> of God's <hi>Holy Attributes</hi> were in this <hi>Evangelical Oeconomy</hi> extended to (a <hi>non-ultra</hi>) their <hi>Outmoſt,</hi> (be it ſpoken with reverence) <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Love.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Wiſdome.</hi> (Of the latter of which hereafter.)</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>A greater Love</hi> then that which God did expreſs in the <hi>Aſſumption</hi> of <hi>Our Nature</hi> into <hi>Perſonal <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> with the <hi>God-head,</hi> is (I dare ſay, to the praiſe of rich grace) <hi>ultra poſſe Divinum,</hi> an utter <hi>Impoſſibility</hi> with God; A thing <hi>Impoſſible</hi> to <hi>Omnipotency</hi> it ſelf; <hi>Hoc non poteſt Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotens.</hi> There be two great and ſignal <hi>Loves</hi> of God to Man, obſervable from Scripture, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The <hi>Love</hi> of God, in making <hi>Man</hi> in his <hi>owne likeneſs.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. The <hi>Love</hi> of God in making <hi>Himſelf</hi> in <hi>Man's likeneſs.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>God made <hi>Man</hi> like <hi>Himſelf</hi> in the <hi>firſt</hi> Man, <hi>Adam:</hi> God made <hi>Himſelf</hi> like <hi>Man</hi> in the <hi>ſecond</hi> Adam, <hi>Chriſt.</hi> There <hi>God</hi> was the <hi>Pattern,</hi> and <hi>Man</hi> the <hi>Pourtaicture;</hi> Here <hi>Man</hi> was the <hi>Pattern,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> the <hi>Pourtraicture.</hi> Now Chriſtians, the latter is the <hi>greater</hi> Love. In the former God <hi>communicates</hi> Himſelf to the Creature But it the latter, God doth by an infinite condeſcention aſſume the <hi>Creature</hi> into <hi>Perſonal <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> with the <hi>Deity.</hi> That <hi>God</hi> ſhould <hi>take</hi> upon Him the <hi>Humane Nature,</hi> intimates
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:29874:16"/> greater <hi>Love,</hi> then that <hi>Man</hi> ſhould <hi>partake</hi> of the <note n="*" place="margin">2 Pet, 1. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature.</hi> O Matchleſs Inſtance of <hi>Affection!</hi> Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, Heaven it ſelf could not anſwer the demands of a ſoul touching a <hi>greater Love</hi> then <hi>this</hi> is. <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quò Nitè Dei? Quo tua flagravit Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas? Quo crevit tua Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignitas?</hi> &amp;c. Aug. l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. Med. cap. 7. pag. 698. Tom. 9. Baſil. 1569.</note> 
               <hi>Whither? O Son of God! Whither flamed thy Charity? Whither encreaſed thy Benignity? Whither reached thy Love? Whither amounted thy Compaſſion? &amp;c.</hi> Here we may <hi>ſay much,</hi> and <hi>ſpeak</hi> but <hi>little.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. This <hi>Love</hi> of God is a <hi>Diſtinguiſhing Love.</hi> Signal is that <hi>Diſcrimination,</hi> which this <hi>Love</hi> hath made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Men,</hi> in the favour of <hi>Mankinde.</hi> The <hi>Son</hi> of God was <hi>made of a Woman;</hi> ſo that <hi>God</hi> became <hi>Man;</hi> but we do not read that <hi>God</hi> became an <hi>Angel.</hi> God <hi>took not upon him the Nature of Angels, but he took upon him the Seed of Abraham,</hi> Heb. 2. 16. <hi>Angels</hi> did eminently partake of the <hi>Divine Nature,</hi> (that is) of God's <hi>Communicable</hi> Graces and Excellencies) but <hi>God</hi> did not partake of the <hi>Angelical</hi> Nature; But</p>
            <p>As God made <hi>Man</hi> like <hi>Himſelf</hi> in the <hi>firſt Creation,</hi> ſo he made <hi>Himſelf</hi> like <hi>man</hi> in the Goſpel-work of the <hi>Incarnation,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <q>God ſent forth his Son made of a woman.</q>
            <p>The <hi>Perſonal <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> of the <hi>Humane</hi> Nature with the <hi>Deity,</hi> was a Capital and <hi>Diſtinguiſhing Honour</hi> conferr'd upon <hi>Mankinde.</hi> O highly honoured <hi>Man! Angels</hi> are not fit <hi>Competitors</hi> with <hi>thee.</hi> I challenge the whole * <hi>nine</hi>
               <note place="margin">Angels, Archangels, Vertues, Powers, Principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Dominions, Thrones, Cherubims, Seraphims.</note> 
               <hi>Orders</hi> of them. What <hi>Angel</hi> can plead <hi>Conſanguinity</hi> to the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>God?</hi> This <hi>Man</hi> can do. What <hi>Angel</hi> can ſay that of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which <hi>Adam</hi> ſaid of <hi>Eve;</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 2. 23.</note> 
               <hi>This is Bone of my bone, and fleſh of my fleſh?</hi> This <hi>Man</hi> can ſay. <hi>Thy</hi> Nature, O Man! is <hi>Perſonally One</hi> with the <hi>God-head</hi> in Chriſt; The <hi>Angelical</hi> Nature is not thus ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:29874:17"/>
            <p>There is a <hi>Royal</hi> Dignity conferr'd both upon the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> and upon the <hi>Perſons</hi> of <hi>Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. Upon their <hi>Natures;</hi> for</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our Nature</hi> being <hi>Perſonally</hi> United to the <hi>Deity</hi> in Chriſt, partakes of the <hi>Legiſlative</hi> Power of Heaven, and is <hi>Entitled</hi> to the <hi>Crown Royal</hi> thereof. The <hi>Deity</hi> and <hi>Humanity</hi> of Chriſt (though <hi>diſtinct Natures,</hi> yet) wear not <hi>diſtinct Crowns,</hi> but are (as hath been often ſaid) <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally One</hi> in <hi>King</hi> Chriſt. Now, the <hi>Father</hi> and the <hi>Son</hi> divide neither <hi>Crowns</hi> nor <hi>Scepters,</hi> but (joyntly) exerciſe one and the ſame <hi>Juriſdiction.</hi> The <hi>Man</hi> Chriſt is the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Angels.</hi> O what a <hi>Pre-eminence</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> is that!</p>
            <p>The <hi>Humane Nature,</hi> is by vertue of its <hi>Perſonal <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> with the <hi>God-head,</hi> promoted (as I may ſay) to <hi>Regal Authority</hi> over the <hi>Angels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. Upon their <hi>Perſons;</hi> for</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Men</hi> may be ſaid to be of the <hi>Blood-Royal</hi> of Heaven, and are (ſo to ſpeak) more neerly related to the <hi>Imperial Crown</hi> of Heaven, then <hi>Angels.</hi> Now Beloved, what is this other then the fruit of a <hi>Diſtinguiſhing Love?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Diſtinguiſhing Love</hi> of God may be further il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrated from this conſideration; namely, That <hi>Angels</hi> are <hi>Spiritual;</hi> and <hi>men, Corporeal Subſtances;</hi> ſo that there was a greater <hi>conformity</hi> in <hi>Nature</hi> between <hi>God</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi> (for both are <hi>Spirits</hi>) then between <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Men;</hi> Now that God ſhould condeſcend to aſſume to himſelf a <hi>Body,</hi> rather then a <hi>Spirit,</hi> was meerly from the <hi>diſcrimina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> Love of God. What? And muſt <hi>Clay</hi> be encircled with the <hi>Rayes</hi> of <hi>Divine Majeſty?</hi> Would not the <hi>Angelical</hi> Nature have been a more proper <hi>Receptacle</hi> for the <hi>Deity</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Alienum erat a Natura &amp; Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinitate (Dei) ſanguinem &amp; carnem ſuſcipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, propter nos autem ea quae ſibi erant aliena ſuſcepit,, vt domeſticos ſibi ſaceret, qui ſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>romus alioni per peccatum.</hi> Origen. <hi>in</hi> Eſaium, Hom. 7.</note> then <hi>Duſt</hi> and <hi>Aſhes,</hi> that inferiour piece of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:29874:17"/>
            <p>Such was the <hi>Love</hi> of God to <hi>Mankinde,</hi> that he <note n="*" place="margin">Illos neglexit Illos dilexit.</note> paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the fallen <hi>Angels,</hi> and took upon him the <hi>Nature</hi> of fallen <hi>Man,</hi> being <hi>made of a woman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence <hi>Angels</hi> and not <hi>Men</hi> are <hi>Divels</hi> to day; O what an Impreſſion ſhould this make upon us! What? That <hi>Man</hi> by the Order of <hi>Creation, Satan's</hi> Inferiour, ſhould be honoured with <hi>Conſanguinity</hi> to the <hi>Son</hi> of God, and neer Relation to the <hi>B. Irinity!</hi> And that <hi>Satan</hi> once an <hi>Angel</hi> of <hi>Light,</hi> ſhould be the <hi>firſt</hi> Inhabitant of <hi>outer darkneſs!</hi> That the <hi>Angels</hi> which <hi>kept not their firſt eſtate,</hi> ſhould be left irrecoverably in their <hi>loſt</hi> and accurſed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, and be <hi>reſerved in everlaſting chains under darkneſs!</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iude 6.</note> Whereas the <hi>Son</hi> of God hath graciouſly condeſcended to unite to Himſelf the <hi>Nature</hi> of <hi>fallen Man,</hi> that <hi>Man</hi> might be recovered out of a <hi>miſerable</hi> eſtate, and reſtored to a <hi>better</hi> eſtate then that from which he had <hi>fallen!</hi> Is not that a <hi>diſtinguiſhing Love?</hi> Though I could <hi>ſpeak with the Tongues of Men and of Angels,</hi> yet ſhould I fail in this ſo amazing an inquiſation: This is <hi>Soraphical</hi> Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Chriſtians! <hi>Eternity</hi> it ſelf is little enough to admire, and with praiſe to Comment upon this Theam of God's <hi>ſuperlative</hi> and <hi>diſtinguiſhing love</hi> to <hi>Mankinde,</hi> in.</p>
            <p>3. Evangelical Humility.</p>
            <p>That the <hi>Son</hi> of the <hi>living God</hi> ſhould be <hi>made of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> was the greateſt Inſtance of <hi>Humility</hi> that is imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, Chriſt's <hi>Humiliation</hi> was <hi>gradual;</hi> there were theſe two ſteps in it, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The <hi>Aſſumption</hi> of our <hi>Nature.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Obedience, Active</hi> and <hi>Paſſive</hi> in that Nature.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe were the two <hi>gradual</hi> parts of the <hi>Lord</hi> Chriſt's <hi>Self-denyal;</hi> but the former was the greater of the two.</p>
            <p>That <hi>God</hi> ſhould become <hi>Man,</hi> was a greater argument of <hi>Self-denyal</hi> in Chriſt, then that <hi>God-Man</hi> ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>Obedient</hi> (even) unto <hi>death;</hi> in that there is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely greater diſtance between <hi>God</hi> and <hi>man</hi> (in reſpect of <hi>Being</hi>) then there is between <hi>Man</hi> and <hi>death;</hi> (for
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:29874:18"/> 
               <hi>God</hi> is of an <hi>Infinite</hi> Being, and <hi>Man</hi> (but) of a <hi>finite</hi> and limited capacity,) whereas (in a ſenſe) it is as Natural for <hi>Man</hi> to <hi>die</hi> as to <hi>live.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>He</hi> who for <hi>Nature</hi> was <hi>co-eſſential</hi> with <hi>God,</hi> ſhould become <hi>co-eſſential</hi> with <hi>man!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>He,</hi> who for <hi>Dignity</hi> was <hi>co-equal</hi> with <hi>God,</hi> ſhould become a <note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 53. 11. Mat. 12. 28. Phil. 2. 7.</note> 
               <hi>ſervant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>He</hi> who for <hi>Time</hi> and Duration was <hi>co-eternal</hi> with <hi>God,</hi> ſhould condeſcend <hi>in the fulneſs of the time to be made of a woman!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhould be <hi>made</hi> of Her whoſe <hi>Maker</hi> he was! Is not that <hi>Humility?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the <hi>Incomprehenſible Majeſty</hi> of Heaven, * whom<note place="margin">1 Kings 8. 27.</note> 
               <hi>the Heaven of heavens cannot contain,</hi> ſhould ſtoop to <hi>nine moneths</hi> confinement in the wombe of a poor Virgin!</p>
            <p>That the <hi>Glory</hi> of God ſhould fill a <hi>Tabernacle of Clay!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That * <hi>the High and Lofty One</hi> ſhould pitch in <hi>duſt</hi> and<note place="margin">Iſa. 57. 15.</note> 
               <hi>aſhes!</hi> That the <hi>Sun</hi> of <hi>Divine Glory</hi> ſhould ſuffer an <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe</hi> by the Interpoſition of <hi>Earth!</hi> O what a ſtupendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous condeſcention was that! Beloved, <hi>Heaven</hi> ſeemed in this to have been wholly devoted to <hi>Man.</hi> The whole <hi>Trinity,</hi> (ever admired be Free Grace) ſeems to have been <hi>Self-denied</hi> here; The <hi>Father</hi> was (in a manner) <hi>denyed</hi> to his Dear and only Begotten <hi>Son;</hi> and the <hi>Son</hi> to <hi>Himſelf;</hi> to his <hi>Connatural Glory</hi> (which he ſuffered to be clouded for a time) in condeſcending to become <hi>Man;</hi> as he was to <hi>life</hi> it ſelf, in condeſcending to <hi>die</hi> like a Man; though <hi>he thought it not robbery to be equal with God, yet he made himſelf of no reputation</hi> (he degraded himſelf) <hi>and took upon him the form of a ſervant, and was made in the likeneſs of men,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 6, 7. <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quo nate Dei? Quo tua deſcendit humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litas? &amp;c.</hi> Aug. <hi>lib. Med. cap. 7. pag. 698. Tom.</hi> 9. Baſil. 1569.</note> 
               <hi>Whither! O Son of God! Whither deſcended thy Humility? I have been proud, and thou baſt been humbled;</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:29874:18"/>
            <p>4. <hi>Evangelical Wiſdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the <hi>Saviour</hi> of mankinde ſhould be <hi>the Son of God, made of a woman,</hi> is an Inſtance of aſtoniſhing <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi> What?</p>
            <p n="1">1. That God ſhould contrive ſuch a method of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as that he could <hi>puniſh ſin,</hi> and (yet) <hi>ſpare</hi> the <hi>ſinner!</hi> What is that other then the plot of <hi>infinite Wiſdome?</hi> God did <hi>puniſh ſin</hi> in the <hi>Nature</hi> of ſinners, and (yet) did <hi>ſpare</hi> the <hi>perſons</hi> of ſinners; <hi>Juſtice</hi> received <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> in our Nature, and (yet) <hi>Mercy</hi> was glorified in the <hi>ſalvation</hi> of our Nature; and (which is a glorious ſoul-refreſhing truth) the <hi>ſame Juſtice</hi> which obliged God to <hi>puniſh</hi> ſin in our <hi>Nature,</hi> doth now oblige him to <hi>pardon</hi> ſin in our <hi>Perſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That God ſhould at once glorifie both <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Mercy</hi> in a Saviour, is the memorable product of <hi>Divine Wiſdome.</hi> Thoſe two <hi>Attributes,</hi> viz. <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Mercy,</hi> are both at once glorified in <hi>Chriſt; Juſtice,</hi> In that God did <hi>indiſpenſably</hi> require <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> in order to the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners <hi>ſalvation; Mercy,</hi> In that God did from an impulſe of <hi>free Love</hi> to ſinners, <hi>provide</hi> a <hi>Surety</hi> and <hi>Mediatour</hi> in order to <hi>ſatisfaction;</hi> God <hi>ſatisfied</hi> Himſelf in <hi>Himſelf:</hi> So that here is a ſweet <hi>Attemperation</hi> (ſo to ſpeak) of <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Mercy.</hi> Thoſe two <hi>Attributes</hi> (however they may ſeem to repreſent God with a contrary Aſpect, yet) are (as it were) <hi>reconciled</hi> in <hi>Chriſt;</hi> Here <hi>Mercy</hi> is acted in the ſevereſt piece of <hi>Juſtice;</hi> never was there a more ſevere Act of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> then that God's own <hi>Son</hi> ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a <hi>ſacrifice,</hi> rather then <hi>Juſtice</hi> ſhould not be <hi>ſatisfied.</hi> Again, Never was there a more ſignal Act of <hi>Mercy,</hi> then that God's own <hi>Son</hi> ſhould become a <hi>ſacrifice,</hi> rather then <hi>Mercy</hi> ſhould not be <hi>glorified.</hi> O the <hi>Wonder-working Wiſdome</hi> of God!</p>
            <p>Had God called a General Aſſembly of the <hi>Peers</hi> of Heaven, thoſe Celeſtial <hi>Intelligences,</hi> they could never have deviſed ſuch a <hi>method of ſalvation</hi> for poor ſinners,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:29874:19"/> as God hath in love to their ſouls, contrived in his own <hi>Son, made of a woman; O the depth of the Riches both of the wiſdome and knowledge of God!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus I have endeavoured to diſplay matter of Wonder and thankful Admiration. Beloved, theſe are things which the very glorious <hi>Angels deſire to look</hi> (and pry) <hi>into.</hi>
               <note place="margin">* 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 12. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Angelical Speculations!</hi> And I dare ſay, that it will be a great part of the work of <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Saints</hi> in glory, to celebrate thoſe <hi>Mirabilia Dei,</hi> and Evangelical wonders, with praiſes, to all eternity.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> 2. Here is ground of <hi>Reprehenſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Was the <hi>Son</hi> of God <hi>in the fulneſs of the time made of a woman?</hi> This may ſerve ſharply to reprove two ſorts of perſons.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The <hi>Jew.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. The <hi>Judaizing</hi> Chriſtian.</item>
            </list>
            <p>1. The <hi>Jew.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Although it is palpably manifeſt, and clear (as the light) from the infallible Oracle of <hi>Goſpel,</hi> the viſible accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of <hi>Prophetical Predictions,</hi> &amp;c. That the Son of God is already (long ago) come in the <hi>fleſh;</hi> that the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> the promiſed <hi>Seed of the woman,</hi> is come; yet <hi>Jewes</hi> (poor wretches!) <hi>will not believe it.</hi> To this day do they continue in <hi>obſtinate incredulity,</hi> and a vain expectation of the <hi>Meſſias</hi> their <hi>King;</hi> and ſo (alas! alas!) through a <hi>vain expectation</hi> of the <hi>Saviour,</hi> they miſs of a Saviour. That which my ſoul moſt pities them for, is, That during theſe <hi>ſixteen hundred</hi> yeers darkneſs and deſertion, hundreds of thouſands of them (yea, for ought I know) as many hundred thouſands as there are <hi>centuries</hi> of yeers, have <hi>dyed irrecoverably</hi> in their ſins! (But <hi>juſt is God in all his wayes</hi>) And if God in mercy to their ſouls, haſten not their Converſion, and the <hi>re-ingraf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> of thoſe * <hi>Native Branches</hi> into the <hi>common Root,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 11. 21. 24.</note> (Chriſt;) how many thouſands more may yet <hi>periſh,</hi> the Lord knows! For (oh Lord!) they <hi>dye</hi> daylie! Ah! Thus
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:29874:19"/> it fares with them, who (once) were God's <hi>peculiar peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple!</hi> his <hi>Portion!</hi> the <hi>dearly Beloved of his ſoul!</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>Poor Nation! Whoſe ſweet ſap and juyce,</l>
               <l>Our Cyens have purloyn'd, and left you dry:</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſtreams we got by the Apoſtles ſluce;</l>
               <l>And uſe in Baptiſme, while ye pine and dye:</l>
               <l>Who by not keeping once, became a Debter;</l>
               <l>And now by keeping loſe the Letter.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O that my prayers! mine, alas!</l>
               <l>O that ſome Angel might a Trumpet ſound;</l>
               <l>At which the Church falling upon her face,</l>
               <l>Should cry ſo loud, until the Trump were drown'd,</l>
               <l>And by that cry, of her dear Lord obtain</l>
               <l>That your ſweet ſap might come again!</l>
            </lg>
            <p>The Metrical Apoſtrophe of a <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> George Herbert <hi>of</hi> Cambridge, <hi>in his</hi> Sacred Poems.</note> holy Poet to that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</p>
            <p>It is obſervable of that people, that by adhering to the <hi>Law,</hi> they loſe the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> by cleaving to <hi>Moſes,</hi> the <hi>Typical Meſſias,</hi> they miſs of the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> the true <hi>Moſes.</hi> Were I able by my voice to reach the land of <hi>Jewry,</hi> or the diſperſed <hi>Jewes</hi> where-ever they are ſcattered as forlorn Vagabonds, to day, I would a little expoſtulate with them. Oh, obſtinate and incredulous <hi>Jewes!</hi> Are ye in Covenant with perdition? Are ye reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to periſh in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief?</hi> But, will ye not admit of <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel</hi> (which preſents us with this great Evangelical truth, <hi>viz. That in the fulneſs of the time, God ſent forth his Son, made of a woman?</hi> the only true <hi>Meſſiah</hi>) What? Are ye in league with <hi>Moſes?</hi> In love with <hi>ſervitude</hi> and bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage? The Propheſies concerning the <hi>Meſſias</hi> are fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; yea (as I have ſhewed above) the <hi>Meſſias</hi> his own Propheſies and <hi>Perſonal Predictions</hi> are fulfilled: O that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:29874:20"/> ye would learn <hi>the belief of the Truth,</hi> from the very <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied</hi> Ruines of your <hi>Temple, City, Lawes,</hi> whole <hi>State, Policy,</hi> and <hi>Commonwealth!</hi> Ah! poor <hi>Jew!</hi> The Lord convince you, that there is no poſſibility of <hi>Life</hi> for you, but in him who <hi>dyed</hi> by you! Ye cannot be <hi>ſaved</hi> but through him, whom <hi>by wicked hands</hi> ye <hi>have crucified and ſlain:</hi> The only (poſſible) way and method of <hi>ſalvation,</hi> is that very <hi>blood</hi> which (you are <hi>guilty</hi> of, and) hath theſe ſixteen hundred yeers layn upon your <hi>heads</hi> through your <hi>crucifying</hi> of the <hi>Lord of glory;</hi> and that direful Impre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, <hi>His blood be upon us and our children,</hi> wherein the Curſe of <hi>that</hi> execrable ſin of <hi>blood-ſhed</hi> is entailed upon your <hi>Poſterity!</hi> And, O how ſad is it, when Perſons are <hi>guilty</hi> of that very <hi>blood</hi> which alone is effectual for the <hi>pardon</hi> of <hi>guilt!</hi> for <hi>peace</hi> with God! for the <hi>ſalvation</hi> of precious ſouls! <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. The <hi>Judaizing Chriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Judaizing Chriſtians,</hi> I underſtand thoſe that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for <hi>Ceremonies</hi> in point of Worſhip, in a profeſſed <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church: For a <hi>Ceremonial</hi> kinde of <hi>Worſhip</hi> being <hi>peculiar</hi> to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, (as wholly <hi>Typical,</hi>) it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth by neceſſary Conſequence, That an <hi>Introduction</hi> of <hi>Ceremonies</hi> in point of <hi>Worſhip</hi> (into the <hi>Chriſt an</hi> Church) is a <hi>Reduction</hi> of <hi>Judaiſme.</hi> Now ſuch are lyable to a juſt <hi>Reproof</hi> from hence, namely, That <hi>the Son of God was in the fulneſs of the time made of a woman.</hi> (Where Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate <hi>Rome,</hi> with her <hi>Jewiſh-Popiſh Trumpery,</hi> falls ſhrewdly under the laſh, (only what pity is it that ſo <hi>ſtrong</hi> a <hi>weapon</hi> is in ſo <hi>weak</hi> a <hi>hand?</hi>) For the <hi>Jewiſh Rites</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> being but <hi>Shaddows</hi> and <hi>Typical Adumbrations</hi> of the promiſed <hi>Meſſias,</hi> muſt needs be abrogated now, ſince the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Subſtance</hi> prefigured by them, is come: When the <hi>Body</hi> is come, the <hi>Shaddow</hi> evaniſheth; <hi>Types</hi> ceaſe in the <hi>Anti-type.</hi> So that to retain <hi>Jewiſh Ceremonies</hi> in the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church, were <hi>Antichriſtian Judaiſme;</hi> for that were (virtually) to deny that the <hi>Son</hi> of God is come in the fleſh.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:29874:20"/>
            <p>I lay down no other (as to the ſenſe) then what a great<note place="margin">
                  <hi>D.</hi> Downam, <hi>in his Treatiſe of</hi> Chriſtian Liberty.</note> * <hi>Doctor</hi> of the <hi>Formaliſts</hi> hath aſſerted before me. <hi>The Ceremonial Rites</hi> (ſaith he, they are his own words) <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were principally ordained to prefigure Chriſt, are ſo aboliſhed, that it is not lawful for Chriſtians to obſerve them; for that were to deny that Chriſt is come.</hi> (I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs I am of his judgement) and he cites S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Contra Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum Manich.</hi> lib. 19. cap. 18.</note> 
               <hi>Ea non obſervant Chriſtiani, per quae Chriſtus promittebatur, nec adhuc promittuntur, quia jam impleta ſunt.</hi> Chriſtians obſerve not thoſe things by which Chriſt was promiſed; neither are they as yet promiſed, becauſe they are already fulfilled.</p>
            <p>For my own part (it's true, I am leſs then the leaſt of ten thouſand, and therefore no wonder that men in this Learned Age over-look me, as little objects which eſcape the <hi>ſenſe,</hi> however) it is a concluſion with me, that Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies in point of Worſhip, are altogether unlawful in <hi>Goſpel-times;</hi> ſince <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who was typified by them, is come; (for <hi>when the fulneſs of the time was come, God ſent forth his Son, made of a woman:</hi>) as (bleſſed be God) we read, preach, hear, and believe to day. I do not now plead either <hi>Conſcience</hi> or <hi>Covenant</hi> that <hi>forbidden</hi> Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; But My ground is <hi>Scripture-Evidence.</hi> For,</p>
            <p>Was not this God's great deſigne in ſending forth his Son <hi>made of a woman,</hi> namely, <hi>That he might redeem them that were under the Law?</hi> The <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church was ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the <hi>Ceremonial</hi> and <hi>Judicial</hi> Lawes of <hi>Moſes.</hi> As 1. A <hi>Yoke</hi> in reſpect of her <hi>ſervile-ſtate.</hi> And 2. A <hi>School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter,</hi> and <hi>Rudiments,</hi> in reſpect of her <hi>Infant-ſtate;</hi> (and hence the Apoſtle calls them, <hi>The * Elements of the</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>world,</hi> v. 3.) But the <hi>Son</hi> of God did <hi>in the fulneſs of the time,</hi> (when the Church was grown up to <hi>maturity</hi> and an <hi>adult</hi> age) take upon him our Nature, and was <hi>made un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law,</hi> that he might <hi>redeem</hi> his Church from that <hi>bondage</hi> and <hi>ſubjection. Exemption</hi> from <hi>Legal Rites</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> whether we conſider them 1. As a <hi>Pedago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie;</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:29874:21"/> Or 2. As a <hi>Yoke,</hi> being that part of Chriſt's pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe which is <hi>peculiar</hi> to the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church. And</p>
            <p>What other is the drift of the bleſſed Apoſtle in the Context, then to prove the ſame?—<hi>When we were children</hi> (ſaith he) that is, the Church in her <hi>Infant-ſtate</hi> and <hi>minority,) we were in bondage under the elements of the world</hi>) that is, a <hi>Moſaical Pedagogie</hi> of <hi>Puerile Ceremonies</hi> and <hi>Rituals</hi>) v. 3. <hi>But when the fulneſs of the time was come, God ſent forth his Son, made of a woman,</hi> &amp;c. And hence it is that he ſo roundly checks the <hi>Galatians</hi> (a <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daizing</hi> people in many things, as appears) v. 9, 10, 11. <hi>But now</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>after that ye have known God, or rather are known of God, How turn ye again to the</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>weak and beggerly Elements, whereunto ye deſire again to be in bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage? Ye obſerve dayes, and moneths, and times, and yeers; I am afraid of you, leſt I have beſtowed upon you labour in vain.</hi> What? (would be ſay) Are ye in love with your <hi>Bonds?</hi> Will ye return to your firſt <hi>Rudiments</hi> and A B C? A notable Sarcaſme! And hence is that Cautelary Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Apoſtle to the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> chap. 2. v. 17, 18. <hi>Let no man judge</hi> (or condemn) <hi>you in meat, or in drink, or in reſpect of a holy day, or of the new Moon, or of the Sabbath dayes, which are a ſhaddow of the things to come, but the Body is of Chriſt. Legal Obſervances,</hi> and <hi>Feſtival Times</hi> were meer <hi>ſhaddows</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> to come. He is the <hi>Body</hi> that was prefigured by them. Now this <hi>Body</hi> being come, to what purpoſe are <hi>ſhaddows?</hi> Oh! that men ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ſo eagerly for <hi>ſhaddows!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Once more,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Carnal Ordinances, Rites,</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies, were impoſed</hi> upon the <hi>Jewes. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, until the time of Reformation,</hi> Heb. 9. 9, 10. (O what pity is it that they ſhould be purſued by profeſſed <hi>Chriſtians</hi> inſtead of a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation!</hi>) Now <hi>the time of Reformation,</hi> was the time of the <hi>Churches Emancipation</hi> and deliverance from theſe <hi>carnal Ordinances, Rites,</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> by her Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:29874:21"/> 
               <hi>the Son of God, made of a woman.</hi> In a word, <hi>Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial Worſhip</hi> in a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church, ſeems (to me) to be contrary to God's <hi>deſigne</hi> in coming in the fleſh, not to ſay, to the deſigne of <hi>Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let us examine what the <hi>Ceremonialiſts</hi> ſay for themſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ceremonies</hi> (ſay they) be of two ſorts, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Typical.</item>
               <item>2. Symbolical.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Typical</hi> Ceremonies (ſay they) being ordained to <hi>preſigure Chriſt,</hi> the promiſed <hi>Meſſias,</hi> are by <hi>him abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed,</hi> and (by conſequence) <hi>unlawful</hi> in the <hi>New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament</hi> times; But</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Symbolical</hi> and <hi>Myſtically-ſignificant</hi> Ceremonies may very <hi>lawfully</hi> be continued in the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church, as uſeful for <hi>edification</hi> (beſides <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Decency;</hi>) (by<note place="margin">Dr <hi>Burgeſs</hi> of the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>&amp;c. cap. 17. pag. 52.</hi>
               </note> vertue of ſome <hi>ſpiritual ſignification,</hi> which they attribute to them, calling them <hi>ſacred ſignes of ſpiritual Myſteries.</hi>) Thus the <hi>Surplice</hi> (for inſtance) being (ſay they) a <hi>Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolical</hi> Ceremony, as that which ſignifies the Miniſters <hi>pureneſs</hi> and <hi>Innocency,</hi> may be <hi>lawfully</hi> (yea profitably) uſed (even) by the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Clergie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is not my purpoſe to debate the <hi>lawfulneſs</hi> of thoſe <hi>Myſtical-ſignificant</hi> Ceremonies. I leave that to be learned of thoſe, of whom I may learn. The Learned Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of <hi>the Diſpute</hi> againſt the <hi>Engliſh-Popiſh</hi> Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, hath by divers arguments diſproved it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Only,</p>
            <p>I ſhall preſume to ſpeak my own thoughts (having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the Text) in a few particulars, which I am hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly bold to offer to the <hi>Ceremony-mongers</hi> for ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>1. If <hi>Types</hi> and <hi>Legal ſhaddows</hi> be aboliſhed by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> (the true <hi>Meſſias</hi>) who was (as hath been often ſaid) prefigured by the ſame, and therefore is called <note n="*" place="margin">John 1. 17.</note> 
               <hi>The Truth</hi> in anſwer to <hi>Types;</hi> and <note n="*" place="margin">Col. 2. 17, 18. <hi>Praeſente viri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Typus &amp; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbra ceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit,</hi> Origen <hi>in</hi> Jeſ. Nave. <hi>cap 13. Hom. 17.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The Body</hi> in anſwer to <hi>ſhaddows,</hi> which they <hi>do</hi> and <hi>muſt</hi> acknowledge; Then I deſire for Conſcience ſake to be reſolved, in order to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:29874:22"/> 
               <hi>three</hi> things, namely, what ground there is for</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The Introduction of <hi>Altars.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. The nice obſervance of <hi>Holy-dayes,</hi> (I approve of a <hi>holy obſervance</hi> of dayes.)</item>
               <item>3. <hi>Organical Muſick</hi> in the <hi>Goſpel</hi> Church?</item>
            </list>
            <p>1. As touching <hi>Altare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who knows not that the <hi>Altar</hi> (both That of <hi>Incenſe,</hi> Exod. 30. and That of <hi>Burnt-offering,</hi> Exod. 27.) was an eminent <hi>Type</hi> of <hi>Chriſt?</hi> I dare ſay there was not a more<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Altare ſuit pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, &amp; ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia celebraban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ſed ut venit verus Agnus, qui ſeipſum Hoſtiam obtulit Deo, cuncta illa velut pro tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore poſita ceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaverunt.</hi> Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen. <hi>in</hi> Levit. <hi>cap. 16. Hom. 10. Cum in adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu Salvatoris noſtri Dei è Coelis deſcendens veritas, de terra orta eſt, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbra &amp; exemplaria ceciderunt. Cecidit enim Hieruſalem, cecidit Templum, Altare ſublatum eſt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Id. in Joſ. Nave. cap. 13. Hom. 17.</hi>
               </note> memorable <hi>Type</hi> under the Law, then the <hi>Altar</hi> was. Now then, if <hi>Types</hi> be aboliſhed by Chriſt, why not <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars?</hi> Under the Old Teſtament (ſaith <note n="*" place="margin">Hoſpin. <hi>de</hi> Templis, <hi>de orig. Altarium.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hoſpinian</hi>) there were two <hi>Altars,</hi> and both did prefigure Chriſt; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all <hi>Types</hi> and <hi>ſhaddows</hi> are paſt and evaniſhed, <hi>Nulla Altaria deinceps in Eccleſia, excitari ſen erigi debebant;</hi> It is unlawful afterwards to erect <hi>Altars</hi> in the Church; and he quotes the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> propheſying of the Kingdome of Chriſt, <hi>chap. 17. v. 7. At that day ſhall a man look to his Maker, and his eyes ſhall have reſpect to the holy One of Iſrael; and he ſhall not look to the Altars, the work of his hands, neither ſhall reſpect that which his fingers have made,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>2. As touching <hi>Feſtival</hi> dayes.</p>
            <p>Thoſe alſo were under the Law <hi>Figurative</hi> and <hi>Peda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogical,</hi> as is clear from the <hi>letter; Let no man</hi> (ſaith our Apoſtle) <hi>judge you in meat, or in drink, or in reſpect of a holy day,</hi> &amp;c. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>which are a</hi> Shad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow <hi>of things to come, but the Body is of Chriſt,</hi> Col. 2. 17, 18. Thoſe were <hi>Legal ſhaddows</hi> and <hi>adumbrations</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Body;</hi> therefore they are abrogated. <hi>Quis neſciat, ubi jam eſt corpus ibi umbram deſinere,</hi> ſaith <hi>Zan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy</hi> upon the place; Who knows not that <hi>ſhaddows</hi> ceaſe and evaniſh when the <hi>Body</hi> is come? But</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:29874:22"/>
            <p>It is objected, That <hi>Jewiſh Feſtivities</hi> only are aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, becauſe thoſe were <hi>Typical;</hi> but <hi>Chriſtian Feſtivities</hi> are warrantable, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is well obſerved by <note n="*" place="margin">Hoſpin. <hi>Do Feſt. Chriſt.</hi> cap. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Hoſpinian,</hi> That <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianorum feſta ab hominibus tantum, Judaeorum vero, a Deo fuerunt inſtituta. Chriſtian</hi> Feſtivals were ordained by <hi>Men</hi> only, but the <hi>Judaical</hi> by <hi>God</hi> himſelf. Now if <hi>thoſe</hi> of <hi>God's</hi> own Inſtitution which he ordained for his own honour be aboliſhed by Himſelf. 1. How preſumptuous is the <hi>Papiſt</hi> which dares to preſs the obſervation of feaſts of their <hi>own</hi> deviſing, and that for the honour of <hi>Men</hi> like themſelves? Nay 2. It ſeems not a little ſtrange to me, That when <hi>God</hi> hath aboliſhed what he himſelf did <hi>inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, Men</hi> ſhould preſume to <hi>re-inſtitute</hi> the ſame. <hi>God</hi> is <hi>willing</hi> that <hi>Feſtivals</hi> ſhould evaniſh as meer <hi>ſhaddows;</hi> and is <hi>Man</hi> unwilling? But The <hi>Papiſt</hi> loves to <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erogate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is replyed,</p>
            <p>They do not obſerve their <hi>Feſtivities</hi> after the manner that the <hi>Jewes</hi> did, to whom they were <hi>Pedagogical,</hi> and meer <hi>Figures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is remarkable that the Apoſtle doth ſharply check the <hi>Galatians</hi> for <hi>obſerving of dayes, and moneths, and times, and yeers,</hi> Gal. 4. 10. Now, who doth doubt but that the <hi>Galatians (before whoſe eyes Jeſus Chriſt was</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal, 3. 1. See <hi>Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright</hi> againſt the <hi>Rhemiſt,</hi> on <hi>Gal. 4. 10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>evidently ſet forth</hi>) did believe that the Son of God was come in the fleſh? So that we cannot imagine them to have obſerved thoſe <hi>dayes, moneths, yeers,</hi> the <hi>Anniverſary Solemnities,</hi> and other <hi>Feſtival Times,</hi> as <hi>Figures</hi> and <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umbrations</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> to come; but rather, as <hi>Memorials</hi> and <hi>Commemorative ſignes</hi> that he was already come, and yet behold here they are taxed as <hi>culpable!</hi> Ergo <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. As touching <hi>Organical Muſick</hi> in the <hi>Worſhip</hi> of God.</p>
            <p>That was alſo <hi>Pedagogical</hi> and <hi>Figurative;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>peculiar</hi> to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church: What ground is there
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:29874:23"/> then for the retention of it in the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> and <hi>Goſpel</hi>-Church? Since (as is granted even by thoſe that are ſtick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers for it) all <hi>Types</hi> and <hi>Figures</hi> are aboliſhed.</p>
            <p>Two things are incumbent upon me here, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. To evidence that <hi>Organs</hi> in the Worſhip of God were <hi>Types.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. To inſtance in the <hi>Anti-type,</hi> or the thing (parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly) typified thereby.</item>
            </list>
            <p>As touching the former.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Organs</hi> in the Worſhip of God in the <hi>Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> times, were <hi>Types, Figures,</hi> and meerly <hi>Jewiſh,</hi> may appear from the impregnable teſtimonies of Claſſical Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, (whom I have conſulted in the thing.)</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> that ancient Father (who lived in<note place="margin">Juſtin Martyr Quaeſt. 107.</note> the ſecond Age and Century of the Chriſtian Church,) ſaith, That the <hi>Primitive</hi> Chriſtian Church did explode that <hi>Pedagogical</hi> Cuſtome of <hi>Organical Muſick</hi> in the worſhip of God, as rather beſeeming <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Children, and the <hi>Infant</hi>-State of the Church, then the <hi>Goſpel</hi>-Church; and retained <hi>Vocal</hi> ſinging.</p>
            <p n="2">2. * <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> (who lived about two hundred yeers<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Chryſ. <hi>in Pſal. 150.</hi>
               </note> after him) ſaith, That <hi>Organs</hi> in Divine worſhip were permitted to the <hi>Jewes</hi> becauſe of their <hi>weakneſs;</hi> and he makes a <hi>moral</hi> Application of it to us under the Goſpel. As (ſaith he) the <hi>Jewes</hi> praiſed God with all Inſtruments of Muſick, ſo <hi>Chriſtians</hi> are commanded to praiſe him with all the members of their Bodies; <hi>Eyes, Ears, Tongue, Hands,</hi> &amp;c. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. They are his own words on <hi>Pſal.</hi> 150.) then <hi>Man</hi> himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes (as it were) a <hi>manifold Harp</hi> to God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Iſidorus Peleuſiotus</hi> his Diſciple, aſſerts the very<note place="margin">* <hi>Iſidor. Pelouſ. lib. 1. Epiſt. 457. lib. 2. Epiſt. 176.</hi>
               </note> ſame thing, and puts the <hi>Jewiſh Muſick</hi> (in Divine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip) into the ſame rank with the <hi>Jewiſh Sacrifices,</hi> which who can deny to have been <hi>Typical?</hi> Since (ſaith he) the Lord permitted to the <hi>Jews</hi> their <hi>bloody Sacrifices</hi> becauſe of the <hi>Infancy</hi> and <hi>Puerile</hi> ſtate of that Church;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:29874:23"/> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Why ſhouldeſt thou wonder that he permitted to them alſo the <hi>Harp</hi> and <hi>Pſaltery?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. S. <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nemo ſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertat ad Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gana Theatrica quod ei jubetur in ſe habet; ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut alibi dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi> In me Deus vota tua, <hi>&amp;c. Aug. in Pſal. 32. Conc. 1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auguſtines</hi> teſtimony is very remarkable, <hi>Let no man</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>betake himſelf to</hi> Theatrical <hi>Organs,</hi> (to wit, in the worſhip of God) <hi>thou haſt within thy ſelf (O man) what God requireth of thee;</hi> according to that which elſe-where is ſaid, <hi>Thy vows are upon me, O God, I will ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der praiſes unto thee,</hi> Pſal. 56. 12.</p>
            <p>But further,</p>
            <p n="5">5. <note n="*" place="margin">Aquin. 2. 2 <hi>de Quaeſt. 91. Art. 2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Aquinas</hi> aſſerts the very ſame thing, <hi>Inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Muſica, ſicut Citharas &amp; Pſalteria, non aſſumit Eccleſia in Divinas laudes, ne videatur Judaizare.</hi> The Chriſtian Church makes not uſe of <hi>Muſical Inſtruments,</hi> as the Harp or Pſaltery, in the celebration of Divine praiſes, leſt ſhe ſhould ſeem to <hi>Judaize.</hi> And again ſaith he, <hi>In veteri Teſtamento uſus erat talium inſtrumentorum, tum quia, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulus erat magis durus &amp; carnalis,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Tum quia hujuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi inſtrumenta corporalia aliquid figurabant.</hi> The <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> Church made uſe of ſuch Muſical Inſtruments, both becauſe ſhe was more obdured and carnal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and alſo becauſe thoſe <hi>Inſtruments</hi> did typifie and <hi>prefigure</hi> ſomwhat. Mark that. Hence Cardinal <hi>Cajetan</hi> comment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon that Article, obſerves, That the Church did not uſe <hi>Organical Muſick</hi> in the dayes of <hi>Aquinas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>* <hi>Hoſpinian,</hi> after that he hath cited divers Authors,<note place="margin">Hoſp. <hi>de Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plis, de Orig. Organ.</hi>
               </note> and noted many things concerning the firſt uſe and intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of an <hi>Organ</hi> into the Chriſtian Church, hath theſe words; <hi>Colligimus ex his Organorum hujuſmodi uſum, veteri &amp; Apoſtolicae Eccleſiae prorſus incognitum ſeroque in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventum &amp; receptum fuiſſe.</hi> We gather (ſaith he) from thoſe, that the uſe of <hi>Organs</hi> was altogether unknown to the <hi>Ancient Apoſtolick</hi> Church; and that they are but lately invented and received into the Church; and he
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:29874:24"/> brings in Cardinal <hi>Cajetan</hi> confeſſing the ſame thing, and withal adding, That for confirmation thereof, the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church uſeth no <hi>Organs</hi> before the <hi>Pope;</hi> and <note n="*" place="margin">Suarez <hi>Tom. 2. de Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t. &amp; Stat. Relig. lib. 4. cap. 8. num. 5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Suarez</hi> that <hi>Jeſuitical</hi> Champion gives the reaſon of it: Muſical Inſtruments are not uſed in the <hi>Pope's</hi> Chappel, becauſe (ſaith he) the uſe of them, <hi>non tani gravis judicatur,</hi> is not judged to ſavour of <hi>gravity</hi> enough. Ah! That <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Cathedrals</hi> ſhould come ſhort of <hi>Popiſh Chappels</hi> in point of <hi>gravity!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(The ſame <hi>Suarez</hi> ſpeaks of a <hi>Pope</hi> that did by Edict<note place="margin">* Suarez <hi>ib.</hi> viz. <hi>Tom. 2. de Verit. &amp; Stat. Rel. lib. 4. cap. 8. num. 1.</hi>
               </note> ſo bid <hi>Organical Muſick</hi> in the Worſhip of God, and he brings in <hi>Navarrus</hi> affirming the unlawfulneſs of uſing <hi>Organs</hi> at <hi>Maſs,</hi> or other Divine ſervice, by vertue of that Prohibition.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Baron. <hi>Anal. Eccleſ. ann. Chriſt. 60. pag. 578.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Caeſar Baronius</hi> that great Popiſh <hi>Annaliſt</hi> affirms the ſame thing that <hi>Hoſpinian</hi> upon the matter, <hi>Sane qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Muſica Inſtrumenta, haud antiquitus in Eccleſiam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troducta &amp; recepta eſſe videntur,</hi> ſaith he, Muſical Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſeem not to have been received into the Church in the Primitive times. And he quotes <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting<note place="margin">Juſtin. <hi>q. 107.</hi>
               </note> the ſame thing. Nay,</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Bellarm. <hi>lib. 1. de bonis oper. cap. 17.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelf, that great light of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament, confeſſeth that <hi>Organical</hi> Muſick, was at firſt introduced into the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church in the dayes of <note n="*" place="margin">So ſaith <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laeus</hi> an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Biſhop according to <hi>Hoſpinian de Tem. de orig. Organ.</hi>
               </note> Pope <hi>Vitalian,</hi> Ann. Chriſt. 660. according to <hi>Platina.</hi> Or (ſaith he) if we will credit <hi>Almoinus,</hi> (lib. 4. <hi>de geſtis Francorum,</hi> cap. 114.) not until the dayes of <hi>Lodovicus Pius,</hi> 820. yeers after our Lord's Incarnation, and that by the indu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>try of one <hi>Georgius Venetus</hi> a Prieſt, (as I finde in <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>nian de Templis,</hi> de origine Organorum; where he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>teth <hi>Aventinus,</hi> affirming the ſame thing (<hi>lib.</hi> 4.) t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t <hi>Almoinus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus I have made a Collection of Teſtimonies (having peruſed my <hi>Authors</hi> ſeverally.) From which it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that <hi>Organical Muſick</hi> in the Worſhip of God, was under the Law a part of the <hi>Jewiſh Pedagogie,</hi> and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurative,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:29874:24"/> and (by conſequence) <hi>Peculiar</hi> to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church.</p>
            <p>I might have argued from the <hi>Authentique</hi> Example of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> whom we finde ſinging <hi>Hymnes</hi> and <hi>Pſalmes;</hi> Chriſt and his Diſciples <hi>ſung an Hymne, Matth.</hi> 26. 30. They had not an <hi>Organ</hi> there, at leaſt we read of none. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas ſung praiſes unto God,</hi> Acts 16. 25. <hi>Vocal</hi> praiſe is the <hi>Goſpel</hi> praiſe. This <hi>Chriſt</hi> commends to the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and they to their <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Flocks and Churches (reſpectively) as <hi>Eph. 5. 18, 19. Col. 3. 16. James</hi> 5. 13. But let our <hi>Muſical Zelots</hi> inſtance, when and where <hi>Chriſt</hi> or his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> did either <hi>command</hi> or <hi>commend Organical Muſick</hi> to the <hi>Goſpel</hi>-Church if they can. But</p>
            <p>I was willing to trace them in their own Element, for, they are profeſſed <hi>Antiquaries,</hi> and many of them (I doubt)<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> Aug. <hi>Confeſſ. lib. 10. cap.</hi> 33. Lactant. <hi>lib. 2. cap.</hi> 4. Hierom. <hi>in</hi> Eph. 5. Hoſpin. de <hi>Temp. de orig. Organ.</hi> Eraſm. <hi>in</hi> 1 Cor. 14, Zepper. <hi>de Polit. Eccleſ. lib. 1. cap.</hi> 13. Muſcul. <hi>Epiſt. Dedicat. ante Comment. in</hi> Pſalmos, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> more ready to interpret <hi>Orthodoxy</hi> by the <hi>Fathers</hi> then by the SON. If notwithſtanding thoſe pregnant teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, men remain obſtinate, I can but turn them over to the laſh of the more ſober ſort of <hi>Papiſts,</hi> as <hi>Eraſmus, Cajetan,</hi> &amp;c. who have both lamented and ſharply in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veighed againſt the ſad (and too too frequent) prophanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Divine Worſhip,</hi> by their <hi>Organical</hi> and <hi>Theatrical Muſick; (quae carnis potius voluptati, quam Spiritus aedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficationi inſervit.</hi> Lactanct. lib. 2. cap. 24.</p>
            <p>As touching the latter.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Anti-type.</hi> That which was prefigured by <hi>Organi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Muſick</hi> in the <hi>Old-Teſtament</hi> Church.</p>
            <p>Were I worthy to ſpeak my own thoughts in the thing, I would ſay, That</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Legal Adumbrations</hi> and <hi>Types</hi> might be conceived to have had a threefold reference, <hi>viz.</hi> to</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Chriſt <hi>Perſonal.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. Chriſt <hi>Myſtical.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. The <hi>Glory</hi> of <hi>Goſpel-Miniſtery.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. As they did reſpect Chriſt <hi>Perſonal,</hi> they had a more
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:29874:25"/> eſpecial reference, either to his <hi>Incarnation,</hi> or to his <hi>Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> or to his <hi>Death,</hi> &amp;c. and accordingly were abrogated as to their <hi>Typical ſignification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. As they did reſpect Chriſt <hi>Myſtical,</hi> that is, the <hi>Church</hi> (conſiſting of her <hi>Head</hi> and <hi>Members myſtically</hi> united) they were (according to the <hi>ſucceſſive promulga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and <hi>Plantation</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church) <hi>gradually</hi> aboliſhed, (even) as to their <hi>continuance</hi> and <hi>obſervation.</hi> And hence S. <hi>Paul</hi> did at the beginning, and (as it were) the firſt dawning of <hi>Goſpel,</hi> in the <hi>Gentiles Hemiſphere,</hi> Circumciſe <hi>Timothy</hi> (though by his Fathers ſide a <hi>Greek</hi>) becauſe of the Infirmity of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> Acts 16. 3. But afterwards when the Goſpel was more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally publiſhed, and the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church more ripened, he would not Circumciſe <hi>Titus,</hi> Gal. 2. 3. Now</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Organs,</hi> and other <hi>Muſical Inſtruments</hi> (we may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the <hi>ſilver Trumpets,</hi> Numb. 10.) in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, may (as I humbly conceive) be ſaid to have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figured the <hi>Glory</hi> of <hi>Goſpel Miniſtery.</hi> That <hi>Organical Muſick</hi> was under the <hi>Old Teſtament Figurative</hi> and <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pical,</hi> is I preſume (now) apparent; and why it may not be ſaid to typifie the <hi>Glory</hi> of <hi>Evangelical Adminiſtration,</hi> I cannot learn.</p>
            <p>Why may not <hi>Organs,</hi> &amp;c. be ſaid to have prefigured the ſame thing that the <hi>Silver Trumpets</hi> did? But the <hi>Silver Trumpets</hi> did (if we credit the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Significant praedicationem Evangelicam toto Orbe reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantem.</hi> Cornel. a lap. <hi>in</hi> Num. 10. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Cyrill. <hi>in</hi> Exod. <hi>lib. 3. pag. 323. vid. pag. 322.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Learned</hi>) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figure <hi>Evangelical Preaching</hi> and <hi>Miniſtery.</hi> Ergo <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And</p>
            <p>What could be more properly typified by the <hi>Muſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal ſound</hi> in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, then the <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 89. 15.</note> 
               <hi>joyful ſound</hi> in the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church, even the glorious ſound of the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Goſpel?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:29874:25"/>
            <p>Thus I have endeavoured to ſhew, both 1. That <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganical Muſick</hi> under the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> was a <hi>Type.</hi> And 2. What was the <hi>Anti-type;</hi> Now, ſince it was <hi>Typical,</hi> why is it introduced into the <hi>Goſpel</hi>-Church?</p>
            <p>Poſſibly it will be ſaid that an <hi>Altar, Organ, Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks,</hi> &amp;c. are retained in the <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> (though they were <hi>Typical</hi> in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi>) Church, but not <hi>as Typical.</hi> And then 1. What <hi>Type</hi> was there under the <hi>Law,</hi> which may not (as well as thoſe) be received into the <hi>Goſpel</hi>-Church, ſo it be not received <hi>as a Type?</hi> Why not a <hi>Tabernacle</hi> as well as an <hi>Altar?</hi> (For my part, I would fain learn, what reaſon there is for the one more then for the other.) Why not a <hi>Brazen Serpent?</hi> &amp;c. Again, 2. They muſt be at the expence of coyning a new diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, (for that of <hi>Typical</hi> and <hi>Symbolical</hi> Ceremonies will not bear them out) which we have not heard of as yet.</p>
            <p>This is my firſt anſwer.</p>
            <p>2. Membra coincidunt.</p>
            <p>The Members of that diſtinction of Ceremonies, <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pical</hi> and <hi>Symbolical,</hi> are <hi>co-incident.</hi> Even thoſe <hi>Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies</hi> which are ſaid to be (and retained as) <hi>Symbolical,</hi> were under the Law <hi>Typical.</hi> Now this is contrary to the Rules of a right <hi>Diviſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To inſtance. The <hi>Surplice</hi> and other <hi>Veſtments</hi> are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained as <hi>Symbolical</hi> and <hi>ſignificant</hi> Ceremonies; for a <hi>Myſtical ſignification</hi> is attributed to them; the <hi>Surplice</hi> being a ſigne (as is ſaid) of the Miniſter's <hi>Purity,</hi> &amp;c. Now the <hi>Prieſtly</hi> and <hi>Levitical</hi> Garments, to which theſe anſwer, were all <hi>Typical. Multiplex illa Veſtium Sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotalium diſtinctio &amp; varietas, erat in Veteri Teſtamento Typica; Veritate autem exhibita quid amplius Typos re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirunt?</hi> ſaith <note n="*" place="margin">Syntag. Theolog. lib. 9. cap. 38.</note> 
               <hi>Amandus Polanus.</hi> The diſtinction of <hi>Prieſtly</hi> Veſtments under the Law was <hi>Typical,</hi> but the <hi>Truth</hi> and Anti-type being exhibited, why do men contend for <hi>Types</hi> any longer?</p>
            <p>Chriſt's <hi>threefold Office</hi> was ſhaddowed by the <hi>High</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:29874:26"/> Prieſt's Apparel; (as is obſerved by <hi>Polanus,</hi> and others) <hi>viz.</hi> His <hi>Kingly</hi> Office, by the <hi>Mitre</hi> which the <hi>High Prieſt</hi> did wear upon his Head: His <hi>Prieſtly</hi> Office by the <hi>Plate</hi> of <hi>pure</hi> Gold, whereon was engraven <hi>Holineſs to the Lord;</hi> and the <hi>Ephod</hi> and <hi>Breſt-plate</hi> whereon were engraven the Names of the <hi>twelve Tribes.</hi> His <hi>Prophetical Office</hi> by the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim</hi> and <hi>Thummim</hi> in the Breſt-plate, from which he anſwered as from an <hi>Oracle,</hi> as alſo by the <hi>Bells</hi> and <hi>Pomegranates;</hi> the one typing the ſound of his <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine;</hi> the other the ſweet ſavour of his <hi>Life.</hi> As for the four <hi>extraordinary</hi> Garments which the <hi>High Prieſt</hi> wore only once a year, to wit, when he entered into the <hi>Holy</hi> of <hi>Holies</hi> upon the <hi>Propitiation</hi> day, which were for colour <hi>white,</hi> (and therefore called <hi>Veſtimenta alba,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> white Garments) and for number four, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. The <hi>lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen Breeches.</hi> 2. The <hi>linnen Coat.</hi> 3. The <hi>linnen Gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle.</hi> 4. The <hi>linnen Mitre,</hi> Lev. 16. 4. Theſe (give me leave to ſay it) were not ſo much <hi>ſignes</hi> of <hi>Aarons;</hi> as <hi>Levitical Shaddows</hi> and <hi>Types</hi> of the <hi>Lord Chriſt</hi> (that <hi>immaculate Lambe of God,</hi> the <hi>Holy</hi> and <hi>Juſt One</hi>) his <hi>Purity</hi> and <hi>Innocency,</hi> the <hi>holineſs</hi> of his <hi>Perſon,</hi> and the <hi>Inculpableneſs</hi> of his <hi>Life;</hi> He was our <hi>holy, harmleſs, and undefiled High Prieſt,</hi> Heb. 7. 26.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Amandus Polanus</hi> indeed ſaith, that S. <hi>Paul</hi> in deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing and preſcribing the Chriſtians <hi>Panoplia</hi> and compleat Armour, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. doth allude to the <hi>Sacerdotal Veſtments</hi> under the Law, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Mitre, Breſt-plate, Girdle,</hi> &amp;c. But if the <hi>Chriſtian Clergy</hi>-Men ground the <hi>Myſtical ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificancy</hi> of <hi>Veſtments</hi> upon this, I know no reaſon why the <hi>Laity,</hi> and every Private Chriſtian may not challenge as good a right to the uſe of <hi>Mitre, Girdle, Surplice,</hi> &amp;c. as they, ſince it is incumbent upon every Chriſtian to <hi>put on the whole armour of God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>From what hath been ſaid it may appear, that the <hi>Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Veſtments</hi> under the Law, were <hi>Levitical ſhaddows,</hi> and <hi>Typical;</hi> and yet <hi>thoſe</hi> under the <hi>Goſpel</hi> are ſaid to be
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:29874:26"/> 
               <hi>Symbolical</hi> only, and <hi>Myſtically ſignificant;</hi> then the ſame <hi>Ceremonies</hi> are both <hi>Typical</hi> and <hi>Symbolical:</hi> Now if they were <hi>Typical,</hi> why are they not aboliſhed? If they were <hi>Symbolical</hi> according to our <hi>Biſhops</hi> (elſe why are they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the <hi>Goſpel</hi>-Church?) and (yet) <hi>Typical</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Polanus,</hi> and (as it is evident) then tis needful that they ſtudy another diſtinction then that of <hi>Typical</hi> and <hi>Symbolical</hi> Ceremonies; ſaying, that <hi>Typical</hi> Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies are all aboliſhed, but <hi>Symbolical</hi> Ceremonies may be retained in the <hi>Goſpel</hi>-Church.</p>
            <p>In concluſion,</p>
            <p>I deſire to be reſolved, what is the <hi>Myſtical ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> of a <hi>Mitre</hi> in a <hi>Chriſtian Biſhop?</hi> Not <hi>Dominion</hi> (I<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5. 3.</note> hope) <hi>over God's heritage?</hi> O! Leave that to the <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> who is taught of his <hi>Father the</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 8. 44.</note> 
               <hi>Devil</hi> to <hi>uſurp</hi> power over God's Inheritance, and to <hi>Lord it</hi> (as much as he can) over <hi>Conſciences,</hi> yea, over <hi>Crowns</hi> too, (but ſurely <hi>it was not ſo from the beginning,</hi> that the <hi>Crown</hi> ſhould be ſubject to the <hi>Mitre</hi>). Now</p>
            <p>The <hi>High Prieſt's Mitre,</hi> was (as I have ſhewed above) a <hi>Type</hi> of <hi>Chriſt's Regal Authority</hi> and <hi>Kingly Office.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is my ſecond anſwer to that diſtinction of <hi>Typical</hi> and <hi>Symbolical</hi> Ceremonies; more I might ſay, but I forbear.</p>
            <p>Only give me leave to add, That a <hi>Ceremonial Worſhip</hi> is aboliſhed, not only <hi>Chriſti CORPORE,</hi> but even <hi>Chriſti ORE;</hi> not only by the <hi>Body,</hi> but even by the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> of Chriſt, and his <hi>Perſonal</hi> teaching in the dayes of his fleſh; <hi>The hour cometh</hi> (ſaid he to the woman of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria) and now is, when the true Worſhippers ſhall worſhip the Father in ſpirit and in truth,</hi> John 4. 23. By <hi>worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the Father in ſpirit and in truth,</hi> we are to underſtand a <hi>Now</hi> and <hi>Evangelical</hi> manner of <hi>Worſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here then is principally intimated; Not</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Indiſpenſable Need</hi> of the <hi>Concurrence</hi> of <hi>God's Spirit</hi> with a ſoul in Divine Worſhip. Nor</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:29874:27"/>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Sincerity,</hi> or the <hi>Abſolute</hi> neceſſity of joyning the <hi>Inner</hi> with the <hi>Outward</hi> Man, the <hi>Soul</hi> with the <hi>Body</hi> in Divine Worſhip; for, did not the Religious and Devout <hi>Jewes,</hi> (yea, and for ought I know, many <hi>Samaritans</hi>) worſhip God <hi>thus,</hi> viz. by the ſpecial <hi>aſſiſtance</hi> of God's Spirit, and by a <hi>ſincere</hi> joyning of the <hi>Soul</hi> with the <hi>Body</hi> in his Worſhip, <hi>before?</hi> (it were an uncharitable part for me, or others to think otherwiſe) Now Chriſt doth here mean ſome <hi>New</hi> manner of Worſhip, by worſhipping the Father in <hi>ſpirit and in truth; Woman</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>believe me, the hour cometh, when ye ſhall neither in this Mountain, nor yet at Jeruſalem worſhip the Father,</hi> v. 21. <hi>But</hi> &amp;c. v. 23.</p>
            <p>That then which is chiefly intended here, is,</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Utter <hi>Abrogation</hi> of the <hi>Old Carnal</hi> and <hi>Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial</hi> Worſhip, as a thing meerly <hi>Typical</hi> (worſhipping <hi>in Spirit,</hi> being oppoſed thereunto, as <hi>Carnal;</hi> worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping <hi>in truth</hi> being oppoſed thereunto, as <hi>Typical</hi>) and the <hi>ſubſtitution</hi> of a <hi>New,</hi> and <hi>Evangelical</hi> Worſhip, free from <hi>Jewiſh Ceremonies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is probable that the <hi>Ceremonians</hi> will ſay,</p>
            <p>Though we make uſe of <hi>Ceremonies</hi> in Divine <hi>Worſhip,</hi> yet ours is not a <hi>Ceremonial worſhip;</hi> for we place not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in the <hi>Ceremonies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw. 1. Holineſs</hi> is placed in the <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> Ergo <hi>Worſhip.</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">lib. 5 ſ. 69.</note> 
               <hi>Hooker</hi> in his <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Policy,</hi> ſaith ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, <hi>that ſome dayes ought to be with men more holy then others;</hi> Contrary to <note n="*" place="margin">de Feſt. Chriſt cap. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Hoſpinian,</hi> who affirmeth that one day is not holier then another, in it ſelf, elſe (ſaith he) the <hi>Heathens</hi> are not to be blamed, who, attributing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents to inevitable <hi>fate,</hi> diſtinguiſh of <hi>lucky</hi> and <hi>unlucky</hi> dayes. But what ſhall I ſay? Are not mens <hi>adulterate</hi> practiſes ſhrewd ſymptomes thereof? as, Their Incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations and cringings before an <hi>Altar</hi> of ſtone; a nice and ſuperſtitious regard to a <hi>table</hi> of wood, which they encloſe as if it were a ſecond <hi>Holy</hi> of <hi>Holies;</hi> their <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout</hi> reſpect to a material ſtructure and fabrick, (which
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:29874:27"/> (yet) poſſibly in the dayes of old, was a Receptacle of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> yea and devoted thereunto); their declared ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularity (not to ſay <hi>ſanctity</hi>) of <hi>Veſtments,</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Procul O procul eſte prophani—</q>
            <p>and ſuch like; Are not (theſe I ſay) ſhrewd ſymptomes of the truth of what I ſay? But</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Ceremonies</hi> are purſued as things <hi>neceſſary</hi> to Divine Worſhip; <hi>Ergo</hi> &amp;c. Poſſibly they will not ſay that <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies</hi> are <hi>Eſſential</hi> parts of the Worſhip of God, (though as I ſhall preſently ſhew, ſome have even gone this length) yet I appeal to themſelves, whether they ground not a <hi>Neceſſity</hi> (yea an indiſpenſable one) at leaſt, on the <hi>Myſtical ſignificancy,</hi> or pretended, <hi>teaching</hi> ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue (They are reſolved to teach, if not <hi>Ore,</hi> yet <hi>more.</hi> Ah! dumb Teachers!) or pleaded <hi>order</hi> and <hi>decency</hi> of <hi>Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies,</hi> (though it were an eaſie matter to diſprove, as the <hi>neceſſity,</hi> ſo the <hi>expediency,</hi> yea, the pretended <hi>law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs</hi> and <hi>indifferency</hi> of them.) Now, <hi>Quaecunque ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervatio quaeſi neceſſaria commendatur, continuo cenſetur ad cultum Dei pertinere,</hi> ſaith <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>De vera Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. reſorm. p.</hi> 367.</note> 
               <hi>Calvin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay,</p>
            <p n="3">3. <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Burgeſs <hi>of the</hi> Lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>&amp;c. cap.</hi> 3. See <hi>D.</hi> Burgeſs <hi>cap. 15. p, 41, 42.</hi>
               </note> A great <hi>Formaliſt</hi> ſaith, That <hi>Ceremonies</hi> may be called <hi>Worſhip</hi> of God, not only <hi>ratione modi,</hi> but even <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione medii;</hi> not only as additional things belonging to the reverend uſe of God's preſcribed Worſhip; but alſo as a <hi>mean,</hi> though not by vertue of any thing in it ſelf, but by vertue of ſomwhat elſe. If ſo, with what face can they blame <hi>Papiſts,</hi> who place <hi>worſhip</hi> (indeed) in their <hi>Croſs</hi> &amp; <hi>Crucifix,</hi> but not by vertue of any thing in it ſelf, but in reſpect of <hi>Chriſt crucified,</hi> whom (ſay they) it repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents? Once more,</p>
            <p n="4">4. A thing pertains to the Worſhip of God, ſay the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ad cultum Dei pertinet aliquid dupli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citer, uno modo, cum cum aliquid Deo offertur; alio modo, cum aliquid Divinum aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitur.</hi> Aquin. 2. 2. Quaeſt. 95. Art. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Schoolmen,</hi> two manner of ways; viz. <hi>vel quoad oblatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, vel quoad aſſumptionem;</hi> either when we <hi>offer</hi> to God
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:29874:28"/> any thing in point of Worſhip, or when we <hi>add</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive</hi> any thing into his Worſhip: Hence they are guilty of a <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> and <hi>Ceremonial</hi> Worſhip, not only who <hi>offer</hi> to God for Worſhip, but alſo who <hi>aſſume</hi> in God's worſhip as ſacred, what God himſelf hath not ordained. Such are <hi>Jewiſh-Popiſh Ceremonies,</hi> Ergo <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus I have purſued at large the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of <hi>Reprehenſion,</hi> having reſpect to my Text: O that the Lord would ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond it with the powerful convictions of his Spirit!</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> Here is matter of <hi>Conſolation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beloved; Here is a <hi>Summary</hi> of <hi>Evangelical Comfort,</hi> here is the choiceſt thing that is diſplayed in <hi>Goſpel.</hi> What? A <hi>Redeemer</hi> for undone <hi>Mankinde!</hi> A <hi>Saviour</hi> for <hi>ſinners!</hi> And that one of their <hi>own fleſh</hi> and <hi>blood</hi> too! <hi>viz.</hi> The Son of God <hi>made of a woman.</hi> Here is <hi>Semen Mulicris,</hi> the * <hi>Seed of the Woman,</hi> which was <hi>five thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 15.</note> 
               <hi>yeers ago</hi> promiſed and preached, by <hi>God</hi> Himſelf, the firſt <hi>Evangeliſt,</hi> and Preacher of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Gospel; I will put enmity</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>between thee and the woman, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween thy ſeed, and her ſeed; and IT ſhall bruiſe thy head,</hi> &amp;c. This was the <hi>firſt Goſpel</hi> that ever was preached. The <hi>ſecond</hi> Evangeliſt was an <hi>Angel,</hi> who made a comfortable Sermon upon the ſame <hi>Text: Fear not</hi> (ſaid he to the Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds) <hi>for behold, I bring you good tydings of great joy; for unto you is born this day, in the City of David, a SAVIO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Luke</hi> 2. 10, 11. This <hi>Angelical</hi> was a truly <hi>Evangelical</hi> Sermon. It is well worthy of our obſervation, that an <hi>Angel</hi> was imployed in the firſt pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication of the <hi>Nativity</hi> of our Lord; and <hi>Goſpel</hi>-comfort redounding from thence to ſinful, undone, <hi>Man.</hi> But I would not, I muſt not be too prolix here. The comfort that doth accrue to poor, broken, captive ſinners, from <hi>God-Incarnate,</hi> may appear from an inſpection into the <hi>capital</hi> benefits, mentioned <hi>v.</hi> 5. viz.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Redemption.</item>
               <item>2. Adoption.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:29874:28"/>
            <p>God's great deſigne in aſſuming to himſelf our Nature, was (ſaith our Apoſtle) <hi>That he might 1. Redeem them that were under the Law. 2. That we might receive the Adoption of Sons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe be priviledges of the <hi>firſt magnitude,</hi> and they are <hi>gradual.</hi> In the one we are exempted from a <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile;</hi> In the other we are dignified with a <hi>Filial</hi> conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: By the one, we ceaſe to be <hi>Slaves;</hi> by the other, we become <hi>Sons.</hi> I ſhall (through mercy) ſpeak to both; (but to the latter more briefly) for diſplaying to the Saints <hi>Goſpel-comfort;</hi> which divides it ſelf here (as it were) into two ſtreams or channels.</p>
            <p>Of <hi>Chriſtian Liberty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. The firſt is <hi>Redemption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is a Believers <hi>Chriſtian Liberty,</hi> (that great <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelical Priviledge</hi>) wherein he is freed from his <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Bondage</hi> and <hi>Captivity,</hi> intimated while he is ſaid to be <hi>under the Law.</hi> Now</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſtian Liberty</hi> conſidered in its full Extent and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude hath in it theſe eight ſteps.</p>
            <p>1. The firſt is, <hi>Exemption</hi> from the <hi>Curſe</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning</hi> power of the <hi>Moral Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is a twofold <hi>Power</hi> in the <hi>Law.</hi> viz.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Mandatory.</item>
               <item>2. Damnatory.</item>
            </list>
            <p>A <hi>Commanding</hi> and a <hi>Condemning</hi> Power.</p>
            <p>And accordingly the <hi>Legal Obligation</hi> is two-fold, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Active.</item>
               <item>2. Penal.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>That</hi> is an Obligation to <hi>Duty; This</hi> is an Obligation to a <hi>Penalty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Mandatory</hi> and <hi>Directive</hi> Power of the Law is ever in <hi>force;</hi> for the <hi>Law</hi> is a ſtanding and <hi>Irreverſible Rule</hi> of <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Obedience.</hi> But</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Damnatory</hi> and <hi>Maledictive</hi> Power of the Law (by vertue whereof ſinful <hi>Delinquents</hi> are bound over to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:29874:29"/> 
               <hi>death;</hi> to a <hi>curſe</hi> and <hi>condigne</hi> puniſhment; (<hi>on the day thou eateſt thereof, thou ſhalt ſurely die,</hi> ſaid God to <hi>Adam</hi> concerning the <hi>Probational</hi> Tree of the Knowledge of good and evil, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 17.) is fully <hi>anſwered</hi> and <hi>diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>null'd</hi> for Believers, by Chriſt; for he hath <hi>redeemed us from the curſe of the Law, being made a curſe for us,</hi> Gal. 3. 13. Chriſt hath redeemed the Saints from the <hi>curſe,</hi> though not from the <hi>command</hi> of the Law. And in this ſenſe it is ſaid, that <hi>the Law is not made for a righteous perſon,</hi> 1 Tim. 1. 9. which therefore we muſt not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand in the <hi>Antinomians</hi> and looſe <hi>Libertines</hi> ſenſe, as if the Law were not at all <hi>Obligatory</hi> to a <hi>righteous</hi> perſon, binding him to <hi>holineſs</hi> and <hi>obedience;</hi> O no! The Law is ever <hi>recti-dica,</hi> but never <hi>male-dica</hi> to Believers. In a word;</p>
            <p>Believers are by Chriſt exempted from the <hi>Penal curſe, malediction,</hi> and <hi>condemnatory</hi> ſentence of the Law. So that</p>
            <p>Though (<hi>temporal) death</hi> is inevitably common both to the <hi>Redeemed,</hi> and to <hi>Reprobates;</hi> for <hi>it is</hi> (by an old in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Statute) <hi>appointed unto (all) men once to die,</hi> Heb. 9. 27. yet the <hi>Redeemed</hi> of the Lord are not lyable to <hi>death</hi> (nor indeed to any <hi>affliction</hi> whatſoever) by vertue of any <hi>maledictive influence</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> upon them. <hi>Mors illis nec abeſt, nec obeſt:</hi> though <hi>death</hi> is <hi>inevitable,</hi> yet it is not <hi>hurtful. Death</hi> is neceſſary in the Saints, not by way of <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> to injured <hi>Juſtice,</hi> (for Chriſt hath performed that, and Juſtice were not <hi>Juſtice</hi> if it ſhould require ſarisfaction <hi>twice</hi>): but (as I may ſay) by way of <hi>Introduction</hi> into <hi>Glory;</hi> they are by a bleſſed exchange poſſeſſed of <hi>Eternal</hi> Life, with the loſs of a <hi>Natural</hi> life. <hi>Death</hi> is not a <hi>Penal</hi> or <hi>Judicial</hi> thing in the Saints; for<note place="margin">Inane eſt deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium illud Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſticum de ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptione a poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no aeterna, ſed non a poena temporali.</note> the <hi>curſe</hi> and <hi>ſting</hi> is taken away. The ſame may be ſaid of all the Saints <hi>afflictions;</hi> they are not properly <hi>penal,</hi> but rather <hi>probational</hi> or <hi>caſtigatory; chaſtiſements</hi> rather then <hi>puniſhments;</hi> they are <hi>croſſes,</hi> not <hi>curſes; Medicinal,</hi> not <hi>Maledictory; Phyſick,</hi> not <hi>poyſon;</hi> for <hi>inſtruction,</hi> not
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:29874:29"/> for <hi>deſtruction.</hi> O! What comfort is that. There is not now <hi>mors in olla,</hi> the <hi>deadly pottage</hi> are healed; though I <hi>die,</hi> yet I ſhall not be <hi>damned,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond is exemption from the <hi>Rigour</hi> of the Law, and its <hi>Exaction</hi> of <hi>Inherent Righteouſneſs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Law in its ſtrictneſs and firſt conſtitution, did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of us <hi>perfect</hi> and <hi>perſonal Obedience,</hi> and that upon pain of <hi>death,</hi> according to its <hi>Active</hi> condition, <hi>Do this and live;</hi> Now the Son of God hath in our Nature <hi>ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied</hi> the <hi>Active</hi> demands of the Law, for Believers, as ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually, as if they themſelves had made <hi>perfect</hi> and <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal ſatisfaction</hi> thereunto: by vertue whereof they are exempted from the <hi>Rigid Exaction</hi> of the Law; that is, They are no longer obliged to the performance of Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence <hi>Legally perfect;</hi> nor obnoxious to <hi>vengeance</hi> of the <hi>curſe</hi> for their <hi>Legal</hi> defects.</p>
            <p>There is a two-fold Perfection to be conſidered, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A Perfection of <hi>Degrees.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Perfectio gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duum. Perfectio par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium.</note>
               </item>
               <item>2. A Perfection of <hi>Parts.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The former is <hi>Legal</hi> Perfection, and it ſtands in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to <hi>Imperfection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The latter is <hi>Evangelical</hi> Perfection, and it ſtands in oppoſition to <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> only; for this is that indiſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Goſpel</hi>-Qualification, <hi>Sincerity;</hi> This is <hi>new</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelical</hi> Obedience. Now</p>
            <p>Redeemed ones, are, by Chriſt, who performed Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, <hi>Perſonal</hi> and <hi>Perfect</hi> for them, exempted from the former, <hi>viz.</hi> the ſevere demands of <hi>obedience,</hi> abſolutely <hi>perfect</hi> upon pain of <hi>death;</hi> O what comfort is that to poor ſinners! Though many <hi>weakneſſes</hi> attend our <hi>duties,</hi> and many <hi>enormities</hi> our <hi>life;</hi> though it be as Natural for us to <hi>ſin,</hi> as for <hi>the ſpark to fly upwards;</hi> for (the Lord knows) It is <hi>Natural</hi> for us to <hi>do</hi> that, which without <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> would <hi>undo</hi> us. Yet the poor <hi>ſincere</hi> ſinner is in <hi>Chriſt</hi> accepted, his failings and <hi>defects</hi> being covered with the <hi>robes</hi> of the Lord Chriſt's <hi>righteouſneſs.</hi> God brings a
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:29874:30"/> Believers <hi>Obedience</hi> to the <hi>Touchſtone</hi> rather then to the <hi>Ballance;</hi> He <hi>tryes,</hi> not <hi>weighs</hi> it; He eyes the <hi>Quality,</hi> more then the <hi>Quantity;</hi> the <hi>thing,</hi> more then the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees;</hi> He judgeth of <hi>Evangelical</hi> Obedience, more by the <hi>Principle</hi> then by the <hi>Rule,</hi> by the <hi>Heart,</hi> then by the <hi>Law</hi> (conſidered <hi>in rigore</hi>); It is not; <hi>this,</hi> or <hi>that</hi> haſt thou done; this or that <hi>duty</hi> haſt thou <hi>omitted;</hi> this or that ſin haſt thou <hi>committed,</hi> &amp;c. But, <hi>thus,</hi> and <hi>thus</hi> was thy <hi>heart: If there be firſt a willing minde, it is</hi> (now) <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 8. 12.</note> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third is Exemption from the <hi>guilt</hi> of ſin.</p>
            <p>This is the <hi>Remiſſion</hi> of ſin in <hi>Juſtification;</hi> which is God's gracious <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Oblivion</hi> and <hi>Juridical Acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> (ſo to ſpeak) wherein he <hi>pardoneth</hi> ſin in the <hi>blood</hi> of Chriſt ſo, as that it ſhall not <hi>redound</hi> to the ſinners <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment.</hi> This is a ſingular piece of the Lord Chriſt's purchaſe. God <hi>gives</hi> his <hi>Son,</hi> and God doth in him <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give</hi> ſin. As the <hi>Reigning</hi> power of ſin is taken away in<note place="margin">Reatus pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti. Regnum peccati.</note> 
               <hi>ſanctification,</hi> ſo the <hi>guilt</hi> of ſin is taken off in <hi>juſtification;</hi> that is, the juſtified perſon is acquitted in Chriſt, ſo that God will never deal with him as a <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chriſtus ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipiendo poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam &amp; non ſuſcipiendo culpam, &amp; culpam delevit &amp; poenam.</hi> Aug. de verb. Dom. ſerm. 37.</note> 
               <hi>guilty</hi> perſon, or by way of <hi>puniſhment</hi> properly; for God doth remit both the <hi>guilt</hi> and the <hi>puniſhment:</hi> ſo that the <hi>afflictions</hi> and <hi>croſſes</hi> which juſtified perſons are expoſed to in the world (to ſpeak properly) are not <hi>penal,</hi> but rather <hi>probational,</hi> (as is ſhewed before) <hi>Chaſtiſements,</hi> not <hi>puniſhments;</hi> for <hi>probation,</hi> not for <hi>reprobation; Tollitur peccatum ſi non ne</hi> SIT, <hi>tamen ne</hi> OBSIT. O but this is matter of great comfort! I am pardoned now! the Articles of my peace are confirmed now! God is reconciled! I am acquitted! Although there is a <hi>defiling</hi> power in ſin, yet there is not a <hi>damning</hi> power in ſin! <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The fourth is Exemption from the <hi>Reigne</hi> and <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion</hi> of ſin.</p>
            <p>As in <hi>Juſtification,</hi> the <hi>vis Damnatrix</hi> and <hi>Guilt</hi> of ſin is removed; ſo in <hi>Sanctification,</hi> the <hi>Vis Dominatrix</hi> and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:29874:30"/> 
               <hi>Reigne</hi> of ſin is removed. There <hi>tollitur peccatum, ne</hi> OBSIT; Here <hi>tollitur peccatum, ne</hi> PRAESIT; There ſin loſeth its <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam non ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutus ſed ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitus,</hi> Bernar. Serm. 26. in Cant.</note> 
               <hi>ſting,</hi> Here ſin loſeth its <hi>ſtrength.</hi> A Perſon is in <hi>Sanctification</hi> exempted, though not from the <hi>Preſence,</hi> yet from the <hi>Power</hi> of ſin; though not from the <hi>Tyrannie,</hi> yet from the <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 6. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Dominion</hi> of ſin; though not from the <hi>Rage,</hi> yet from the <hi>Reigne</hi> of ſin; though not from the <hi>permanency,</hi> yet from the <hi>predominancy</hi> of ſin; from the power <hi>of,</hi> though not from a power <hi>to</hi> ſin. A <hi>ſanctified</hi> ſoul is neither a <hi>Throne</hi> not a <hi>Sepulchre</hi> to ſin; though ſin <hi>remains</hi> there, yet ſin <hi>reignes</hi> not there; <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 6. 1, 2.</note> though ſin <hi>continues</hi> in <hi>It,</hi> yet <hi>It</hi> continues not <hi>in ſin;</hi> O poor Soul! though ſin do ſore <hi>preſs</hi> thee, yet it ſhall not <hi>oppreſs</hi> thee; the <hi>Spirit of Sanctification</hi> frees the ſoul from its <hi>Native Captivity</hi> and bondage to ſin. This is a ſpecial part of our <hi>Redemption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. The fifth is Exemption from <hi>Satanical bondage</hi> and <hi>ſubjection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Men</hi> are by Nature (as <hi>Sins,</hi> ſo) <hi>Satans Captives;</hi> but <hi>the Son of God made of a woman,</hi> hath <hi>led captivity captive.</hi> He is the <hi>Seed of the woman,</hi> that ſhould <hi>bruiſe the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents head.</hi> He is the LYON <hi>of the Tribe of Judah,</hi> who hath over powered that <hi>Roaring Lyon,</hi> and <hi>hath ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Principalities and Powers:</hi> The Son of God took upon him our Nature, <hi>that through death he might deſtroy him that had the power of death, that is the Devil,</hi> Heb. 2. 14. The Son of God became <hi>Man,</hi> that he might <hi>deſtroy</hi> the <hi>Devil,</hi> in the <hi>ſame Nature</hi> that the <hi>Devil</hi> had <hi>deſtroyed. Satan</hi> is now become <hi>ſubject</hi> to <hi>thoſe,</hi> who once were <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> to <hi>him. Lord, even the</hi> DEVILS <hi>are ſubject to</hi> US <hi>through thy Name,</hi> ſaid the Diſciples, <hi>Luke</hi> 10. 17. O how is our <hi>captivity</hi> turn'd! The <hi>Prince</hi> of Darkneſs is become <hi>ſubject</hi> to the meaneſt <hi>Diſciple</hi> of Chriſt. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the <hi>Natural</hi> tye that is upon <hi>Satan,</hi> (he being a <hi>creature,</hi> and therefore of a <hi>limitted</hi> capacity) by reaſon whereof he <hi>cannot</hi> do the evil he <hi>would;</hi> there is a
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:29874:31"/> 
               <hi>Providential</hi> tye, by reaſon whereof he <hi>doth</hi> not the evil he <hi>can;</hi> yea, and a purchaſed exemption from <hi>ſubjection</hi> to him.</p>
            <p>We muſt diſtinguiſh between 1. <hi>Subjection</hi> to <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation.</hi> And 2. <hi>Subjection</hi> to the <hi>Tempter.</hi> The <hi>leaſt</hi> of Saints are freed from the latter; though the <hi>beſt</hi> of Saints are not (in this life) ſecure from the former. O what comfort is this to a Militant Saint! What though Satan <hi>attempt</hi> thy <hi>ruine?</hi> yet know, that Chriſt will <hi>ruine</hi> the <hi>attempt;</hi> He may <hi>diſquiet</hi> thee, but he cannot <hi>deſtroy</hi> thee; he may bruiſe thy <hi>heel,</hi> but is it not the work of <hi>the Seed of the woman</hi> to break his <hi>head? Satan</hi> is Chriſt's <hi>Captive</hi> in <hi>chains.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. The ſixth is Exemption from <hi>Legal terrors,</hi> and <hi>fear</hi> of <hi>Wrath, Hell, Death,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The former was a freedom from <hi>bondage</hi> to <hi>Spirits,</hi> this<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Rom. 8. 15. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 2 Tim. 1. 7.</note> is a freedom from the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>bondage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O what fears and terrors is a <hi>Reprobate</hi> Conſcience poſſeſſed withal! The <hi>Law</hi> is violated, <hi>Wrath</hi> is incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>Hell</hi> and <hi>damnation</hi> is deſerved, as condigne puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; the dreadful purſuits of <hi>ſin-revenging Juſtice</hi> are unavoidable; my own <hi>Conſcience</hi> accuſeth me. O the <hi>condemnatory</hi> voice of Conſcience! that <hi>Boſome-hell!</hi> Miſerable Man that I am; What will become of me? Where ſhall I <hi>dwell for ever?</hi> Who ſhall be my <hi>compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions</hi> to all eternity? <hi>Damned</hi> Spirits? or <hi>the Spirits of juſt men made perfect?</hi> Such terrors and fears are (as it were) a <hi>Preface</hi> and <hi>Introduction</hi> to hell. Now <hi>Redeemed ones</hi> are free from thoſe <hi>Legal terrors,</hi> and in ſtead of a <hi>Spirit of bondage,</hi> they are poſſeſſed of the <hi>Spirit of Adoption,</hi> whereby <hi>they cry Abba, Father;</hi> And this is that which breeds comfort in life, and confidence at death in the children of God.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The ſeventh is Exemption from the <hi>Ceremonial</hi> and <hi>Judicial</hi> Lawes of <hi>Moſes;</hi> That Unſupportable <hi>Yoke, which neither the</hi> modern <hi>Jews, nor their fathers were able to bear.</hi> Acts 15. 10.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:29874:31"/>
            <p>
               <hi>This</hi> freedom and <hi>Immunity</hi> are we in a more eſpecial manner to underſtand by <hi>Redemption</hi> in the Text. The <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, like an <hi>Heir</hi> during his <hi>minority,</hi> was ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to a <hi>Pedagogie,</hi> viz. the <hi>Ceremonial</hi> and <hi>Judicial</hi> Laws of <hi>Moſes,</hi> in which reſpect the ſtate of the <hi>Jewes</hi> ſeemed to be a <hi>ſervile</hi>-ſtate; but <hi>when the fulneſs of the time was come</hi> (even the time of the Churches maturity and riper age) <hi>God ſent forth his Son made of a woman, to redeem</hi> his Church from that <hi>bondage</hi> and <hi>ſervitude.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There were three <hi>Laws</hi> committed to the <hi>Jewes,</hi> viz.</p>
            <list>
               <label>The</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Moral.</item>
                     <item>2. Ceremonial.</item>
                     <item>3. Judicial.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The <hi>Moral</hi> Law was ordained to be a ſtanding and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alterable <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Obedience,</hi> both to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church. The <hi>Ceremonial</hi> and <hi>Judicial</hi> Lawes were <hi>Appendices</hi> of the <hi>Moral</hi> Law. The <hi>Ceremonial,</hi> of the <hi>firſt</hi> Table, determining the particulars of that <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> which was <hi>peculiar</hi> to the <hi>Church</hi> of the <hi>Jewes;</hi> The <hi>Judicial,</hi> of the <hi>ſecond</hi> Table, determining the particulars of that <hi>Policy,</hi> which was <hi>peculiar</hi> to the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> of the <hi>Jewes.</hi> So that the <hi>Ceremonial</hi> contained the <hi>Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical</hi> Lawes of that <hi>Church,</hi> and did reſpect God. The <hi>Judicial,</hi> the <hi>Civil</hi> Lawes of that <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> and did reſpect their <hi>Neighbour.</hi> Now</p>
            <p>Chriſt did in the fulneſs of the time redeem his Church both from the <hi>Ceremonial</hi> and <hi>Judicial</hi> Laws, as a <note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 5. 1.</note> 
               <hi>yoke of bondage,</hi> impoſed not upon the <hi>necks,</hi> but even upon the <hi>Conſciences</hi> of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> binding them to a ſtrict and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curate obſervation of the ſame.</p>
            <p>As touching the <hi>Judicial</hi> and <hi>Civil</hi> Law.</p>
            <p>What things ſoever contained therein were <hi>communis juris,</hi> of <hi>common Equity,</hi> and had a foundation in the Law of <hi>Nature,</hi> and might be enforced by the Law <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,</hi> are ſtill <hi>Obligatory</hi> to <hi>Chriſtians:</hi> But, what was <hi>pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar</hi> to the conſtitution of the <hi>Judaical Policy,</hi> and are not
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:29874:32"/> enforceable by any <hi>common Right,</hi> but were the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar poſitive Laws of the <hi>Jewes;</hi> do not more binde Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians then any other <hi>Municipal</hi> Law. For Chriſt deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Jewiſh Commonwealth,</hi> their <hi>Temple,</hi> and <hi>City,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Propheſie of <hi>Daniel,</hi> chap. 9. v. 26, 27. did withall abrogate and deſtroy the whole <hi>Jewiſh Policy</hi> and <hi>Lawes.</hi> And thus it is ſaid, <hi>The Prieſthood</hi> (namely of <hi>Aaron) being changed, there is made of neceſſity a change alſo of the Law</hi> (namely of <hi>Moſes</hi>) Heb. 7. 12.</p>
            <p>As touching the <hi>Ceremonial</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Law.</p>
            <p>That (together with the <hi>Judicial</hi> Law) might be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in a fourfold reſpect, as is evident from Scripture, <hi>viz.</hi> as</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A <hi>Badge</hi> of <hi>diſtinction</hi> between the <hi>Jewes</hi> and all other Nations, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 13, 14.</item>
               <item>2. A <hi>Ratified ſigne</hi> of <hi>Guilt,</hi> Col. 2. 14.</item>
               <item>3. A <hi>Typical Adumbration</hi> of Chriſt and his Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 9, 10.</item>
               <item>4. A <hi>Tutor</hi> and <hi>Schoolmaſter</hi> to the <hi>Infant</hi>-Church, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 1, 2, 3. Now</item>
            </list>
            <p>The <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church is freed from the <hi>Ceremonial,</hi> (as from the <hi>Judicial</hi>) Law, in all theſe reſpects. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Chriſt hath <hi>broken down the middle-wall of partition</hi> between <hi>Jewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 14, 15.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Chriſt hath <hi>aboliſhed and taken out of the way the hand-writing of Ordinances, which was againſt us,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 14.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Typified Body</hi> of <hi>Levitical ſhaddows</hi> and <hi>Adumbrations</hi> (Col. 2. 17.) is come.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>When the fulneſs of the time was come, God ſent forth his Son made of a woman,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>to redeem them that were under the Law,</hi> (his Church) from a <hi>Moſaical Pedagogie</hi> and <hi>Elements.</hi> Gal. 4. 4, 5. Then</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Ceremonies</hi> are not things <hi>Indifferent</hi> in the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church. They were abrogated by the Son of God, whoſe deſigne in coming in the fleſh, was, <hi>to redeem</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:29874:32"/> his Church from that <hi>Legal Yoke;</hi> ſo that to obtrude them upon the <hi>Goſpel</hi>-Church, were to fruſtrate Chriſtians of one great <hi>End</hi> of the <hi>Incarnation;</hi> and to infringe their <hi>Chriſtian Liberty.</hi> (O! How ſad is it when men purſue <hi>Iniquities</hi> for <hi>Indifferencies!) Ergo,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Do Caſ. Conſ. lib. 4. cap. 11. Caſ. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Baldwin</hi> in his <hi>Caſes of Conſcience</hi> hath a paſſage which I cannot omit. <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth cauſed a wretched book called INTERIM, to be publiſhed, wherein yeild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Croſs, Surplice, Holy-dayes,</hi> and other Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies was enjoyned, conformity thereunto being much urged by ſome furious Zelots, who pleaded the <hi>Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours</hi> Commandment in a thing <hi>Indifferent;</hi> the <hi>non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming</hi> Proteſtants replyed, That the Queſtion was not about a thing <hi>Indifferent,</hi> &amp;c. The ſame Reply might we make to thoſe that urge the <hi>Ceremonies</hi> as <hi>Indifferent</hi> things: How can thoſe be ſaid to be things <hi>Indifferent;</hi> which Chriſt hath <hi>aboliſhed?</hi> From which he hath <hi>Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> his Church?</p>
            <p n="2">2. How impudent is the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in burthening <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> with a <hi>yoke which neither they nor their fathers were ever able to bear;</hi> namely, a heap of <hi>ſuperfluous,</hi> yea <hi>ridiculous,</hi> yea <hi>impious</hi> and <hi>Antichriſtian Ceremonies?</hi> But<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sunt pompae iſtae omnes &amp; Ceremoniae Papiſticae, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil aliud quam furi meretricii, ad hoc excogitati, ut homines ad ſpiritualem ſcortationem alliciantur.</hi> Zanchy ad Regin. Elizab. Epiſtol. lib. 1. pag. 112.</note> this is like her. Though they are a <hi>burthen</hi> to the better ſort of Chriſtians, yet they are a part of her <hi>Whoriſh paint,</hi> whereby ſhe endeavours to allure Chriſtians to partake of the <hi>cup of her Fornications.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Ceremonies</hi> of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> impoſed upon the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church were an <hi>Antichriſtian yoke.</hi> What in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolent <hi>Tyrannie</hi> is it then in the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude old <hi>Rotten Ceremonies,</hi> together with a monſtrous heap of her own curſed hatching, upon <hi>Chriſtians?</hi> (I pray God profeſſed <hi>Proteſtants</hi> take not pattern by her) its ſufficient proof that ſhe is <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> and that
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:29874:33"/> THE MYSTERIE OF INIQUITY is at<note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2. 7.</note> work there. By reaſon of ſuch execrable <hi>Tyrannie,</hi> the caſe of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> (I ſpeak it with much regret) is abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly more ſad, and their condition more <hi>ſervile</hi> then was that of the <hi>Jewes;</hi> O what pity is that! <hi>Obſerve,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Ceremonies</hi> were impoſed upon the <hi>Jewiſh,</hi> by <hi>God</hi> himſelf; They are impoſed upon the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church, by <hi>Men</hi> like our ſelves: There the <hi>Jews</hi> were the <hi>ſervants</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> Here <hi>Chriſtians</hi> are made <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 7. 23.</note> 
               <hi>the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of Men.</hi> Nay,</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Jewiſh</hi> was an <hi>Infant</hi>-Church, the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> is a <hi>ripe</hi> and <hi>Adult</hi>-Church; The <hi>Jewiſh</hi>-Church was like an <hi>Heir</hi> under Age, and more <hi>ſervile;</hi> The <hi>Chriſtian</hi>-Church is like an <hi>Heir</hi> come at Age, and a <hi>Redeemed Son,</hi> ſo that <hi>Ceremonies</hi> are more intollerable in the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church. O how <hi>derogatory</hi> are they to the <hi>Ripe</hi> and <hi>Mature</hi> age of the Church? <hi>Num puereſcit Eccleſia?</hi> Shall the <hi>Church</hi> alwayes be a <hi>childe?</hi> Away then with <hi>Pedagogical</hi> and <hi>childiſh Ceremonies.</hi> For my part, I think, that the <hi>Riper</hi> and more <hi>Mature</hi> the Church is, the more <hi>impertinent</hi> (to ſay no more) are <hi>Ceremonies;</hi> and therefore, the <hi>ſixteen hundred yeers</hi> (the Age) of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church conſidered, the <hi>Ceremonies</hi> are infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly more <hi>impertinent</hi> and <hi>ſlaviſh</hi> (I ſay no more) <hi>now,</hi> then they were in the time of her <hi>Infancy,</hi> yea, then they were in the <hi>fifth,</hi> yea, then they were in the <hi>tenth</hi> Century, (<hi>&amp; ſic deinceps) Ergo, &amp;c.</hi> Further,</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Ceremonies</hi> were <hi>aboliſhed</hi> by Him, of whom they were <hi>appointed,</hi> namely, by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <note n="*" place="margin">Col. 1. 18.</note> 
               <hi>Head of the Church:</hi> In the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church they are <hi>appointed</hi> to them, for whom they were <hi>aboliſhed;</hi> namely, by ſome <hi>Members</hi> (rather <note n="*" place="margin">The <hi>Pope</hi> is ſo far from being the <hi>Head,</hi> that I had rather call him a <hi>Monſter</hi> in, then a <hi>Member</hi> of the Church.</note> 
               <hi>Monſters</hi>) of the Church.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:29874:33"/>
            <p>But</p>
            <p n="4">4. What more horrid <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> then to rob <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> of that <hi>Liberty</hi> and Freedome, which the Lord <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath procured and purchaſed for them with the <hi>meritoricus price</hi> of his <hi>deareſt blood?</hi> Now ſuch is their <hi>Exemption</hi> from the <hi>ſervile yoke</hi> of <hi>Rites</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> in the Worſhip of God under the <hi>Goſpel</hi> Ergo, &amp;c. Ah! <hi>Rome! Rome! The Lord rebuke thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quamvis e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim neque hoc inveniri poſſit, quomodo contra fidem ſint; ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam tamen Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligionem, quam Dei miſerecor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia liberam eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe voluit, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilibus oneri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus premunt: ut tolerabilior ſit conditio Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeorum, qui etiamſi tempus libertatis non agnoverunt, legalibus tamen ſarcinis, non Humanis praeſumptionibus ſubjiciuntur.</hi> Aug. <hi>ad</hi> Januar. de Ritibus Eccleſ. Epiſt. 119. cap. 19. <hi>Vid.</hi> Aug. <hi>ad</hi> Januar. de Variis Conſuetud. Region. Epiſt. 118. cap. 2.</note> S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> complained grievouſly of <hi>Ceremonies</hi> wherewith the Church was burthened in his time; (O how much more may we complain of the ſame in our time!)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Although</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>they were not things contrary to the Analogie of Faith, yet Religion which God in mercy</hi> and pity (to his Church) <hi>would have to be free, is burthened thereby, as with a ſlaviſh yoke; inſomuch that the ſervile condition of the Jewes was more tollerable</hi> (then that of <hi>Chriſtians) becauſe they were ſubject to</hi> LEGAL <hi>and Divine Impoſitions, not to</hi> HUMAN <hi>Preſumptions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> complained that in his dayes the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church was more plagued and burthened with rotten <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> then was the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church in her time. I pray God <hi>We</hi> have not cauſe to complain, that <hi>the Church is burthened with a heavier yoke</hi> in <hi>our</hi> dayes, then ſhe was in S. <hi>Auguſtines time;</hi> Where then were our <hi>Chriſtian pre-eminence</hi> to the <hi>Jewes?</hi> Mens <hi>fiercely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zealous contentions</hi> for a <hi>numerous</hi> heap of <hi>Jewiſh-Popiſh Ceremonies</hi> and <hi>Innovations</hi> in the <hi>Worſhip</hi> of God, are ſad, ſad <hi>Prognoſticks</hi> thereof. Give me leave to add, That the <hi>Retention</hi> and purſuance of ſuch things in the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church, would prove,</p>
            <p n="1">1. A <hi>Load</hi> and <hi>burthen</hi> to <hi>Religion;</hi> and then might it not juſtly be feared, that <hi>Religion</hi> it ſelf would become
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:29874:34"/> 
               <hi>burthenſome?</hi> O let Men take heed, leſt, by <hi>burthening Religion</hi> (as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> phraſeth it) they make <hi>Religion</hi> become a <hi>burthen!</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. A <hi>Bar</hi> to the <hi>Jewes converſion.</hi> I much wonder, with what confidence we could Wooe or Court the <hi>Jew</hi> to <hi>our</hi> Religion, as long as we preſs or retain a <hi>Legal yoke</hi> of <hi>Ceremonies</hi> in the Worſhip of God, which in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects aforeſaid, is more intollerable, then was <hi>that, which neither the (later) Jews,</hi> nor <hi>their fathers were able to bear,</hi> we ſhould urge them but with mean ſucceſs, to caſt off a <hi>Divine,</hi> and to ſubmit their necks to a <hi>Human</hi> yoke; Sure the <hi>Jew</hi> might hope for Exemption from the <hi>hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>writing of Ordinances,</hi> and burthenſome <hi>obſervance</hi> of <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Types</hi> and <hi>Shaddows,</hi> by the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> when come; But alas, their <hi>hopes</hi> would receive little life or ſtrength from the <hi>Gospel</hi>-Church! Nay</p>
            <p>Is not their <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief</hi> and <hi>Incredulity</hi> touching the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> ſtrengthened and confirmed from the retention of thoſe very things in the <hi>Chriſtian</hi>-Church, whereby he was typed and preſigured? Is it not probable that this might prove an <hi>Obſtruction</hi> to their <hi>converſion?</hi> For ought I know, had not <hi>adulterate Rome</hi> been in the way, JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RUSALEM had borrowed as much from LON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DON (long ere now) as ROME hath from JERU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SALEM, in point of <hi>Divine Worſhip;</hi> What? And are <hi>Ceremonies</hi> ſtill a <note n="*" place="margin">Eph. 2. 14.</note> 
               <hi>middle wall of Partition</hi> between <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. A <hi>Hinderance</hi> and <hi>Impediment</hi> to the <hi>Churches gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual Excellencies, growth,</hi> and <hi>propagation.</hi> The <hi>Riper</hi> and more <hi>mature</hi> the Church is, ſhe ſhould be for <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> more <hi>Eminent;</hi> for <hi>Doctrine</hi> more <hi>Powerful;</hi> for <hi>Diſcipline</hi> more <hi>Regular;</hi> for <hi>Worſhip</hi> more <hi>Pure;</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In concluſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ceremonies</hi> may not be retained;</p>
            <p>1. As a <hi>Wall of Partition</hi> between <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles.</hi> Nor 2. As a <hi>ſigne of ſin-guiltineſs.</hi> Nor 3. As <hi>Typical</hi>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:29874:34"/> and <hi>Figurative.</hi> Nor 4. As <hi>Rudimental</hi> or <hi>Pedagogical.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(For that were to <hi>Judaize.</hi>)</p>
            <p>Nor 5. As things <hi>Sacred</hi> and <hi>Holy.</hi> Nor 6. As <hi>matter</hi> of <hi>Worſhip.</hi> Nor 7. As matters of <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> and <hi>Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory</hi> to <hi>Conſcience.</hi> Nor 8. As things of a <hi>Spiritual Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacy.</hi> Nor 9. As matters of <hi>Merit.</hi> Nor 10. As mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Perfection.</hi> Nor 11. As things of a <hi>Teaching</hi> Quality. (The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is like to be well taught) but do they not in point of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> tend more to <hi>deſtruction</hi> then to <hi>inſtruction?</hi>) Well,</p>
            <p>That were to <hi>Romanize.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor 12. When <hi>Scandal</hi> doth from thence accrue to ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Conſciences. Nor 13. When they are abuſed to <hi>Idolatry</hi> or <hi>Superſtition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If theſe reſpects be excluded from the <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> a very little matter would make me (<hi>caeteris paribus</hi>) turn <hi>Proſelyte.</hi> I am for <hi>Ornamenta,</hi> but not for <hi>Onera</hi> in the Church. They miſerably err (in my minde) who inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret the Churches <hi>Burthen</hi> to be the Churches <hi>Beauty!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus I have diſpatched the ſeventh ſtep of <hi>Chriſtian</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Liberty.</p>
            <p>8. The eighth (which is conſequentially dependant thereon) is Exemption from all <hi>Bond</hi> of <hi>Conſcience</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of things <hi>Indifferent;</hi> theſe are things neither <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded</hi> nor <hi>forbidden</hi> in the <hi>Eternal Law of God.</hi> This is in a more eſpecial manner called <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> and it hath a two-fold reference; namely,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. To the <hi>Creatures</hi> of God.</item>
               <item>2. To <hi>Humane Ordinances</hi> in things <hi>Indifferent.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>1. As touching the <hi>Creatures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſtians are <hi>freed</hi> from <hi>ſcrupuloſity</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> in reſpect of them, and from the <hi>Legal</hi> obſervance of the <hi>difference</hi> of <hi>meats, clean</hi> and <hi>unclean,</hi> made by the <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonial</hi> Law, <hi>that</hi> being taken away under the <hi>Goſpel:</hi> Hence ſaid Chriſt, <hi>Not that which goeth into the mouth defileth a man,</hi> Matth. 15. 11. And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> after
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:29874:35"/> him, <hi>I know, and am perſwaded by the Lord Jeſus, that there is nothing unclean</hi> (or common) * <hi>of it ſelf,</hi> Rom. 14.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 14. Now, <hi>Every creature of God is good, and nothing to be refuſed, if it be received with Thanksgiving,</hi> 1 Tim. 4. 4. Now, <hi>all things are lawful,</hi> 1 Cor. 6. 12. Now, <hi>unto the pure all things are pure,</hi> Tit. 1. 15. This <hi>Liberty</hi> is an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelical Priviledge, whereby a true Chriſtian may with a <hi>ſafe</hi> and <hi>free</hi> Conſcience, <hi>uſe</hi> or <hi>forbear</hi> any of the <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> of God appointed for his uſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As touching the <hi>Ordinances</hi> of <hi>Men</hi> in things <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different.</hi> Certain it is, that the <hi>Conſcience</hi> of a Chriſtian cannot be <hi>bound</hi> thereby, but is <hi>free</hi> from the <hi>Obligatory</hi> vertue of all <hi>Human Commandments.</hi> For my more diſtinct proceeding, I ſhall expreſs my ſelf in theſe following pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, whereof ſome be gradual.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <note n="*" place="margin">Vid. <hi>Ameſ.</hi> de <hi>Conſ,</hi> lib. 1. cap. 2. <hi>Perk.</hi> Treat. of <hi>Conſ.</hi> cap. 2. ſect. 3. <hi>Alſted.</hi> Theol. <hi>Caf. cap. 2.</hi>
               </note> He is ſaid to <hi>binde the Conſcience,</hi> who hath ſuch a ſtrict and <hi>Immediate Authority</hi> over it, as that <hi>Conſcience</hi> ought to be <hi>ſubject</hi> thereunto; inſomuch that what is <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary</hi> to it, is <hi>ſin.</hi> A <hi>binding</hi> Power, is an <hi>Ordering</hi> and (as it were) a <hi>Coactive</hi> Power. To urge and enforce <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ad aſſenſum vel diſſenſum,</hi> to <hi>aſſent</hi> to a thing <hi>as law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,</hi> or that ought to be done, or to <hi>diſſent</hi> from a thing as <hi>unlawful,</hi> or that ought not to be done, may be ſaid to <hi>binde Conſcience. Vid.</hi> Ameſ. <hi>de</hi> Conſ. <hi>lib. 1. cap. 3. Item</hi> Calv. <hi>Inſtit. lib. 4. cap.</hi> 10. § 5.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>God</hi> alone can <hi>bind Conſcience.</hi> And in this ſenſe, <hi>He</hi> is ſaid to be our <hi>only Law-giver,</hi> Jam. 4. 12. <hi>Imperial Authority</hi> and <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> over <hi>Conſcience</hi> is <hi>peculiar</hi> to <hi>God</hi> alone. Hence ſaith <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Com.</hi> in 1 <hi>Pet. 5. 3. Neque enim cum huminibus ſed cum uno Deo, negotium eſt Conſcientiis noſtris,</hi> Calvin. Inſtit. <hi>lib. 4. cap. 10. Sect. 5. Erga animas &amp; conſcientias noſtras, nemini quicquam juris niſi Deo.</hi> Tilen. <hi>Synt. part. 2. Diſp. 32. Thef. 4. Liberi ſumus ab omnibus humanis Ritibus, Quantum quidem ad Conſcientiam attinet.</hi> Hemming. <hi>Enchyr. claſ. 3. cap. 14. Ab omni traditionum huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narum jugo, liberas habent conſcientias (fideles) cum ſolius Dei ſit, res ad Religionem pertinentes praeſcribere.</hi> Profeſſ. Leidenſ. <hi>Synt. pur. Theol. Diſp.</hi> 35. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Luther, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num Dominum habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, qui animas noſtras gubernat;</hi> We have but <hi>one Lord</hi> and <hi>Governour</hi> of our <hi>ſouls.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:29874:35"/>
            <p>From hence it is evident, that the <hi>binding</hi> and <hi>obliging</hi> Power over the <hi>Conſcience</hi> is <hi>peculiar</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> But</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Lawes</hi> of God, wherein were determined thoſe particulars which are neither <hi>commanded</hi> nor <hi>forbidden</hi> in the <hi>Moral</hi> Law of God, are <hi>abrogated;</hi> Now thoſe were the <hi>Ceremonial</hi> and <hi>Judicial</hi> Laws of <hi>Moſes;</hi> the one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining <hi>Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> the other <hi>Civil</hi> matters, <hi>peculiar</hi> to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, and Commonwealth. From both which <hi>Chriſt</hi> (as hath been ſaid) hath exempted the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church. Now</p>
            <p n="4">4. The <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>Men</hi> (whether <hi>Civil</hi> or <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> (as <hi>ſuch</hi>) are not properly <hi>Binding</hi> or <hi>Obligatory</hi> to <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. God</hi> is (as hath been ſaid) the <hi>ſole Lord</hi> of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</hi> As for <hi>Human Laws</hi> and <hi>Ordinances;</hi> neither is <hi>ſimple Obedience</hi> due unto them; neither doth a thing which in reſpect of the <hi>Law Moral</hi> is <hi>Indifferent,</hi> that is, neither <hi>commanded</hi> nor <hi>forbidden,</hi> by vertue of them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>ſimply neceſſary.</hi> They are <hi>Declarative</hi> only, not <hi>Authoritative:</hi> that is, they <hi>declare</hi> what is <hi>fitteſt</hi> to be done in things which are <hi>Indifferent,</hi> and cannot be enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, either by the Law of <hi>God</hi> or <hi>Nature.</hi> There is in them a <hi>Directive</hi> Power, but not a <hi>Coactive Juriſdiction.</hi> They have only <hi>vim dirigendi &amp; monendi</hi> ſaith <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Synt. part. 2. Diſp. 27. Theſ.</hi> 39. <hi>Vid.</hi> Marcum Antonium <hi>de Dom. de Repub. Eccleſ. lib. 5. cap. 2. N.</hi> 12 Chem. <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>am. 2. de bon. Oper. p.</hi> 179. Calvin. <hi>Inſtit. lib. 4. cap. 10. Sect.</hi> 6. Ameſ. <hi>de Conſ. lib. 1. cap. 2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Tilenus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And hence is that charge of the Apoſtle to the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians, Ye are bought with a price, be not ye the ſervants of</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7. 23.</note> 
               <hi>men,</hi> (which we are not to underſtand of <hi>ſubjection</hi> to <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> or of <hi>External</hi> ſervitude, but of the <hi>bondage</hi> of <hi>Conſcience.</hi>) And that to the <hi>Coloſſians, Let no man</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 2. 16.</note> 
               <hi>judge you</hi> (or uſurp power over the Conſcience) <hi>in meat, or in drink, or in reſpect of a holy day.</hi> And hence is that ſharp reproof, <hi>Why are ye ſubject to Ordinances, Touch not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 2. 20, 21.</note> 
               <hi>Taſte not, Handle not?</hi> that is, Why do ye obſerve <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:29874:36"/> Traditions, as if the Conſcience were bound by them? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Conc. Trid. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſſ. 4.</note> Curſed is the Tyrannie of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, which impoſeth her Heterodox <hi>Traditions</hi> upon <hi>Conſcience,</hi> teaching that they are with like reverence to be embraced, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Written Word</hi> of God.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The <hi>Oligatory</hi> and <hi>Binding</hi> Power of <hi>Human Laws,</hi> whether <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> or <hi>Civil,</hi> is, <hi>Vis quaedam Divina, Divine Authority.</hi> This is <hi>Ratio Legis,</hi> the very <hi>Reaſon</hi> of the <hi>Law;</hi> without which the <hi>Law</hi> it ſelf can never <hi>bind.</hi> There muſt be more of REASON then of WILL in all <hi>Human</hi> Ordinances; though WILL without enquiry after REASONS, is <hi>Obligatory</hi> in <hi>Divine</hi> Ordinances: Now the REASON of <hi>Man's Law,</hi> can be no other, then the WILL of <hi>God</hi> in his Law.</p>
            <p>As touching <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Laws.</p>
            <p>It is not the <hi>Authority</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> of <hi>Councils,</hi> or <hi>Convocations,</hi> but the <hi>Matter</hi> of the Canon, not <hi>Ratio Precipientis,</hi> but <hi>Ratio Praecepti,</hi> that <hi>bindes.</hi> In a word,</p>
            <p>There muſt be in all <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Laws</hi> and <hi>Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, 1. Conformity</hi> to the <hi>Word</hi> of God, that is the <hi>Rule.</hi> 2. They muſt <hi>Manifeſtam <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tilitatem prae ſe ferre</hi> (ſaith <note n="*" place="margin">Inſtit. lib. 4. cap. 10. Sect. 32</note> 
               <hi>Calvin</hi>) they muſt ſerve as to the <hi>Glory</hi> of God, ſo for the <hi>Publique Good;</hi> this muſt be the <hi>End.</hi> They muſt tend to the maintaining of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> (as of <hi>Verity</hi>) theſe muſt not be ſeparated) <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Decency,</hi> to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting of <hi>Scandal,</hi> without <hi>Impoſitions</hi> upon <hi>Conſcience,</hi> or the <hi>infringing</hi> of the purchaſed <hi>Liberty</hi> thereof: Elſe to <hi>Obey</hi> Eccleſiaſtical <hi>Canons,</hi> were not (believe it)<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> Jun. Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madv. <hi>in</hi> Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm. <hi>controv. 3. lib. 4. cap.</hi> 16. Item <hi>Theſ. Theol. de lib. Chriſt. Theſ.</hi> 11. Tilen. <hi>Synt. part. 2. diſp. 27. Theſ.</hi> 39. Item <hi>Theſ.</hi> 9. Alſted. <hi>Theol. Caſ. cap.</hi> 2. Hoſpin. <hi>de Orig. Feſt. Chriſt. cap.</hi> 2. Bez. <hi>Conf. cap. 5. art</hi> 16. Paraeum, <hi>comment. in</hi> 1 Cor. 14. Calvin. <hi>Inſtit. lib. 4. cap. 10. ſect.</hi> 32. Item <hi>Reſp. ad lib. de</hi> Pii viri officio, <hi>pag.</hi> 413. Prof. Leid. <hi>Synt. pur. Theol. Diſp. 35. Theſ.</hi> 19. Jus Canon. <hi>decret. part. 1. dict. 61. c.</hi> 8. Perkins Treat. <hi>of</hi> Conſ. <hi>cap. 2. ſect.</hi> 8. &amp;c.</note> CANONICAL OBEDIENCE.</p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:29874:36"/>
            <p>As touching <hi>Civil Laws.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are <hi>bound in Conſcience</hi> to obſerve the <hi>Magiſtrates Commandments.</hi> Though we are not <hi>bound in Conſcience</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quamvis ad Juſtas Leges humanas, juſto modo obſervandas, obligentur homines in Conſcientiis ſuis a Deo; ipſe tamen Leges humanae, qua ſunt Leges hominum, non obligant Conſcientiam.</hi> Ameſ. de Conſ. lib. 1. cap. 2.</note> BY thoſe Commandments, <hi>as ſuch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obedience (Active</hi> or <hi>Paſſive</hi>) to the <hi>Magiſtrates com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands</hi> is <hi>neceſſary;</hi> though not <hi>Neceſſitate conſequentis,</hi> yet <hi>Neceſſitate conſequentiae;</hi> that is, Though they are not <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligatory</hi> to <hi>Conſcience</hi> (<note n="*" place="margin">Proſ. Leid. <hi>Synt. pur. Theol. Diſp. 35. Theſ. 39.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>primo</hi> &amp; per ſe) <hi>primarily, direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> and by vertue of any <hi>Genuine binding</hi> power <hi>In them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> and <hi>as ſuch;</hi> yet they are <hi>binding</hi> by vertue of 1. The <hi>Lawfulneſs</hi> of the <hi>matter</hi> commanded; and 2. <hi>God's</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Exod. 20. 12. Rom. 13. 1, 2. 1 Pet. 2. 13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>General Precept</hi> touching <hi>indiſpenſable Obedience (Active</hi> or <hi>Paſſive</hi>) to the <hi>Magiſtrates Commandments.</hi> In which reſpect we muſt <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 13. 5.</note> 
               <hi>be ſubject even for Conſcience ſake.</hi> Thus, though this, <hi>viz. The lawful Commandments of the Magiſtrate are neceſſarily to be obeyed,</hi> is not <hi>true</hi> by the <hi>ſimple neceſſity</hi> of the <hi>Conſequent,</hi> as an <hi>Axiome</hi> and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple manifeſt of it ſelf, or by a <hi>ſimply neceſſary</hi> Connexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on between the <hi>Antecedent</hi> and <hi>Conſequent,</hi> or <hi>Subject</hi> and <hi>Predicate, viz. The Lawful Commandments of the Magiſtrate,</hi> and <hi>Neceſſary Obedience.</hi> Yet, it is <hi>true</hi> by the<note place="margin">In Divinis ad <hi>Praecipientem,</hi> In Humanis ad <hi>Praeceptum</hi> reſpiciendum eſt.</note> 
               <hi>neceſſity</hi> of <hi>conſequence,</hi> that is, ſuch a <hi>neceſſity</hi> as may be ſoundly concluded from the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> wherein <hi>Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> to the <hi>Lawful Commandments</hi> of Magiſtrates is <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſably commanded;</hi> ſo that it is a <hi>Concluſion</hi> manifeſt by <hi>Diſcourſe;</hi> and thus, upon theſe Premiſes, <hi>viz. 1. That all lawful Commandments of Magiſtrates are neceſſarily by vertue of God's Commandment to be obeyed.</hi> And 2. <hi>That this or that is a lawful Command of the Magiſtrate.</hi> It will follow <hi>Neceſſitate conſequentiae,</hi> That <hi>This or that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment of the Magiſtrate, is neceſſarily to be obeyed.</hi> In a word,</p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:29874:37"/>
            <p>There be two things which oblige us to obey the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates</hi> Commandments. 1. The one is, the <hi>Matter</hi> of the <hi>Human</hi> Precept, which muſt be <hi>Conſonant,</hi> at leaſt, not <hi>Repugnant</hi> to the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> 2. The other is, The <hi>Authority</hi> of the <hi>Divine</hi> Precept, wherein (as hath been ſaid) <hi>Indiſpenſable Obedience</hi> to the <hi>Lawful Commandments</hi> of <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> is enjoyned.</p>
            <p>From what hath been ſaid, it is evident, That</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Human Laws</hi> are <hi>Obligatory</hi> and <hi>Authentique,</hi> only by vertue of the <hi>Law of God;</hi> their <hi>binding</hi> Power being purely <hi>Mutuatitious.</hi> We are to <hi>obey</hi> the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> and all that are in <hi>Authority,</hi> ſo far forth, as that in obeying <hi>them</hi> we obey <hi>God;</hi> the Great <hi>Law-giver. Vid.</hi> Alſted. <hi>Theol. Caſ. cap.</hi> 2. Prof. Leid. <hi>Synt. pur. Theol. Diſp. 35. Theſ.</hi> 19. But</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quaeſt.</hi> What if the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> command things which <hi>Conſcience</hi> will not ſuffer to conform unto?</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> 1. <hi>Subjection</hi> to <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> and <hi>Loyalty</hi> is an <hi>Indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable duty;</hi> It is very obſervable, that none of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles did more urge and enforce that Duty, then S. <hi>Paul</hi> did, though he was a Subject to the greateſt <hi>Tyrant</hi> that ever lived, namely that Monſter of Mankinde, <hi>Nero Caeſar,</hi> who was the Author of the * <hi>Firſt Perſecution,</hi> and is called<note place="margin">Nero <hi>ex Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaribus primus in Chriſtianos diſtrinxit gla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium.</hi>
               </note> by <note n="*" place="margin">Apolog. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Tertullian, Dedicator Damnationis Noſtrae,</hi> the <hi>firſt</hi> that made a Law to condemn <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to death.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is (according to ſome of the Learned) a great difference between <hi>Subjection</hi> and <hi>Obedience; Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection</hi> (ſaith <note n="*" place="margin">Of the Church. <hi>lib. 4. cap. 34.</hi>
               </note> D. <hi>Field</hi>) is generally and abſolutely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, where <hi>Obedience</hi> is not; as when <hi>Conſcience</hi> ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers not a Man (<hi>Actively</hi>) to <hi>Obey,</hi> yet <hi>Duty</hi> leads him (by <hi>Paſſive</hi> Obedience) to <hi>ſubmit</hi> and ſubject himſelf to Authority; and thus the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Rom. 13. 1. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 1 Pet. 2. 13.</note> Greek word notes <hi>Submiſſion</hi> or <hi>Subjection</hi> in Scripture; which is much to be obſerved, leſt in ſtead of <hi>ſubmitting,</hi> Men either (by <hi>Active</hi> Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience)
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:29874:37"/> 
               <hi>conform</hi> contrary to <hi>Conſcience,</hi> or (which <hi>Piety</hi> abhors) <hi>rebel</hi> contrary to <hi>duty.</hi> Thus, had I been an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Note,</hi> It is one thing to obey <hi>Nero</hi> the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate,</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to obey <hi>Nero's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment.</hi>
               </note> Magiſtrate under <hi>Nero,</hi> and by him commanded to execute that curſed Edict of his, touching the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning of Chriſtians to death, I would not have (<hi>Active<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) obeyed</hi> him, neither would I have <hi>rebelled:</hi> What then? Why, I would have offered him my <hi>Neck</hi> (through <hi>paſſive</hi> ſtrength from the Almighty) not my <hi>hand.</hi> The ſame may be ſaid in reſpect of the contraverted <hi>Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies,</hi> when impoſed by Authority; though I cannot <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form</hi> to them, yet (through the Grace of God) I ſhall never <hi>rebel;</hi> but according to Scripture injunction, I will <hi>ſubmit to the Higher Power, whether it be to the</hi> KING<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>as Supream, or unto Governours, as unto them that are ſent by Him.</hi> Let men know then, that there is a <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> between <hi>Active Obedience</hi> and <hi>Rebellion,</hi> viz. SUB<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MISSION. The Lord forgive them that interpret <hi>Non-Conformity</hi> to the <hi>Mitre,</hi> to be no leſs, then <hi>Diſloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty</hi> to the <hi>Crown;</hi> The latter (I thank God) I am taught of him to abhor. Again,</p>
            <p n="3">3. I like well that diſtinction of <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Parker</hi> of the <hi>Croſs,</hi> cap. 5. ſect. 14, 15.</note> 
               <hi>Non Obedire,</hi> and <hi>Nolle Obedire;</hi> the one is no more then <hi>not to conform</hi> by <hi>Active</hi> Obedience. The other is, <hi>Obſtinate Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> and <hi>Contempt,</hi> which is ever to be avoided.</p>
            <p>But</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> How are <hi>Magiſtratical Injunctions</hi> in things <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different,</hi> and <hi>Indiſpenſable Obedience</hi> thereunto, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with <hi>Liberty of Conſcience?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>6. <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Limitations</hi> are not inconſiſtent. A <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Internal Liberty</hi> may very well conſiſt with <hi>Extrinſecal Limitations.</hi> That we may the better apprehend this, let us conſider, That</p>
            <p>There is a two-fold <hi>Reſtraint;</hi> namely,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. One upon the <hi>Conſcience</hi> and <hi>Inner</hi> Man.</item>
               <item>2. Another upon the <hi>Perſon,</hi> and <hi>Outward</hi> Man.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:29874:38"/>
            <p>Now,</p>
            <p>There may be a <hi>Reſtraint</hi> upon the <hi>Perſon,</hi> when (yet) there is no <hi>Conſtraint</hi> upon the <hi>Conſcience</hi> of a Man; and therefore we muſt diſtinguiſh between 1. The <hi>Right</hi> and <hi>Truth</hi> of <hi>Liberty,</hi> and 2. The <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> and <hi>Exerciſe</hi> of <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Libertas Conſcientiae,</hi> and <hi>Ligatio Conſcientiae</hi> (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c.) are inconſiſtent; <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience</hi> is oppoſed only to <hi>bond of Conſcience,</hi> not to an <hi>Extrinſecal Reſtraint</hi> of the <hi>Outward</hi> Man, in reſpect of the <hi>Exerciſe</hi> of our <hi>Liberty.</hi> Undoubtedly there may be a <hi>Reſtriction</hi> upon the <hi>Practice,</hi> or upon the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> as to the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of his <hi>Liberty;</hi> and yet 1. Nothing derogatory to the <hi>Indifferency</hi> of the thing <hi>in it ſelf.</hi> Nor 2. Any violence offered to the <hi>Internal</hi> and <hi>Real Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience;</hi> even as the <hi>Actus Imperati</hi> may be hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered or reſtrained, without any violence offered to the <hi>Actus Eliciti</hi> of the Soul. And thus, who doth doubt but that the <hi>King</hi> (our Dear and Dread Soveraigne) may on a <hi>Civil</hi> account, for the <hi>publick good</hi> of his Kingdoms, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn his Subjects <hi>abſtinence</hi> from <hi>ſuch and ſuch Meats,</hi> &amp;c. Now, here were a <hi>Reſtraint</hi> upon <hi>Perſons,</hi> in reſpect of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> and <hi>Exerciſe</hi> of their <hi>Liberty;</hi> and yet no vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence offered (upon the Kings part) to the <hi>Internal Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience;</hi> for though the <hi>Outward</hi> Man is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained by the <hi>Civil</hi> Sword, yet the <hi>Inner</hi> Man, and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> is left <hi>free;</hi> that is, My <hi>Conſcience</hi> is not <hi>bound</hi> by the <hi>Magiſtrates Commandment,</hi> though I be <hi>bound in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> by vertue of the <hi>Law of God,</hi> to yeild <hi>Obedience</hi> to that Commandment, the matter thereof being a thing <hi>Indifferent,</hi> and (therefore) <hi>lawful.</hi> Though I be tyed up by the <hi>Command</hi> as to <hi>practice,</hi> yet my <hi>Conſcience</hi> is ſtill <hi>free,</hi> while I am perſwaded in <hi>Conſcience</hi> that the thing is <hi>in it ſelf Indifferent:</hi> Why may not I give my <hi>neck</hi> to my <hi>King,</hi> and yet keep my <hi>Conſcience</hi> for my <hi>God?</hi> Why may not I yeild my <hi>Outward Man</hi> to the <hi>Civil Sce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter</hi> of the <hi>King, Qui (vel) Nolentibus praeeſt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Jerome,</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:29874:38"/> and yet reſigne my <hi>Inner</hi> Man to the <hi>Divine Scepter</hi> of my <hi>God,</hi> to whom appertains <hi>Interior Animae Gubernatio,</hi> as <note n="*" place="margin">Inſtit. lib. 4. cap. 10. ſect. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Calvin</hi> words it?</p>
            <p>The ſame may be ſaid in reſpect of <hi>Cloathing.</hi> Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the <hi>King</hi> may for the good of his <hi>Subjects,</hi> on ſome emergent occaſions, confine them to one kinde of <hi>Cloath,</hi> one kinde of <hi>Colour,</hi> one kinde of <hi>Habit,</hi> while neither <hi>Conſcience</hi> is <hi>impoſed</hi> upon, nor a <hi>Religious</hi> account ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged; for the <hi>Reſtraint</hi> would in ſuch a caſe be; not upon the <hi>Conſcience,</hi> while it is ſtill perſwaded of the <hi>Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency</hi> of the thing in <hi>it ſelf,</hi> and that it is not urged on a <hi>Religious,</hi> but a <hi>Civil</hi> account, and for the <hi>Weal-Publique;</hi> but only upon <hi>Perſons</hi> in reſpect of the <hi>Indifferent Exerciſe</hi> of their <hi>Liberty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Once more,</p>
            <p>What reaſon is there to doubt but that the <hi>King</hi> may for the <hi>Publique Good</hi> of his Kingdoms, tye his Subjects to eat <hi>Swines fleſh</hi> for ſome weeks, once a year? Yea, (and as the occaſion ſhall vary) at other times to <hi>abſtain</hi> from <hi>Swines fleſh</hi> for ſome weeks? Now, here were a <hi>Reſtraint</hi> upon the <hi>Perſon</hi> in reſpect of the <hi>Exerciſe</hi> of his <hi>Liberty,</hi> and yet none upon the <hi>Conſcience</hi> in reſpect of the <hi>Reality</hi> of his <hi>Liberty,</hi> while he is perſwaded in Conſcience, that the thing is <hi>Indifferent</hi> in <hi>it ſelf,</hi> and in reſpect of the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> though now it ceaſeth to be <hi>Indifferent</hi> in its <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> by reaſon of the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Man,</hi> viz. the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> whoſe Commandments in things <hi>Indifferent</hi> we are bound in Conſcience to obſerve.</p>
            <p>All which, that we may the better underſtand, let us conſider, That</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Chriſtian Liberty</hi> in reſpect of things <hi>Indifferent,</hi> conſiſts, <hi>in uſu vel abſtinentia,</hi> (ſaith <note n="*" place="margin">Synt. Theol. lib. 6. cap. 33.</note> 
               <hi>Polanus); tam in abſtinendo, quam in utendo</hi> (ſaith <note n="*" place="margin">Inſtit. <hi>lib. 3. cap. 19. ſect. 10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Calvin); in uſe</hi> or <hi>abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence,</hi> indifferently. Now</p>
            <p n="2">2. Here is <hi>Liberty,</hi> namely, That I may with a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience <hi>free</hi> from all <hi>Divine Obligation</hi> to the contrary,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:29874:39"/> obſerve <hi>Human Conſtitutions</hi> made, <hi>pro re nata,</hi> upon va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious (yea contrary) occaſions emergent, for the <hi>Publique Good,</hi> that is, the good of that <hi>City, Kingdom</hi> or <hi>Body-Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick,</hi> whereof I am a <hi>Member.</hi> For inſtance, Poſſibly it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary at one time, for the Publique good, that rhere be an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of <hi>Swines fleſh</hi> (it may be to ſave other <hi>Beaſts,</hi> or becauſe of exceſſive plenty) Now, by vertue of my <hi>Chriſtian Liberty,</hi> I may with a <hi>free</hi> Conſcience, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a Statute made by the Magiſtrate, for the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of <hi>Swines fleſh:</hi> A <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Magiſtrate might make no ſuch Law. Again, poſſibly it is as neceſſary at another time that there be an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Abſtinence</hi> from <hi>Swines fleſh,</hi> (it may be for <hi>Healths</hi> ſake, or <hi>ſcarcity,</hi> &amp;c.) Now by vertue of my <hi>Chriſtian Liberty,</hi> I may with a <hi>free</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience obſerve a Statute made by the Magiſtrate, (upon a quite contrary occaſion <hi>viz.</hi>) for an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Abſtinence</hi> from <hi>Swines fleſh,</hi> &amp;c. Whither we <hi>uſe</hi> or <hi>abſtain,</hi> the <hi>Conſcience</hi> is never the leſs <hi>free;</hi> yea, therefore becauſe we are <hi>free; libera Conſcientia (utimur vel) abſtinemus,</hi> we <hi>uſe</hi> or <hi>forbear</hi> with a <hi>free Conſcience. Vid.</hi> Calvin. <hi>Inſtit. lib. 3. cap. 19. Sect.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>Nay,</p>
            <p>By vertue of my <hi>Liberty,</hi> I may <hi>abridge</hi> my ſelf of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty. By vertue of the undoubted <hi>Reality</hi> of it, I may <hi>limit</hi> my ſelf as to the <hi>Indifferent uſe</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>Here is <hi>Liberty,</hi> that I may <hi>freely</hi> impoſe a <hi>Neceſſity</hi> upon my Liberty, <note n="*" place="margin">Calv. Inſtit. <hi>lib. 4. cap. 10. ſect. 32.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quatenus <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, aut Charitatis ratio exigit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here is <hi>Liberty,</hi> namely, That (notwithſtanding the <hi>Indifferency</hi> of things in themſelves, yet) I may <hi>freely tye</hi> my ſelf <hi>to,</hi> or <hi>from ſuch</hi> and <hi>ſuch meats</hi> or <hi>ſuch</hi> and <hi>ſuch Cloaths,</hi> in reſpect of <hi>Decency</hi> or <hi>Charity,</hi> or warrantable <hi>Congruity</hi> and <hi>Pleaſingneſs</hi> to my own minde, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally,</p>
            <p>They are much miſtaken, who think that the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates <hi>Impoſition</hi> in a thing <hi>Indifferent,</hi> takes away, or <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringeth
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:29874:39"/> Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience;</hi> for who knows not that This is a thing <hi>Indifferent,</hi> namely, to begin <hi>Sabbathical Duties</hi> at <hi>four</hi> or <hi>ſix</hi> a clock in the morning? I prove it, (Though, the <hi>Obſervance</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian Sabbath</hi> be of <hi>Indiſpenſable Neceſſity,</hi> (I am no <hi>Anti-Sabbatarian,</hi> yet) to begin the <hi>Sabbath then,</hi> is neither <hi>Forbidden</hi> nor <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded;</hi> to begin it <hi>then,</hi> or <hi>ſooner,</hi> or ſomwhat <hi>later,</hi> is not <hi>repugnant</hi> to the <hi>Word, Ergo,</hi> &amp;c. Now, May not the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> tye me (yea, and all his other Subjects) to <hi>ſix</hi> or <hi>four</hi> a Clock in the morning for the beginning of the <hi>Sabbath?</hi> Yes, That he may; and yet ſay, if in ſo doing, he doth infringe <hi>Chriſtian Liberty.</hi> No <hi>Impoſition</hi> is repugnant to <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> but <hi>Impoſition</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Conſcience.</hi> What I have ſaid doth not at all counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> ſince (as is evident from what hath been ſaid above) they are juſtly denyed to be <hi>Matters</hi> of <hi>Indifferency,</hi> (about which <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience</hi> is moſt properly Converſant.) I would they would decide the Controverſie, by their, unheard of, <hi>Achillean</hi> proofs. <hi>Parturiunt montes &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus I have endeavoured to ſhew (which is a difficult theame to ſuch a raw head) how the <hi>Magiſtrates Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> in things <hi>Indifferent;</hi> &amp; <hi>Neceſſary Obedience</hi> thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to are conſiſtent with <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Boundaries</hi> or <hi>Rules</hi> of <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> follow, which may be ſaid to be five. <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Piety;</hi> This is <hi>Loyalty</hi> to God, ſpecified, 1 <hi>Cor. 10. 31. Whether therefore ye eat or drink, or whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever</hi>
               <note place="margin">See <hi>Rom. 14. 7, 8 Etiam illaeacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones quae ſunt ſua natura Adt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aphorae debent tamen a Chriſtianis fieri in nomine Chriſti, hoc eſt juxta voluntatem Chriſti, &amp; ad gloriam Chriſti.</hi> D. Davenant in locum.</note> 
               <hi>ye doe, doe all to the Glory of God.</hi> The <hi>End</hi> of our <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi> is Gods GLORY; this ſhould be the <hi>Scope</hi> of all our <hi>Actions,</hi> even of <hi>Indifferent</hi> ones. Our <hi>Own Good</hi> is <hi>ſubordinate</hi> not <hi>co-ordinate</hi> to <hi>That.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:29874:40"/>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Loyalty.</hi> This is injoyned <hi>Subjection</hi> to the <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate,</hi> who is (as it were) Gods <hi>Vice-Roy</hi> here on earth in reſpect of the <hi>Civil Sword</hi> entruſted by the <hi>King of</hi>
               <note place="margin">See <hi>Rom. 13. 1, 2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Kings</hi> to him; <hi>Submit your ſelves</hi> (ſaith <hi>Peter) to every Ordinance of Man for the Lords ſake, whether it be to the King as Supreame,</hi> &amp;c. 1 Pet. 2. 13, 14.—<hi>as free,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>v.</hi> 16. Obſerve, <hi>As free,</hi> there is <hi>Liberty;</hi> but yet <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit</hi> AS <hi>free;</hi> there is a <hi>Limitation.</hi> Then ours is a <hi>Limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Liberty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Charity.</hi> By this we are reſtrained from the <hi>uſe</hi> of any thing from whence <hi>ſcandall</hi> and juſt offence might ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crue to <hi>weak Brethren. Take heed</hi> (ſaith our Apoſtle) <hi>leſt by any meanes this Liberty of yours become a ſtumbling block to the weak.</hi> 1 Cor. 8. 9. <hi>It is good neither to eat fleſh, nor to drink Wine, nor any thing whereby thy brother ſtumbleth, or is offended, or made weak.</hi> Rom. 14. 21. Hence ſaid S. <hi>Paul, If meat make my Brother to offend</hi> (or ſtumble) <hi>I will eat no fleſh while the World ſtands.</hi> 1 Cor. 8. 13. <hi>Cum charitas ſemper ſit colenda, ſcandala ſemper ſunt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanda,</hi> ſaid <note n="*" place="margin">Synt. part. 2 diſp. 27. Theſſ. 31.</note> 
               <hi>Tilenus.</hi> Since <hi>Charity</hi> is ever to be enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, <hi>Scandal</hi> is ever to be avoyded. By vertue of this <hi>Law of Charity</hi> we are tyed not only <hi>from</hi> the uſe of what might prove <hi>Scandalous</hi> and <hi>Offenſive</hi> to weak Brethren, but alſo <hi>to</hi> the uſe and purſuance of ſuch things as are <note n="†" place="margin">Vid. Par. in 1 Cor. 10. 23. Vid. Calvin Inſtit. lib. 3. cap. 19. ſect. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Expedient</hi> and <hi>Ediſicatory. Let us therefore follow after the things which make for peace, and things wherewith one may edifie another.</hi> Rom. 14. 19. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> Is there not ſometimes a <hi>repugnancy</hi> between the Law of <hi>Charity</hi> and the Law of <hi>Loyalty:</hi> as when the Magiſtrate <hi>commands</hi> That, which if we ſhould <hi>obſerve,</hi> we ſhould <hi>offend</hi> and <hi>ſcandalize</hi> the <hi>weak?</hi> Let us ſuppoſe, the Magiſtrate to enjoyne a <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> to be read; If I ſhould read it, I ſhould <hi>ſcandalize weak Chriſtians;</hi> if I ſhould not read it, I ſhould ſeem to <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey</hi> the <hi>Magiſtrate;</hi> what ſhall I doe in ſuch a caſe? I muſt not <hi>ſcandalize</hi> him <hi>for whom Chriſt dyed;</hi> I but nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther muſt I <hi>diſobey</hi> the <hi>Magiſtrate.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:29874:40"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Doctrine of Chriſtian Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty.</note> Dr. <hi>Downame,</hi> preſents us with This, as an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient in this caſe of ſeeming <hi>Antinomy;</hi> namely, That if we anſwer or obey the <hi>Superiour Law,</hi> viz. that concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> the <hi>Inferiour,</hi> viz. that concerning the <hi>weak Brethren</hi> (which giveth place to the other) is not <hi>broken</hi> or <hi>diſobeyed,</hi> &amp;c. And I muſt confeſſe there is much in it, and I can but commend the D<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Invention; but yet under favour,</p>
            <p n="2">2. There had been more in it, if this had been ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, namely, That not only the <hi>Magiſtrates Command</hi> but alſo his <hi>Conſcience</hi> comes in competition with the weak Brothers <hi>Conſcience;</hi> that is, If the Magiſtrate himſelf had been ſuppoſed to be of a <hi>tender Conſcience.</hi> For then, we ſhould ſeem by gratifying others, not only to <hi>diſobey</hi> the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> but alſo to <hi>offend</hi> and <hi>ſcandalize</hi> his <hi>ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Conſcience.</hi> However,</p>
            <p n="3">3. Since I am ſo <hi>weak</hi> as not to pick ſatisfaction here, I ſhould betake my ſelf to <hi>Paſſive Obedience:</hi> I dare not <hi>conforme</hi> by <hi>Active Obedience,</hi> for then I ſhould <hi>with my</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 14. 15.</note> 
               <hi>meat deſtroy him for whom Chriſt dyed.</hi> I dare not out of a reſpect to the <hi>Conſciences</hi> of <hi>Inferiour</hi> Chriſtians oppoſe or contemne <hi>Authority;</hi> God forbid. <hi>Rebellion</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> my principles could never yet reconcile; and I have ever thought, that it is not only <hi>ſinne,</hi> but even a <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quod ad ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalum atimet.</hi> Vid. Magde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg. Cent. 1. lib. 2. cap. 4. col. 441. Aug. Epiſt. 36. ad Caſul. Zanch. de Imag. Pag. 390. Chemnit. exam. part. 1. pag. 179. Par. in Rom. 14. dub. 1. Calv. Inſtit. lib. 3. cap. 19. ſect. 11, 12, 13. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> to labour with <hi>Anti-Magiſtraticall</hi> Principles. Therefore I would chuſe that which I am perſwaded in Conſcience, to be the <hi>pars tutior,</hi> the ſafer way; namely, to <hi>Submit:</hi> this is <hi>Paſſive Obedience;</hi> whereby I ſhall hope to eſhun both the one and the other evill.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Purity.</hi> This is another <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>Boundary</hi> of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Conſcience, which is mentioned <hi>Rom. 14. 14. I am perſwaded that there is nothing uncleane</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>of it ſelf,</hi> there is <hi>Liberty; but to him that eſteemeth any thing to be uncleane, to him it is uncleane;</hi> there is a <hi>Limitation. He
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:29874:41"/> that doubteth is damned if he eateth, becauſe he eateth not of faith, for what is not of faith is ſinne.</hi> Rom. 14. 23. That<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In this caſe the</hi> Magiſtrate <hi>may</hi> Command lawfully, <hi>and (yet) the</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject obey ſin fully.</note> is, if a man be not fully <hi>perſwaded</hi> of the <hi>Lawfullneſs</hi> of what he doth, he <hi>ſins:</hi> Hence ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Let eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man be fully perſwaded in his own mind;</hi> Rom. 14. 5. This is that <hi>Plerophory</hi> of Conſcience without which a thing is <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nclean</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawfull</hi> to us, though it be <hi>Lawfull</hi> in its own Nature. Hence ſaith <note n="*" place="margin">In Rom. 14. 7, 8. Vid. <hi>Calv.</hi> in v. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Calvin, Nefas omnino eſt quipptam aggredi quod putes (Domino) diſplicere, imo quod non perſuaſus fis illi placere;</hi> It is <hi>unlawfull</hi> for thee to attempt any thing which thou thinkeſt may <hi>diſpleaſe</hi> God, yea, which thou doſt not <hi>perſwade</hi> thy ſelf to be a thing that will <hi>pleaſe</hi> God. Thus, If a thing ſhould be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn'd whereof (though) I could queſtion neither the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition</hi> nor the <hi>Impoſition;</hi> (yet) if I ſhould <hi>uſe</hi> or attempt it <hi>againſt</hi> or with a <hi>Reluctancy</hi> of, <hi>Conſcience</hi> I ſhould ſin; For <note n="*" place="margin">Vid. Calv. in Rom. 14. 5. Alſted. Theol. Caſ. cap. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Quicquid fit repugnante Conſcientia peccatum eſt,</hi> whatever is done <hi>contrary</hi> to the <hi>Voyce, Dictates</hi> and <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> that <hi>Boſome-Guide,</hi> is a <hi>ſin:</hi> yea, The <note n="†" place="margin">Vid. <hi>Hem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming.</hi> Enchyr. Claſſ. 2. cap. 7. <hi>Aquin.</hi> 1. 2. Queſt. 19. Art. 5. Tanner. Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit. to 2 in 12. diſp. 2. q. 4. dub. 2. n. 21. Baldwin. de Conſ. Caſ. lib. 1. cap. 7. Ameſ. de Conſ. lib. 1. cap. 4. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Learned tell us that in things <hi>Indifferent</hi> (at leaſt), even an <hi>Erroneous</hi> Conſcience <hi>ligat,</hi> though <hi>non obligat.</hi> It <hi>binds,</hi> by a <hi>Negative tye;</hi> that is, though we are not <hi>obliged</hi> to <hi>do</hi> what it <hi>preſcribeth,</hi> yet we are <hi>bound not to do</hi> what it <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth</hi> or <hi>forbiddeth.</hi> The reaſon whereof muſt be, the <hi>Repreſentation</hi> of the <hi>Will</hi> of God therein; for an <hi>Errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Conſcience</hi> judgeth it ſelf to act by <hi>Rule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Sobriety.</hi> This is another <hi>Boundary</hi> of <hi>Liberty of Conſcience. Brethren</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>ye are called to liberty, only uſe not your liberty as an occaſion to the fleſh.</hi> Gal. 5. 13. That were to paſſe the bounds of <hi>Sobriety, Temperance, Humility, Frugality, Modeſty,</hi> &amp;c. That were not a <hi>holy Liberty</hi> but a <hi>ſinfull Licentiouſneſſe.</hi> That were not the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> but the <hi>Abuſe</hi> of our Liberty. Theſe are the <hi>Bounds</hi> of our <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:29874:41"/>
            <p>And thus I have diſpatched the laſt ſtep of <hi>Chriſtian Liberty;</hi> and the firſt <hi>Capitall</hi> Priviledge, <hi>viz. Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> O how doth it concerne us, to contend for what Chriſt hath procured! <hi>Periculoſum eſt in divinis rebus ut quis cedat jure ſuo,</hi> ſaid <hi>Cyprian,</hi> de Haeret. baptiz. vid. Par. Comment. in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 23. Tilen. Synt. part 2. diſp. 44. Theſ. 33.</p>
            <p>The other great <hi>Evangelicall</hi> Priviledge is, <hi>Adoption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One great deſigne of the Son of God, in aſſuming to himſelf our Nature, was; <hi>That we might</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>receive the Adoption of Sons.</hi> Here is noted the <hi>filial</hi> ſtate of the <hi>Church;</hi> not, but that all the <hi>Saints</hi> in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, were <hi>Sons,</hi> but becauſe the condition of the <hi>Jewiſh Church</hi> conſidered as a <hi>Collective Body,</hi> was by reaſon of the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Non dixit Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolus,</hi> accipia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, <hi>ſed,</hi> reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piamus, <hi>ut ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificaret hoc nos amiſiſſe in Adam ex quo mortales ſumus.</hi> Aug. in loc.</note> YOKE of <hi>Rites</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> more <hi>ſervile</hi> then that of the <hi>Chriſtian Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Adoption</hi> is that Evangelicall Priviledge, wherein the <hi>Naturall</hi> Sons of ſinfull <hi>Men,</hi> become the <hi>Adoptive</hi> Sons of the Living <hi>God.</hi> It is peculiar to <hi>Beleevers,</hi> the Lords <hi>Redeemed</hi> ones. <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the <hi>Son</hi> of God by <hi>Naturall, Eternall,</hi> and <hi>Ineffable Generation, Angels</hi> are <hi>Sons</hi> of God by <hi>Creation;</hi> but <hi>Men</hi> (viz. <hi>Believers</hi>) are <hi>Sons</hi> of God by <hi>Adoption.</hi> There be two great and admirable truths in the Text.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Here, The <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>God</hi> became the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>Man. God ſent forth his Son made of a Woman.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. Here, The <hi>Sons</hi> of <hi>Men</hi> became the <hi>Sons</hi> of <hi>God. That we might receive the Adoption of Sons.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Chryſ. <hi>in Joh. cap 1.</hi>
               </note> The <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>God</hi> became the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>Man,</hi> that the <hi>Sons</hi> of <hi>Men</hi> might become the <hi>Sons</hi> of <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:29874:42"/>
            <p>O what Comfort is this to <hi>Redeemed</hi> Ones! what? that <hi>Slaves</hi> ſhould become <hi>Sons!</hi> that ſuch as are <hi>by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the children of wrath,</hi> ſhould through Grace, become<note place="margin">Eph. 2. 3.</note> the <hi>Children</hi> of the <hi>Moſt High God!</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This Theame doth well deſerve another Treatiſe; but I muſt conclude.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 4. Here is a <hi>Motive</hi> to <hi>Thankfullneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here is the moſt quickening Motive to <hi>Gratitude, Praiſe,</hi> and <hi>Thanksgiving,</hi> that Heaven can afford to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind: What? That <hi>the Son of God ſhould be made of a woman,</hi> for the <hi>Redemption, Adoption, Salvation</hi> of <hi>Sinners! Angels</hi> payed a <hi>Tribute</hi> of <hi>Praiſe</hi> for this Contrivance; <hi>Glory to God in the higheſt,</hi> ſaid they. Surely <hi>Men</hi> are much<note place="margin">Luk. 2. 14.</note> more concerned, ſince God <hi>took not upon him the Nature of Angells but the Seed of Abraham.</hi> O Let <hi>Men</hi> hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth<note place="margin">Heb. 2. 16.</note> become <hi>Tributaries</hi> to the moſt High God! bleſſe God Chriſtians, write a <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>thankfullneſs</hi> upon your <hi>hearts,</hi> and Copy it out in your <hi>Lives.</hi> Bleſſe God <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives,</hi> here is a <hi>Redeemer!</hi> Bleſſe God <hi>Sinners,</hi> here is a <hi>Saviour!</hi> One of your own <hi>fleſh</hi> and <hi>blood!</hi> O let us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin our <hi>eternall</hi> work, where I end. I dare ſay, this is a Theame, which <hi>ten thouſand times ten thouſand and thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 5. 11.</note> 
               <hi>of thouſands,</hi> even the whole Hoſt of Heaven will with <hi>praiſes</hi> Celebrate and Comment upon to all <hi>Eternity.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:29874:42"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
